Hello everyone and welcome to this lecture on time stamps.
So in this lecture run to learn how to use time stamps what there are and keep in mind that different
sequel engines such as My sequel Oracle may use slightly different syntax so you may need to refer to
the online documentation necessary but we're going to try to show you the most basic and transferable
syntax as far as extracting time information from a time stamp object.
So sequel allows us to use the time stamp data type to retain time information as we've seen in a lot
of the tables such as Date Created or payment's dates.
That kind of thing later on we're going to learn how to actually create time stamped columns when we
go over creating data and creating tables.
But for now let's focus on extracting information from time stamp objects.
So the extract function allows us to extract parts from a date and the syntax basically looks like extract
.
And in parentheses unit from date and we can extract many types of time based information from a time
stamp or date or time objects.
So here's a giant table all the different types of units you can extract from a time stamp object.
So for example you can extract day from that time stamp and return the day of the month.
You can do day of the week day of the year millennium's millisecond centuries etc..
There's a lot of information and different types of things you can extract or a time stamp object.
So you can refer to the documentation for all the units and I'll show you the link later on before we
jump to PGE admin.
Or you can just google search postscripts sequel date time or postgresql equal time stamp or Mystikal
date time or whatever sequel engine you're using plus date time or time.
So let's go out and see some quick examples of extracts to get a better understanding of how it works
.
Before we hopped PGE admin I'm going to go ahead and show you that post gresse sequel documentation
page.
Let's go ahead and go to it now.
OK so here we are at the post gresse sequel documentation page.
And notice if you just google search post-career sequels plus date time etc. or date or time.
Most often it'll take you straight to this page as the first hit and it will basically give you a list
of date time functions and operators.
So we're going to focus on extract function in this lecture but I also wanted to let you know that you
can use earth medic operator such as Plus or times with date time objects.
So for example if we scroll down here if I wanted to use the plus operator on some dates I could say
something like this which has dates on this string which converts to a time stamp Plus the integer of
seven string which converts it to the integer 7 and that will add days to your time stamp perforation
.
So this is 2001 month 9 day 28.
And if I add 7 to it it's going to return 2001 month 10 days 5 or the fifth.
So just keep that in mind later on if you find yourself needing to do this sort of operations you can
reference back to STATE time documentation.
You can do the same thing with subtraction.
You can trip subtract time intervals or basically add time intervals to various time stamp informations
.
OK.
So this is pretty useful stuff in case you want to add or subtract from your current date and you can
also multiply by intervals to get larger chunks at time.
This really depends on what your data looks like and we're trying to accomplish as far as the actual
use cases.
So let you reference the documentation when you need it.
There's also date time functions which allow you to work and return things from a date time object.
So if we just zoom out here for a second we can grab things such as the current date or we can also
do things such as age which basically passen to time stamps and all return the interval between them
which is basically just doing the same thing as subtract.
So takes one time stamp subtracts another time stamp and it's the age or the interval between them.
So for example it gives you something like this for three years nine months and 27 days between these
two timestamps.
Again we're going to focus more on just using the extracts statement since we're focused right now more
on reading from a sequel table versus creating time stamp information.
So let's go ahead now and you can go ahead and check out these functions on your own time through the
documentation.
If you ever need to but we're going to go ahead and jump to PGA now to show you a couple of quick examples
of using extract.
So I'm going to go ahead and help the PGA out of it now.
OK.
So here we are at PGE admen.
I went ahead and selected all the columns from the payments tables to select Asterix from payments and
we were going to be dealing with here is the payments underscored date column.
So that's going to be the time stamp and no it doesn't have the actual time so.
Won't be able to grab time some information from it.
But let's go out and explore how we could use extract.
So let's just start off with getting the payment date.
Column itself.
So we're going to say something like this selects and let's go ahead and say select payments underscore
date from payments semi-colon.
Go ahead and run that.
And here's our payment date column.
And then the way we would use extract looks like this will say extract
princes around payment dates and then we're going to have a unit from the payment date.
So I can say extract day from the payment dates and the recent extract from our lower case here is so
that you don't get confused that you're extracting something from a table called payment date.
So here by conventional we're using from lower case.
So now I've been able to if I ran that I saw I have a list of days now.
So this is quite useful and we will be able to use this information when we want to filter by something
.
So for example I can select another column from the payment table if we go ahead and selects.
So sick customer id call them let's go ahead and run that and so now I have a customer ID and a date
part which is that day so we can actually say for example as in order to rename that so I can say something
like as they run that again.
And now I have days that column name.
OK so let's go ahead and see a real example of why doing extract would be useful.
Let's say I wanted to figure out the total amount expenditure by the month.
So how would I do that I could say something like this.
I know I have an amount column in here so I will sum the amount column and I'm going to extracts month
from the payment date and I will say extract this as month.
That way I can reference it as month later on that I'm going to say from payments and since I'm doing
an aggregate function of some I will need to group by month go ahead and run this.
And now we see the total sum.
And let's go ahead and order this by the amount
and we'll go in and say or actually order it by the sum of the amounts
run at 5 here and I can go ahead and put that in descending order and let's go ahead and limit this
to one.
And this basically answers the business task of how much did I get in payments of my highest grossing
month.
That's going to be month for January February March April.
So that's in April.
My total amount was twenty thousand five hundred fifty nine dollars and 46 cents.
So that's a really nice use case for using extract.
So here we're we're saying select the total sum of the amounts.
Extracts this month from payment day as month from the payment table.
Go ahead and group that by that month column that we just created order by the sum of the amount in
descending order unlimited by 1.
Something that might be useful here is just to say as total for that some amount column and then we
can say order by and sort of having it clarified by some amount we can go ahead and say order by total
.
And if we run that you'll get the same result.
OK.
So go ahead and reference the documentation for more stuff you can extract by Booch have just gotten
out of this lecture is how to use extract and how it's useful for queries that have to do with time
stamp your affirmation.
Again the syntax is just extract parentheses.
The units you want to extract and then from and then the column name and by convention we're going to
say this from it's lowercase.
So we don't get this column name confused if a table name.
OK with that being said that's it for this lecture.
Thanks and I'll see you at the next one