Hello everyone and welcome to the mathematical functions lecture in this lecture.
You're going to learn where you can find various mathematical functions available and post-career sequel
and they're We're going to see some basic examples.
Keep in mind most of the examples we're going to learn about will be available in whatever sequel engine
you're using.
But in the documentation you may be alerted to some specific post-career sequel functions.
Now sequel comes for a lot of mathematical operators built in that are very use for numeric column types
.
You can explore all of them in the documentation you can find that this link or you can just google
search postscripts sequel plus math and this will be the first link that pops up.
So you can go ahead and go to this link or just google search for postscripts sequel plus math and this
will be the first hit.
So it's good to explore that documentation and then we'll see some examples in Peachi admen and how
to actually use his mathematical operations and functions are going to go ahead and jump to the documentation
now.
OK so here we are at the documentation and something I want you to know is that there are a ton of mathematical
functions and operators way more than we have time to go over in this course and they're really outside
the scope of the course a lot of them.
So issues like coastline are signed and they're really not useful.
Given our data set but in case you do need them here's the documentation link so you can check them
out.
Again it's just that post-career sequela org slash talks slash.
In this case I'm looking at the latest version 9.5 slash static slash functions math.
Each Tamil or again.
Just google search post-career sequel plus math and this will be the link that shows up.
So we have basic mathematical operators available to us just plus minus multiplication and basically
anything else you can think of just square roots cube roots factorials cetera.
So if you have a numeric column types and you want to do mathematical operations on them you can with
the use of these operators and there's examples here as well as results.
Then there's also basic mathematical functions such as absolute values taking the ceiling of a number
meaning takes a small integer not less than the argument.
So here's an example of how you can use it.
There's degrees exponentials logarithmic operations PI power operations rounding operations you've actually
already seen this one.
Remember we had around the numbers.
OK.
And there's a ton of them here that you can go through if you need them.
There's also random operations that you can use to fill out random values or select random values.
Then there's also trigonometric functions as ArcSight inverse sine etc..
OK so let's go ahead and explore some of them are useful ones.
And then let's go ahead and hop to PGE admin to see that I'm going to go to hop to PGE admen now and
we'll explore a few of these useful mathematical functions and operators.
OK so I went ahead and opened up a sequel editor.
And what I'm going to do now is just explore a table and what kind of operations we can do on it.
So don't say select everything from the payment tables and say no there's payment numbers there.
OK.
So here we have the payment table we have a payment ID customer id staff id the rental id amount and
a payment date.
So just an example of how you can use the basic operators such as like a plus or minus or the vision
lets say we want to make a new ID for a specific event and that ID was going to be defined by the customer
ID and the rental ID so that specific event could have an ID.
This case we already have a payment ID is a specific event lets say you want to make one.
How can we do that.
We could just say take the customer and the add it to the rental ID and that will be that.
You bet.
Now you may have repetitive events in this manner but this is just a very basic example of how you could
use an addition argument here or an operator could say something like select customer id plus in this
case rental ID.
I will say as lets go ahead and define this as a new ID I will go ahead and select that from payments
.
Now if I run this will get this new ID which is an integer.
So we have this new ID for all the events of the payments.
So he just basically took the customer ID column and added the slightly column we could also multiply
them together and Ill do the mathematical operational allocation we can subtract them we can divide
them etc..
So heres a division in this case.
Notice how the vision by itself produced all zeros here.
If we take a look at the documentation just this division symbol by itself will be integer division
that truncates the result.
So this is happening because if we go ahead and change this to a comma basically everything is being
rounded down to zero because we have this small three digit integer being divided by this larger four
digit integer.
We went ahead and reversed it.
So we say Rensil ID divide it by a customer ID and ran that and put it are in there.
Then we start getting these actual new ID results.
That makes sense.
OK.
So those are the basics of the mathematical operators.
Let's go ahead and show you the basics of the mathematical function.
So if we go ahead and say select we'll go ahead and say avi for the average amount from payments for
the go ahead run that we get this average amount.
So its $4 and 20 something cents just as a reminder you could do something like round's which is a mathematical
operation and tag or insert whatever column or query you're putting into a round and then run that until
around that for you.
Remember we've actually seen this because we can add a second argument which will be how many decimal
places after the zero we want around to.
So in this case around the two places after this.
OK.
So again you can explore the documentation yourself if you're ever finding the need to perform mathematical
function.
This is lecture's main purpose is just to show you that they're available for you if you ever find yourself
needing them.
OK.
With that being said that's it for this lecture in the next lecture we're going to go ahead and explore
a couple more advance features of sequel.
Thanks everyone and I'll see you there.