Hello everyone and welcome to the string functions and operators lecture.
This lecture we're going learn where you can find various string functions available and post-career
sequel and then we're going to see some basic examples.
This is going to be almost like a sister lecture to the mathematical functions.
There's a ton of string functions and operators in post-career sequel as well it's just basic sequel
.
So what makes sense to go through all of them but what I want you to get out of this lecture is just
know that they're available to you and see some basic examples of them.
So like a mission sequel comes a lot of string operators already built in.
And you can explore all of them in the documentation at this link.
Or you can just basically Google search post-career sequel plus string functions and we'll take you
to this link as the first hit.
With that being said let's go ahead and jump to the documentation.
Explore and then see some basic examples.
We're going to go ahead and jump to the documentation now.
OK so here we are at the documentation.
It's under string functions and operators.
And basically here just like the mathematical function section you'll have a list of functions the type
of data it returns either text or integer description of what it does.
An example of it.
So just by coincidence my name is actually here and some of the examples.
And you can check out the examples yourself.
So some of these really useful ones can be just like concatenating strings together meaning putting
them together such as like post Chris sequel.
That's just these two bars here and there's a ton a ton of functions here for you to check out as well
as some other string functions for putting them in different Unicode in case you're familiar that at
all.
But you can go ahead and check all of these out.
We're going to go ahead and jump to P.G. admen as I scroll down and you can see there's a huge list
of them.
So let's go over through some of the most basic ones and some of the most useful ones.
OK.
I going to go ahead and jump to PGE Atman and open up a sequel Ed. there.
All right everybody so here I am at the sequel editor for P.J. admen.
The table we're going to be working with to see a couple of these string function examples is the customer
table.
So let's go out and selects all columns from customer them put semi color.
We're going to go ahead and run this.
And here's our data output and we have three columns here where the specific data type is character
.
So that means it's strings that we can play around with as far as the string functions.
So we have first name last name and e-mail.
Let's go out and play around of first name and last name first.
One of the most basic functions are string operators you can use is concatenation meaning kind of sticking
stuff together.
So let's go ahead and try that out.
I can take one column this case I'll say first name and concatenate it.
Basically sticking it together with the last name and the way I do that is by using these two vertical
bars.
So I say select first name these two vertical bars you can usually find them above your enter or return
key.
So shift and then that button there last name from customer let's go and see what that looks like around
that.
And notice here we have the first name of the customer the last name of the customer kind of squished
together meaning they've been concatenated together in order to make this look a little nicer.
Let's go ahead and put a space in between these names and then change the name column.
So a more useful example of what this would look like is if I took an empty string.
So just a single quote a space in a single quote and concatenated that in between the first and last
name so saying the first name column with concatenation of an empty string.
Number two vertical bars here and then the last name in column from customer.
And then I'm going to use aliasing which is just using that as statements to name this column we'll
call this column fool underscored name from all it comes from the customer.
Let's go ahead and run this.
And now we have this nice full name column the full name of the customer.
Jared alley Mary Smith etc. So this is kind of a real use case of when you may want to be using these
sort of string operators in order to figure stuff out like that.
So we have a full name here.
Let's go ahead and mess around with one other string function and that might be trying to figure out
how many characters a name has.
So we take a look at the first name column we have Jared and Mary Patricia Alynda as those first two
outputs.
Well we can do is use the function character length which is C H A R underscore length so c ha our underscore
length and pasan a column of characters.
In this case first name and if we run that will return.
How many characters are in that specific row for that column.
So another just basic string function we can do is like upper and lower so I can say like upper first
name and all that will do is return everything uppercase and you can do the same thing with lower dollar
turn everything lower case again as I showed in the documentation there's a ton a ton of string operators
of functions for you to explore.
So purify yourself needed to work with string functions operators or trying to use string functions
.
Let's say like a regular expression if that's something you're familiar with.
Basically trying to find patterns where it's just the simple like statement isn't enough for you.
You can go ahead and check out the documentation and if I go out and jump to it real quick I actually
have it open in a tab here.
We have string functions and operators zoom in a bit for more advanced users of sequel and more advanced
programmers in general.
You may want to check out regular expressions in sequel granted.
Make sure you reference your specific sequel's engines documentation in order to fully understand how
to use it.
But if we scroll down here you'll notice you have some regular expressions so that means basically you
can Passons stream columns and look for matches of certain words here and I'll tell you when they pop
up.
You can also do replacements etc..
And as another quick note there's actually a whole subsection of postscripts sequel's documentation
to explore regular expressions a little further.
So I encourage you to check this out.
In this specific documentation link.
If regular expressions is something you feel you're going to be using a lot.
Now again I always recommend trying to use something like like in order to use a regular expression
operator as far as a pattern matching scheme just because it's a lot simpler and easier to come back
to when you're reading your code later on.
But if you do need some more complicated tasks sequel and specifically postscripts sequel can support
that.
OK so I hope this you've gotten out of this lecture is just a general idea of what's possible with string
and functions and operators and you know what the documentation is in case you want a reference anything
later on for your own specific data sets either at home or at work.
OK thanks everyone and I will see you at the next lecture