Hello everyone and welcome to the lecture on sub query.
So we're going to learn how to use soap queries and that so clearly syntax to form really complex and
really powerful queries and the best way to show this is through some simple examples.
So overall a sub query allows us to use multiple select statements where we basically have a query within
a query and we're going to show this by a few examples.
The first example is this.
Suppose we want to find the films whose rental rate is higher than the average runs.
All right what do we we could do this isn't two steps we can find the average rental rate by using the
select statement with the average function.
And then after finding the average rental rate we can use the result of the first query in the second
select statement to find the films that we want.
So we go ahead and go to the sequel editor to code that out and we're going to show how we could do
that in two steps.
And then later on we'll see how we can use a query to simplify the task.
So first we're going to go the long way about it and then we're going to show you how you can use a
sub query to simplify it.
So again the task we're trying to solve is this first bullet point here.
We want to find the films whose rental rate is higher than the average rental rate.
Let me go ahead and jump to the sequel Ed. now.
OK.
So here I am at the sequel Ed. We're going to be working with the film table because if we scroll to
the right of the film table notice here we have the rental rate.
So again we want to find the movies whose rental rate is higher than the average run rate.
One way to do this given what you know right now would be to do two distinct separate steps that would
be step one find the average rental rates for say something like a Viji rental underscore rate call
get the average from film that run that query notice that's $2 in 98 cents.
And then once we have that result $2 a 98 cents then we would continue with the rest of the query would
say select for instance title and rental rates from the film table where rental underscore rates is
greater than two point ninety eight dollars a 98 cents which we discovered from our first query.
And if I run that here I have all the movies whose rental rate is greater than the average $2 in 98
cents.
That's basically 299 and above.
So that was a little inconvenient because I had to use two queries so I'm going to jump back real quick
to the PowerPoint slides.
And again to comments here we are at the slides to come back and we just saw the code we just went through
isn't so elegant it requires two steps.
And what's really annoying is you have to write down or remember the result of the first query.
We really want a way to pass the result of the first query to the second query in just a single chunk
of sequel syntax in one query.
And the solution to that is to use a sub query
a sub query is a query that's nested inside another query and to construct the query.
What we do is we put the second query in brackets or round parentheses and use it in the WHERE clause
as an expression.
So for instance to construct the subquery.
We put again the second query in brackets.
Some people just call these round parentheses or refer to them as both brackets in parentheses here
.
And you use it in the WHERE clause is an expression.
So we can say something like this select the columns we want fill my the title rental rate from film
where the rental rate and in the previous example we had a say greater than 2.9 8 because we had already
done this statement here select average run rate from film with this sub query.
We're able to skip that first step and actually incorporate it into our entire query here.
And so notice the main syntax that allows us to do this query or the sub query is these brackets or
parentheses around the sub query here.
So say select the columns we want from the table we want where.
And then inside the WHERE clause.
Here we have another query.
Let's go ahead and code this out and code out a couple more examples.
So I'm going to go see a few more examples in the sequel EDR as well as just show you the one we just
went over to reiterate how we can change two queries to just one with a sub query going to go ahead
and jump back to PGE Adam and now and open up a sequel after.
OK so here I am back at the sequel Ed. I remember this when we were doing before we had to actually
run a first query and get this number.
These two point nine eight value and we're going to do now is see how we can use that sub query.
So the so queries just this we put in parentheses or brackets here and in which you want to call them
.
So we put in those parentheses and then we say select average rental rate basically just put in that
first query wanted select the average transfer rate from.
And in this case it's the field table and then make sure here that the syntax highlights it so you know
it's balanced out.
And then if we run this you'll notice we get the exact same results.
I just executed that when we got the exact same thing.
OK.
So this post gres sequel executes the query that contains a sub query and the following sequence.
First it's going to execute the sub query here.
So as far as the order in which this actually gets executed by the sequel engine it first executes the
query then second it gets the result and passes it to the outer query and then third it executes that
outer query.
OK so a query can return 0 or more rows.
So use the query you can also use an in operator in the WHERE clause.
So let's go to show you another example of using a subquery with some more complex tasks.
It start off we're going to explore two tables just to remind ourselves of what's going to select all
the columns from the rental table and take a quick look at it.
So the rental table and you can go ahead and set limits so you don't return everything which is looking
for the column names here but the rental table has a rental ID number a rental date stamp and then so
Inventory ID number customer ID number a return date staff ID and last update.
And so a quick issue here is that I don't actually have the film ID.
I only have this rental ID.
And so what I want to do is match an Inventory ID integer if another table the inventory table in order
to start building up a query here.
So what I want to do is get films that have been returned between two specific dates let's say May 29th
and May 30th.
So I'm going to go ahead and explore.
Real quick.
The inventory table.
So again here below have the rental table and note I have an Inventory ID on this rental table and a
return date.
And those are the two main columns we're going to be using from the rental table from the inventory
table if we go ahead and check it out let's just limit that to one row.
We have an Inventory ID and a film ID.
And so this is the link we want we want to link up this Inventory ID from the inventory table to the
Inventory ID from the rental table.
So let's go ahead and do that using a joint.
So I'm going to say this and you go in and delete that line going to go ahead and say select inventory
dot film underscore ID basically at the end of the day.
I just want to list the film IDs and I'm going to grab it not from inventory but from rental joint on
inventory and we're going to do an inner join because I only want it where they both exist.
So you can go ahead and review inner joints.
We actually specifically Joines rental and inventory throughout some of those examples.
So go ahead and review that.
If this is a little fuzzy so I'm going to say select inventory the film.
So the film might call in from the inventory table from rental inner join inventory on inventory thought
inventory underscore ID equal to rental inventory underscore ID where and in this case I'm going to
say return dates.
And notice I don't have to specify what table return they is from because it's only in the rental table
.
So if I wanted to I could say rental return date but I don't have to because return date is only in
the rental table.
So then I'm going to say between and we'll say 2005 let's say May 29.
Pass that in as a string.
So note the dashes there ans
2005.
May 30th.
All right.
So let's go out and see if this worked out for us make sure we did everything right.
Looks like it did.
So we have a list of film IDs that were returned between May twenty of 2005 and May 30th 2005.
So let's go ahead and review this kind of it's a little bit of a query but hopefully it's not too complicated
.
We selected the film ID column from the inventory table from excuse me.
Yeah.
Film ID column from the inventory table.
And then we said select that specific column.
So I noticed table that column from Rentoul inner join inventory on inventory that inventory underscore
I.D. and rental inventory underscore IDs.
So we're joining the inventory table with the rental table on the inventory underscore ID column and
that matches up.
And that's the way we can grab information based off the return day from the rental table but hook it
up to the inventory table so we can grab the fill mighty.
So go ahead and review the inner join lecture and the between lecture.
If any of this is a little fuzzy or unclear.
OK.
So moving along.
Let's go ahead and use this entire query as a sub query to get the titles of the films.
So I'm going to put this entire query delete that semi-colon and put this all in between parentheses
here.
And so that's my giant So queery this list of film IDs.
And those are films.
These were the return date was between 2005 May 29 and 2005 May 30th.
And so then what I'm going to do is grab those film IDs and the movie title.
So I'm going to say this selects the film Id Khama title from film where the film ID is in and then
I put in the entire sub query.
So basically what this is saying is return these two columns the film ID and the title caudal column
from the film table were the film ID is in this list so its going to basically treat this entire multiple
rows as a list of values in this subquery.
So if I go ahead and run this and put a semi-colon there at the end outside of the brackets are parentheses
.
And now I have the film ID and the title for movies that were returned between 2005 May 29 and 2005
May 30th.
OK so I know this may look a little daunting and usually giant some queries are a little daunting and
this is where it gets really important to use certain naming schemes or aliasing or code formatting
.
So for example some people like to put select from on one line.
Others like to separate it out and this is where you are going to really discover your own style as
far as how you like to space stuff out and separate it and make use of whitespace.
But its really critical to begin to think about organizing your sequel queries when youre using these
sub queries so these queries can be really powerful and get you exactly what you want and they operate
a lot quicker than doing multiple queries in a row.
But just keep in mind they can start to get a little unreadable here.
So let's go out to review everything that we just learned as far as the basics.
A So query is the query within a query.
So a simple example was that rental rate where we had a sub query to return that value and then we got
that result and basically input it into the outer query and then hear a more complicated example is
getting a list of multiple rows return and then we use that using the in operator.
Again if you go back to the first example that rental rate example we just use some sort of comparison
operator or we could have used like if it was a string that was return but if its just a single integer
or a single string return then youre going to use either some sort of comparison operator or an equals
or like if your so query is going to return a bunch of rows back to you then you're going to use in
and then that sub query that returns a bunch of rows.
OK so I know this may be tricky.
So go ahead and feel free to ask any discussion questions to clear up any questions that you have.
We'll be exploring this topic of sub queries on the second assessment test.
All right.
So that's it.
Make sure review the lecture and play around.
It's just critical that you understand how to create your queries and how they're useful to you.
And I think that's actually really clear in the first example where we showed those two separate queries
and then showed that it was easier to make it as one query.
But again feel free to post any discussion questions and I'm happy to answer questions for you guys
.
OK well thanks everyone.
And I will see you at the next lecture