Hello everyone and welcome to the lecture on self-join and this lecture we're going to learn how to
use a self-join statement.
See an example in the slides and then we'll see another example of postscripts sequel and PGE admin
.
It's the database we've been working with.
So you've already learned how to join a table with other tables using things such as an inner join a
left outer join or right join etc..
However there is a special case the join a table to itself which is known as a self-join is self-join
.
When you want to combine rows with other rows in the same table to perform the self-join operation you
must use a table alias to help sequel distinguish the left table from the right table at the same table
.
And what I mean by alias is using that as statement.
So remember we were able to call whole tables or whole column something like column ID as some other
name or some alias name.
That's what we're referring to when we say table alias and you'll see examples of that as we go forward
.
So imagine we have the following table.
We have one column with employee name and another column with employee location and we can see here
that Joe is from New York.
Suppose you want to actually find out which employees are from the same location as the employee named
Joe.
So we quickly scan this table we can see at the bottom there.
Jack is also from New York so we want to find out which employees are from the same location as the
employee named Joe.
There's a couple of ways to do this.
In this example like I mentioned that location that Joe lives in is New York and let's assume that we
cannot just directly search the table for people who live in New York with a simple query like this
.
So maybe we don't want to hard code the city name in the sequel queery etc..
And what I mean by that is let's imagine that we couldn't couldn't just do this.
We can't just say we're employee underscore location equals New York for some reason we just can't directly
put in our query where employee location equals New York.
And there's a bunch of real world scenarios where that's going to be the case.
Either you don't want to have to look it up again or you don't want to have to run to queries etc..
So let's just imagine for the sake of argument an example here that we can't write that bottom line
exactly like that.
In that case we have some other options we could use a sub query and we just saw that earlier in some
lectures specifically a subquery lecture where I could say select employee name from Employee table
where employee location in and then I have my sub query there in parentheses or round brackets in Iman's
and then I'm saying select employee location for an employee where employ underscore name equals Joe
and that will bring back New York and then I'll do the other query into the query and that should do
then bring back Jack.
OK so that's one way to do it.
And while a sub query is a valid solution it is actually more efficient to use the self-join that we're
learning about.
So we're going to join a table to itself again as a general rule.
We need to always use aliases or remember that as statement when using a self-join.
So for that particular example it would look something like this.
I would say select ie one dot Employee Name column from employee as one comma employee as E-2 where
each one employee location column equals to that employee location and each to that employee name is
equal to Joe and so noticing the actual syntax of the sequel query doesn't specifically use any of the
terms join and that's because it's a self-join.
So because I'm using this aliasing technique saying employee as E-1 comma employ as E-2.
So I basically have two tables in there with from as two aliases but they're actually the same table
employee employee.
This is known as a self join.
So again I'm saying select the employee name column from each E-1 from employee as the one com employee
as to where E-1 the employee location is equal to E-2 the employee location so that employee location
match matches EON's where that employee name from 8 to was equal to Joe.
So let's go to break down a little further.
What this is actually doing.
So again this crew's going to return the names Joe and Jack to shack as the only other person who lives
in New York like Joe and generally queries that refer to the same table can be greatly simplified by
rewriting the queries.
A self joins.
So if you compare the query text to the self-join text there's a lot less text in the self-join.
So it looks a lot cleaner and in addition to this there is a performance benefit as well to doing a
self-join vs doing to save queries.
So let's go at a breakdown with that self-join is actually doing it's good to recall our original table
where we have the employee name and the employee location.
And then again remember that Joe lives in New York and Jack lives in New York.
So then we created two aliases.
He wanted me to notice the same table.
So they're both instances there of the employee table.
They're just aliases.
And then the final result of running the self-join query above the actual join table would look like
this.
You'd have the E-1 the Employee Name column that you wanted the employee location column self-join to
eat to that employee name to that employee location.
So you would get this as your actual adjoined table.
And this is where you actually call the columns off of it.
So if a member of the column is called off of it was e one there.
And the reason we get two instances of Joe here is because if you look back to the self-join query we
had that and statement that said and E-2 that employee underscore name is equal to Joe.
OK.
So that's what the actual join table looks like when you return office self-join.
So let's go out and see an example in NPG adamant to work with our database and get some more understanding
of how the self-join is actually operating.
I'm going to go ahead and jump to P.G. Adam now.
OK.
So here we are at PGE admin and I'm going to go ahead and be using the customer table.
So it's good to remind ourselves what the customer table looks like.
We have a first name and a last name of the customer and then some other information on them are going
to be specifically concerned with the first name and last name columns.
Let's go ahead and imagine that we wanted to retrieve all customers whose last name matched the first
name of another customer meaning if we had a name like Sandra Martin and we had another name or another
customer whose first name was Martin and last name was something like Bayles we'd have a match there
so we'd have Sandra Martin matches with Martin Bayles.
So we want to achieve all the customers whose last name matches the first name of another customer.
And the best way to do this is using a self-join.
So let's go ahead and explore how we can do that.
So to say this selects the ADA first underscore Name column and we'll say Ada last name column and then
we'll say be the first name column and be dots last name column.
And I'm going to select that from the customer table but remember I have to use aliasing here.
So I'm going to say from customer as a comma customer as B and then we're going to say for the actual
join I'm going to go ahead and use a WHERE clause.
So and then I'm going to say where a first underscore name equals the last underscore name.
Now let's go ahead and run that.
And you'll notice here we get some results and if we look at them we can see that our query ended up
working.
So here we have the first name.
Rose Howard shares the first name to the last name of Darleen rose and we have Kelly Torres and Denise
Kelly So we see the matches on the first column and the last column.
And let's go ahead and confirm that these are two separate people.
The way you can do that is by grabbing their customer id name as well.
So here I'm going to add just two more calls when I say that customer id column and then I'm going to
also add the b dot customer id column here and then I'm going to go ahead and run this again at 5 or
just execute here on the query.
And so here I have the customer ID number.
So I have 65 matches of customer 157.
So these are two separate people and were able to match up people to have the first name that matches
the last name of someone else in the actual table.
Now using this sort of comma syntax for a self-join statement is pretty common.
But I also want to show you how you could use it with just actually explicitly saying join.
So that is possible as well for a self join statement.
Some people prefer the way I just did it right.
Now if a comma in the way I showed it in the slides.
Other people prefer actually explicitly writing that joint statement and then it would look like this
you would say from customer as a joyn customer as B and then sort of saying where you would say on a
first name is equal to last name here.
And so if we run that we get the exact same results.
So again you're going to discover your own style as far as what you prefer and what's easier to read
for you.
I think for a lot of beginners actually this second way that I just showed you is usually easier to
read and understand with the caveat being that you're going to use an on statement instead of a where
statement if you prefer prefer thinking about it using from and then the customer as Alias Khama customer
as alias and then using a where statement.
That's also totally fine.
So again it's really what you prefer.
As far as self-join syntax.
And then if we wanted to we could actually continue to work on this query by saying something like order
by let's say a customer ID
and then we have everything ordered by the customer ID and you can see here that we're going to get
.
Rose Howard and Arlene Rose Kelly Torres Denise Kelly etc. Now you may be wondering is my only going
to use an inner joined by default.
What if I wanted a left join or right join.
So self joints are not limited to just an inner join.
While the cases we've seen make the most sense of inner join you can also use a left join to provide
all records from the left table.
Regardless if there is actually a match.
So if for some reason we wanted to get everything from the left table regardless if there was a match
or not.
Then we can also specify left or right outer joins.
So for example I can edit this and say something like.
Left join.
And remember this is the same as saying left outer join.
I can just say left joined by default.
Sequel engines will know your specifically meaning an outer join because of the term left there.
So if I do this then go ahead and run this.
Notice that I'm going to get a bunch of no or empty values here because this specific person is from
the left table so the A or customer has a table and didn't have this first name matching with the last
name of anyone else in the table.
So we're going to get no values if we do it this way.
But as we scroll down you should see some matches pop up.
So for example Joy George.
Matches.
Matches with Joseph.
Joy so Joy Joy there.
So it's up to you and up to whatever the business task you're trying to solve is if you're going to
use a self-join or an inner join or a left join.
More likely than not you'll usually use these with inner joins because you're specifically looking for
some sort of match there.
You don't care about returning everything with the nulls but it's good.
Keep in mind that you can use it with left and right outer joints for the tables regardless.
OK so that's it for the inner joins.
I would recommend doing now is actually Google searching manager plus employee self-join.
So if I go ahead and do that real quick.
So here am I just jumped to Google and I did a manager employee self-join in the Google search and you'll
get a lot of results.
Go and explore those if you want to learn more about self-join beyond what we just covered here.
Although it's pretty straightforward as far as your joining a table to itself.
The specific reason I want you to check out manager employee self-join is that for whatever reason this
is an extremely common interview question for people who are going to be interviewed and sequel.
It's basically the de facto way to check if you know what a self-join is or not.
So basically what happens is you're given this table with employees and managers and you have to figure
out what employees make more salary than managers etc..
That kind of thing.
But for whatever reason this is a really common interview question.
As far as testing your knowledge of self joints and sub queries so go ahead and explore that.
If you plan on getting interviewed in self Joines or sequel anytime soon.
That should probably show up or some form of that question will show up OK.
If not then you understand self-join already go ahead and feel free to continue on without doing that
Google search.
OK.
Well thanks everyone and I will see you at the next lecture