Hello everyone and welcome to this lecture on using postgresql with Python and using the library psycho
PGE too.
So I'm right now using the Jupiter notebook system in order to show you how all this syntax works.
You can feel free to use any editor.
I read that you prefer for Python.
If you've already experienced one of my other Python courses you're probably already really familiar
to Jupiter or python no pick system if you're not and want to find that more.
You can go to WDW w that Jupiter org and explore that Web site and also give you a link on how to install
it and you can explore it more.
I really like it as far as for teaching and quick scripts but you can also explore everything we're
about to do in your preferred idea or development environment for Python.
So let's go ahead and start by just importing the library that we downloaded from the previous lecture
.
So again go to the previous lecture for more notes on how to actually download everything.
And for the PI file that has all the code that Imman execute here or the notebook file has again all
the code and some notes of what I'm going to execute here during the lecture.
So to get started like I was saying we need to import psyco PGE too to so psycho mixtures.
Well that right Sekou PGE too.
So by convention we just import as PGE 2.
And then the next thing you're going to do is connect to your database and by convention that C O and
N and you're just going to say PGE to and then call the connect method and you're going to pass in a
couple of arguments here.
The first one is what database you're going to connect to.
I'm going to go ahead and connect to the DVD rental database that we've been working with a lot and
then you have to define the user.
So depending on how you actually set up your PC admin account you may have set up your own particular
username if you don't specify the user name in this argument of the connect method.
They'll automatically by default on a Windows computer.
And I believe on a Mac as well default to the user profile name.
But if you've just been following along with all the lectures the default for PGE admin as far as the
username is just post gress.
So if you're having any trouble if your own username try just saying post.
And if you set everything to default it should be postgresql and then the last thing you have to input
is your password.
Now I've already set up my password as the variable called secret appear.
So if you want you could just set up a variable called secret and put in your password.
Obviously my password is not the string your password goes here.
So if you've done all this correctly you should be able to run this line of code or put this line of
code inside your IP y file and then you should have a connection there.
So in this Juber notebook system I'm basically just running each of these cells as a separate block
of code.
And that way I can run the cells and show the output at the same time.
So now that we've established the connection to postscripts sequel The next step is to retrieve the
cursor and the cursor is just a control structure that enables traversal over the records in a database
.
So you can basically think of it as some sort of iterator or a pointer for Sequel data retrieval.
And the way we're going to do that is we're going to go in and create a variable called C-u are and
then we're going to have a connection object.
So that was this c o n n and then we call the cursor method off of it.
And so now we have our cursor and I was essentially the last thing we need to do in order to execute
Suko queries from Python.
So using their cursor object I can say execute off of it.
And then you basically inside the execute method you pass in a string of whatever you want to actually
ask the database or query the database so we can say something like this select Asterix from let's go
ahead and say from payments.
So now this cursor has the execute statements and this cursor then has a couple of methods available
.
It has fetch all fetch many and fetch one.
So what these do is they basically return rows of data.
So if I just say fetch one ill return the first row of that data.
So these are the numbers that correspond with that row data from select everything from payment.
I can also say fetch many and then actually pasan how many rows I want to fetch.
So I can fetch 10 rows and you'll notice that it returns as a list of tuple items which is nice because
then you can use tuple and packing later on.
And also note that depending on the data type.
Also specify like a date time data type.
If you have a time stamp information on it for that particular column in your database table so those
are really the main features you're going to be using with first psycho P.G. 2.
And as far as using this all in Python is going to be kind of up to you.
Hayes these main three or four commands in order to use the power of python and use the automation capabilities
of Python to query your database or put things into your database.
So again let's just go over what we've done so far you have to import Cyclopedia to as PGE to then you
had established a connection.
I said it is the variable c o n n.
And you said PGE to that connect you had to pass in the database name you're connecting to pass in the
user you are connecting as the default user for any postscripts application is post gress.
And then you had a pass and the password that you set up when you're first installing Peachi admin and
post-career sequel.
Then you had to get a cursor off of that connection and with that cursor you could then execute sequel
queries off of it.
And then once you have that cursor execute that query you can actually fetch the rows that are returned
you can fetch many rows.
You can fetch just one row or the final option is actually to fetch all of them.
And notice here since there's quite a few rows you may want to use this carefully.
Otherwise you'll just end up with a ton of rows returned.
So it's good and change that back to fetch one.
So again this is really nice because you can use tuple and packing along with it so you can say something
like just say fetch money such as 10.
Well let me actually execute that query again.
Notice I had to execute the query in order to fetch them off so I could execute the query one more time
and we'll say this is equal to data.
And if I take a look at data I have this list and I can index off of it as you would expect tuple and
pack it keep indexing off of it just to get particular data points.
It's really up to you as far as what you're going to use this type of data for and this sort of Python
or psycho PGE format with but hopefully basically these lines are the most important ones and that can
really be you're building blocks as far as how you're going to use postgresql with Python that sort
of applications really up to you and more likely are not just going to be a smaller part or back and
the application in Python when you're communicating with your database once you're done communicating
executing off your database you're going to want to close your connection.
You going to want to say it's your connection and go ahead and close it.
And that's really all there is to it.
You can check out the PI for a python file from the previous lecture or the python notebook file from
the previous lecture to get a couple of more useful hints and tips for how to use Cyclopes too with
postgresql and Python.
Other than that it's really just the basics of it.
That's kind of all we need to know to start exploring how you can use post-career sequel with your own
python applications.
Again the most important parts are just the import.
Establishing that connection creating the cursor and then executing the sequel queries.
One thing I wanted to know is to make sure that you kind of avoid using Python print's formatting or
string formatting when you're executing the sequel queries.
What do you mean by that is.
Imagine you have this situation where you want to say executes and you input some commands and let's
say earlier in your code your command line was something like.
Maybe one selects all from and then you are going to add another string to it later on.
So maybe that string was another object and what I'm trying to say is you may want to be careful when
you're doing this sort of thing with a psycho pgm post-career sequel with Python because it's kind of
dangerous if you accidentally call add something like drop table later on.
This could kind of like potentially screw up your database so just keep that in mind.
It's always best practice to put in the entire sequel query as just one single string and to verify
that it's a single string that you want.
There's a couple more notes on that in the note book but it's just something to be aware of.
OK with that being said that's really it as far as this.
Just a quick overview of how you can use cycle PGE and postgresql of Python.
Feel free to ask any questions in the discussion section of the course and you can also feel free to
refer to the resources from the previous lecture for more hints and more tutorials on how to use this
really useful library.
OK thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next lecture