Hello and welcome to the complete sequel boot camp I'm Jose Portsea and I've taught thousands of students
on you to me the most in-demand tech skills such as Python data science and coding.
Interview preparation and now I'm excited to launch this new course designed to teach you one of the
most in-demand skills using sequel's interact for database and analyze data.
I've designed this course to take you from zero to hero of sequel so no prior programming experience
is necessary whether you a marketing or business analyst looking to learn a sequel.
A data scientist for someone who wants to improve their data analysis capabilities.
This comprehensive course is right for you.
Sequel is currently the most in-demand skill for the tech sector and learning it can dramatically change
career prospects.
Once you complete this course you'll feel comfortable putting sequel on your resume.
We'll be working with one of the most popular indemand versions of postscripts sequel but the syntax
and skills you learn in this course can be applied to any other major database or software that uses
Secord.
This includes database systems such as Amazon redshift My sequel Microsoft sequel server Oracle database
and much more.
Throughout the course you'll video lectures explaining concepts clearly and you get challenges to complete
against the real database to test new skills.
Ms course also includes comprehensive assessment tests so you can review your sequel knowledge.
You'll also receive a certificate of completion that you can post here to lengthen account to show your
new skills.
Employers not only do you get great content you get an effective learning experience and when you join
this course you'll also get a lifetime access to a helpful community of students and discussion forums
.
This course also comes to a 30 day money back guarantee.
If you're not 100 percent satisfied with this course I'll refund you your money no questions asked.
This course is designed to help you achieve your career goals.
Whether you're looking to get more into data analytics increase your earning potential or just want
a job more freedom.
This is the right course for you.
Check out the next preview lecture for a full curriculum overview.
So what are you waiting for.
Begin the next chapter in your career and enroll today.