Hello everyone and welcome to the course curriculum lecture for the complete sequel boot camp.
In this lecture we're going to go over the entire courses curriculum and understand that building blocks
that make up this course to begin.
You'll start off by installing postscripts sequel mpg admen.
We have full installation walkers for both Windows and Mac computer systems.
Once we've done that we'll start off with some basic sections the first section will cover databases
and table basics.
Then we'll learn about sequels statement fundamentals and that section of the Course you'll finally
begin to use sequel syntax to query the database in the tables you created in the previous section.
Then we'll step it up a notch by learning about the group by clause and once we've finished that you'll
have your first assessment test during the course.
Once you've completed that first assessment test you'll learn about Joines some more advanced sequel
commands and then you'll have a second assessment test to test your understanding of everything you've
learned up to this point in the course.
After that you'll have your final sections.
You'll learn how to create database and tables directly through a sequel syntax.
Then you'll have your third assessment test that will test your knowledge on creating databases and
tables directly through sequel.
Then we also have some extra bonus lectures lectures.
These topics include views using postgresql of the Python programming language as well as the special
discount offers from other courses.
With that all being said lets go ahead and get started with the entire course so it can build up our
knowledge.
Thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next lecture