Hello everyone and welcome to the database overview lecture.
So in this lecture we're going to learn what are databases and why use databases.
And after we answer those two fundamental questions we'll get a sense of where this course fits in the
realm of things.
So let's turn off the basic definition database or systems that allow users to store and organize data
and they're useful when dealing of large amounts of data.
So you might be wondering what are the typical users look like who deal with databases while databases
actually have a wide variety of users.
These can include analysts such as a marketing analyst a business analyst or a sales or sales operation
analyst or more technical people like data scientist software engineers or web developers.
Basically anyone needing to deal data has a great use case to work for database.
So since most users have some familiarity with a spreadsheet software either Google Spreadsheets or
Microsoft Excel we're going to do is discuss the transition from going from spreadsheets to databases
.
So it's good to discuss some use cases for spreadsheets versus use cases for databases and then leverage
that knowledge to better understand databases.
So spreadsheets are really good for a one time analysis or to quickly need to churn something out such
as in Excel and they work with reasonable data set sizes something that can excel or Google Spreadsheets
can open up really easily.
Now what's really nice about spreadsheets is they allow the ability for untrained people to work with
data.
So anyone can just double click an Excel file open it and work with it.
However they do have downsides where databases really shine.
So databases are really great for data integrity meaning you don't want to have someone be able to just
click on a cell and change the data.
Databases don't really allow for that.
And they can also handle massive amounts of data data sizes that would just basically make excel or
Google Spreadsheets crash and they can also quickly combine different data sets something that might
be difficult to do for larger data sets in a spreadsheet.
They also are perfect for automating steps for reuse due to the school syntax which will learn about
later and they can also support data for Web sites and applications.
So most Web sites and web applications or mobile applications are linked to some sort of database to
store their data and retrieve their data.
So let's go in and leverage that knowledge from spreadsheets to understand databases and see the similarities
between them.
So here we have a picture of a looks like a normal spreadsheet.
Here we have the columns.
It's just the basic glucose tracking spreadsheet.
And we have columns which just time some measurements etc. and various rows with different data points
.
And then at the bottom here we have tabs which are referencing various sheets in the spreadsheet software
here using Excel.
So we're transitioning from a spreadsheet to a database.
We can think of databases tables as the tabs of a spreadsheet system.
Each of those tabs of the spreadsheet handles various types of data or different rows in different columns
.
Those tabs will translate to tables in a database so that a database is made up of many tables and then
those tables are made up of rows and columns so the columns in the Table of a database is basically
exactly what you would think as a column in a spreadsheet.
It's just a vertical column that denotes a certain data type.
So for instance the first one here we have time.
Second we only have measurements so columns and spreadsheets are basically the same as columns in the
Table of a database.
And then the other feature we have from a spreadsheet to a database is going to be rows and rows again
behave exactly like you would expect them to in the database table.
They're just the actual row of all that data for a certain data point.
So in this case we're highlighting the data points seven eight and nine and then all the measurements
for those columns.
So again databases and sort of tabs they're going to have tables and those tables are also going to
have rows and columns and you can basically just imagine them as spreadsheets just much larger that
you can't individually click on.
OK.
So again we have columns rows and a set of tabs we're going to have tables.
So what are database platform options.
Well there's actually lots of database platform options a lot more than what I put here.
But here are some of the main ones you have postgresql sequel things such as my sequel and my sequel
server express Microsoft Access and then sequel lite.
Each of these has their pros and cons but we're going to be focusing on postgresql sequel.
The reason for this is because postscripts sequel is free open source.
It's widely used on the Internet.
It's multi-platform So meaning if you have various operating systems like Windows or Mac users you can
all use postscripts sequel and one of my main reasons for choosing it is that it's super easy to install
and just hit the ground running.
So post-career sequel's a great database choice for learning how to use sequel and sequel's a structured
query language that's what it stands for and that's what we're going to learn in this course.
Sequel is going to be the way we communicate for database.
So we were going to be able to communicate database to get data out of it or put data into it.
And the sequel learn this course can be applied to a variety of databases or siecle based software.
So we're not going to pigeonhole ourselves that just postscripts sequel what you learn in this course
you're going to be able to apply it to a variety of databases or software that uses sequel.
So for example of what a general sequel syntax would look like it would look something like this selects
some column names from a table and then you have some functions or clauses you're ordering by the first
name.
So we're going to learn how to write a new sequel syntax like this in this course.
So sequel is actually useful for a lot of things.
Everything I've listed here runs on some sort of syntax of sequel so you have postscripts sequel or
my sequel or Oracle databases Microsoft Access to the basic databases you would think of that can use
sequel but there's also a lot of software out there that use a sequel as a way of interacting for data
such as looker or periscope data.
And there's also some abstractions that run on top of big data systems such as Hadoop and you can use
sequel with hive or Google's big queery or Facebook's presto which is basically using sequel to run
on top of very large data systems that use distributed data.
So sequel going to be incredibly useful to operate a variety of tools and databases with.
So you're also going to be notified if any of the sequel commands we learn in this course are specific
to the post.
Gress sequel environment.
Most of the commands we learn are actually just going to be general sequel so you won't get too many
of these notifications.
Basically everything you learn here you're going to be able to apply directly to any conventional sequel
database.
OK let's go to review what we learned.
We learn what a database is why we should use a database.
We learned about the various sequel options and we also learned how to use sequel's skills in this course
and how we're going to be able to apply them to many other software programs.
OK.
But that being said let's go at and continue and learn some more.
Thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next lecture