Hello everyone and welcome to the P.G. admin and post-career sequel installation lecture in this lecture
.
We're going to briefly discuss what is PGE admin.
We'll give you some notes over the various versions of PGE admin.
And then we'll go over the installation guide.
So let's discuss what is PGE admin.
Usually when you're working with a sequel engine whether it be my sequel postgresql sequel Microsoft
sequel server you're going to be working through some sort of graphical interface not just direct the
command line although you can work direct the command line.
It's much easier to use one of these graphical interface tools sometimes known as Gucci's or graphical
user interface.
PGE Addleman is the most popular interface for postgresql sequel.
Now a quick note about the versions of PGE adamant Peachi Adam and four recently came out and it's officially
out of beta.
It used to be a little buggy for students.
So when this course was filmed we filmed that with Peachi admin 3.
But keep in mind all the sequel commands will work the same with PGE admin for.
So even though the interface may look a little different the course notes and sequel notes will all
work the same regardless of what PGE admen version you're using.
Now let's go ahead and go over the installation for this lecture and this lecture.
We're going to go ahead and install post-career sequel NPG admen through a convenient interactive installer
.
Then we'll go ahead and do is download the tar file which is a resource for this lecture.
We'll use that tar file to restore our film stored database which is the main database we're going to
be using or we're learning how to program a sequel in this course.
Later on you'll get another tar file for another database for another assessment test in order to get
started.
Let's go ahead and go to the w w w the post gres sequel dot org.
I'm going to go ahead and jump to my browser and Meacher at that Web site.
All right.
Here I am at postscripts sequel which you're going to go ahead and do is click on this download tab
or if you want it can actually just go directly to w w that postgresql or slash download.
You should see something that looks like this downloads which are going to go ahead and do is come down
and choose the prebuilt package which corresponds to your OS suffusing Mac OS.
You'll go ahead and click on this link right here.
From Windows you'll go ahead and click on this link.
And if you are on Linux depending on what version you're using you have a bunch of options here.
So if you go to either Mac OS package or the Windows installer package you should see some sort of installer
by enterprise DB.
So you'll see it on both Windows Installer and on this Mac OS X package.
So what you're going to go ahead and do is basically download this installer from Enterprise D.B and
then you'll go ahead and follow the instructions that the graphical or interactive installer prompts
you to.
So again we're going to be using the enterprise D-B you'll see that in both pages for Mac OS and Windows
.
There's another installer by big sequel.
Some students sometimes have trouble with this one so I really recommend this enterprise D-B.
So let's go ahead and download the installer and this installer actually includes not just postscripts
sequel but it also includes PGE admen the graphical tool for managing and developing these databases
.
So instead of having to download PGE admin a postgresql separately we're going to go ahead and download
it altogether.
So once you click that link it should take you to the enterprise DB and you'll get the same link whether
you're on Mac OS or windows.
And let's go ahead and just zoom in a bit and you'll see that there's versions here you can download
there's 9.6 nine point five five.
And what these versions actually mean this is the version of postgresql sequel.
So we're going to be using PGE admen for for this installation lecture and we'll also use version nine
point six point one you'll want to use the latest version that is not in beta.
So right now there is no beta version up here but later on you may be seeing something like nine point
seven or maybe nine point six point two et cetera.
And if it's as beta they're go ahead and skip down 1 to the latest version.
That is not in beta right.
So go ahead and click the relevant operating system link here.
So if you're a Mac OS you click this one.
I'm on Windows right now so I will go ahead and click Windows 64 bit.
Make sure you check whether you have a 32 bit Windows computer or 64 bit.
If you're on some sort of relatively modern Windows computer it's probably going to be 64 bit.
Ms go ahead and click on this to begin the download.
So that's beginning in the download I'm going to go ahead and jump forward in time for the download
to finish.
I'll see you there.
OK so my download has completed.
Let's go ahead and open up this executable file.
And if you see some Microsoft Visual pop up you can go ahead and continue through that.
All right so here we are at the installer.
Go ahead and click Next through the setup you'll want to specify the director postgresql will be installed
.
Go ahead and just choose the default C. Program Files.
Postscript sequel and you should see something like nine point six or nine point seven pending on what
versions you're doing right now were just on 9.6.
Let's go ahead and click next.
Then you'll want to select the directory under which this sort of data defaults fine.
And then this is a really really important part.
It's going to ask you to please provide a password for the database.
Super User host gress it's extremely important that you remember what you're going to type here.
I'm going to just go ahead and use a very simple one I'm going to write password.
You know like I mentioned it's extremely important that you remember so go ahead and write this down
somewhere or whatever you typed in for your password here.
OK then you're going to want to select the port number the server should listen on you'll want to go
ahead and choose the default default value.
My case is five four three three.
Most likely that will also be the same default value for you.
So go ahead and just leave the default there.
Click next and you'll want to select the location or locale to be used for the new database cluster
.
Go ahead and just use the default.
That's also OK.
And now setup is now ready to begin.
So go ahead and click next and you should see it installing.
OK.
So it's creating all the directories and setting up everything for postgresql sequel.
We'll go ahead and fast forward through this and get to the next step.
So now go ahead and jump forward in time now.
All right so my installation has finished now at the very end of the installation you should see something
like Do you want to check out stack builder.
You can go ahead and just uncheck that box.
It's not necessary.
Once you have that you should be able to open a PGA admin for this case you can actually just search
your computer for it.
So it's CPG admen.
I have both versions here the old one pgm and three.
But let's go ahead and click on PGE admen for and see what it looks like.
So PGA 10:04 should look a lot slicker and cleaner than PGE outman theory.
All right so now I can see here that PGA admen for has been loaded and opened.
And we should see some servers here.
I have 9.5 9.6.
If you don't see these servers then something probably went wrong with your installation.
So go ahead and check that again.
But if you follow the instructions it should have worked fine for you and the only one you should see
if this is your first time running this is just 9.6.
You should see at least one server here in here we can go ahead and see something that looks like this
will say please enter the password for the user postgresql and then connect to the server.
This is where you're going to enter the password that you saved earlier.
So go ahead and just put that in and can click here save password that we don't have to constantly enter
this click OK.
And you should see something that looks like then like this.
Everything's working fine.
All right so once you're at this screen we're going to go ahead and do is restore a database using the
tar file.
So remember to download the tar file which is a resource for this lecture.
You'll go ahead and right click here you'll say create database
and then you'll have the database name option.
In this case I'm going to call this database DVD rental and then click Save that created the DVD rental
database so you can see here.
We'll go ahead and click on it and you should see something that looks like this cast catalogs the events
triggers et cetera.
Now right now we just have an empty database.
We actually need to restore some data to it.
OK now that we created a new database called DVD rental.
Let's go ahead and use the tar file from the resource section of this lecture in order to actually restore
this database.
We have some sort of data information and we'll go ahead.
Right click on this and then you will click restore.
Now you may get a pop up that says something like this please configure the postgresql binary path in
the preferences dialog.
So if you get this pop up let me go ahead and show you how you can create this configuration.
You'll go ahead and just click OK and then you will click File preferences that are going to make this
full screen here and you'll see something that says path's binary path.
So we're here and where you're going to go ahead and do it just post the postgresql sequel binary path
.
Now this sounds kind of intimidating but it's actually quite simple.
You're just going to find the binary path where it was default located.
So let me go in and show you they can find them.
Should be a really similar process on your Mac computer that will show you how to do this on Windows
.
Go ahead and jump to your program files to postscripts sequel.
Want to go ahead and do that now.
So here I am under program files postscripts sequel.
This is just the default location where everything was installed.
You should have 9.6 somewhere.
You probably don't have these DVD rental tar files if you haven't done it.
But go ahead and see nine point six.
And then there's a bin folder here.
Double click on that.
And this is the folder you need to get to.
So it just should be under the default location program files.
Post-career sequel 9.6 been so wherever it was default installed on your computer go heading then go
to 9.6.
We should see some sort of folder called Ben.
That's what PGE admin for wants to know.
This is the location it's asking for.
And you can see up here it says path to the directory containing utility programs.
PGE dump PGE restore etc..
So if you scroll down here to you get to the PS You should see stuff like PGE underscore it.
PGE underscore restore somewhere around here.
There it is.
So if you want to you're having trouble finding this you can just search your computer for these actual
file names and then it should take you to this bin folder.
So we're going to go ahead and do it just copy this address and then paste it here.
So by default should be under-sea program files postgresql 9.6 Ben and then hit.
OK.
All right so now let's go ahead and try this again will reichlich DVD rental hit restore and you should
see something that looks like this restore the database.
We want to select the format so we want a custom or tar.
OK now that we've set up custom or tar file here we gonna go ahead and put in the file name.
So you have a couple options here.
If you click on these three dots here you make it a bug and you may have a hard time actually finding
the DVD rental file.
You'll get something that pops up saying that there's no disk found and Dr.
So instead of actually searching for this manually it's usually much easier to just put in the whole
file path here.
So go ahead and go to wherever you happen to put the DVD rental that tar file in my case it's under
Downloads.
When I go ahead and go to that now you'll see something that looks like this.
So I have it under my downloads here here's the DVD rental the tar file I downloaded.
I'm going to.
Right click.
Go to its properties.
And then I should see the file path here.
So says location.
I'm going to go ahead and just copy that location then hit OK or Cancel whatever.
And then I'm going to paste that in and then I'm going to do another slash and say DVD rental tar.
So here it is.
Saved under my downloads DVD rental tar.
As I mentioned if you click on this three thoughts here sometimes it's a little bit buggy.
So go ahead and just instead put in the whole path to the file then I want to go ahead and just briefly
show you the restore options.
So these restore options and expand this to all screen.
You can actually select to only install schema by clicking on this switch button here or only the data
and later on we'll discuss or have a little exercise for you to actually try to restore only the scheme
or only the data.
Basically what that means is you only want to return the actual tables themselves not the actual data
that's in the tables.
So you're trying to duplicate the format.
You can install something like only schema buffering.
Now go ahead and leave these all to the default.
Should a lot of them just should just say no.
Come back to the general.
You have your file name your format.
Go ahead and then click restore and it should say restore job created.
They'll give you a little count down of how long it's taking and it should hopefully say successfully
completed and then what you'll need to do is check here and we'll go ahead and click refresh and this
step is really important.
Otherwise it may look like you haven't done anything so click on refresh it'll go ahead and refresh
that DVD rental file.
Come down here click on schemas.
You should see a public schema and they should come down here to where it says tables expand that and
you should see actor address category city etc..
So if you're seeing all that you are good to go.
Let me go ahead and walk you through a simple sequel query on this new database you have.
All right now that we've successfully restored this database Let's confirm that everything is working
.
By executing our first simple query.
Now again don't worry if you don't understand everything about the type in this query that's the whole
point of course we're going to teach you a sequel but let's go ahead and kind of do a hello world example
just by selecting all the columns and all the rows in a table.
So I will right click on DVD rental and then I will click on if you go down here there's the query tool
has a little lightning rod go ahead and click on that.
You should see a new window pop up that looks like this.
And then where you're going to go ahead and write is selects Asterix from and then choose any of these
tables that are down here.
I'm going to go ahead and choose the actor table.
So say it from actor semi-colon and that's it.
So basically what this is saying is select all the rows from the actor table.
And I'm going to come over here to this lightning rod and then click on execute and refresh.
Now when you click on execute and refresh you make it something that looks like this is a little datagrid
.
You can go ahead and click back here to your normal tab and you should see the results of the data output
So here I see the actor Id the first name and the last name and the last update.
So this is the actual data from my table.
So if you're able to see this data output it means you are good to go and I will see you at the next
lecture.
If you have any questions please don't hesitate to post the Q&A forums.
I know there's a lot of steps here but make sure you actually watch the video and follow all the steps
and makes you got everything right before posting to the Q&A forums.
In case you ran into something or forgot to step.
Thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next lecture