Hello everyone.
Welcome to the post postscripts sequel Mac installation lecture video to start off.
Go ahead and open up your browser and go to W..
They'll be w that post.
Gresse sequel.
Org.
OK.
And go ahead and jump to the browser.
See you there.
OK here I am at postscripts sequel.
Or what you're going to go ahead and do is click download and when you go to download what you're going
to do is go ahead and scroll down and click.
Mac OS X and then you'll notice there's a graphical installer.
So go ahead and download that graphical installer.
You can go ahead and close any pop ups that happen.
So this will take you to the download postgresql page depending on what what say you go to.
It may be hosted on like Enterprise D-B dot com.
Don't worry about that.
It's just like some free hosting service.
So again you'll see download post sequel and then go ahead and click for the latest version.
At this point it's nine point 5.1 at the time of the filming of this lecture video.
Go ahead and download the latest version and then click.
Mac O S X..
So go ahead and download that.
That doesn't download you can always click here you'll download the DMG file.
Let's go ahead and save that and then wait for the download.
So I'll go ahead and jump to the Stallard being finished.
So now that it's finished downloading Let's go ahead and click on that file.
You'll go ahead and see that it's opening.
And so now that we have this open we can go ahead and double click this file and you'll notice you may
get a warning.
Here you can just go ahead and click the on me and then you can go and open that you may be prompted
for your password.
Go ahead and type that in.
Click OK and you'll notice it'll get the postgresql sequel installer running.
So you have a little set up wizard.
Just go ahead and follow the directions.
You can specify a specific directory where post-procedure will be installed.
I'm going to go ahead and go of the defaults here again David their victory just the default.
Here's the important part.
You're going to need to provide a password for the database.
Superuser.
Get into what a super user is later.
But go ahead and type a password here and retype it.
But make sure you write this password down somewhere.
You can go ahead and be the same as the password to your laptop computer or your just your Mac.
So go ahead and type in that password.
Remember you should write this down and you should remember it.
You'll get a port here.
Five four three two that it should be listening on.
Go ahead and leave that as the default and you may get some selection.
Go ahead and keep that the fault for the locale and then go ahead and click next and it's going to go
ahead and install that.
And you'll notice it installs it pretty dang fast.
So go ahead and let it happen.
This may take a couple of minutes and we'll go ahead and let that happen.
So you'll see a stack builder.
Go ahead and just don't install that and click Finish.
Now that we've installed postscripts sequel we're gonna want to install a PGE admin which is a GeoEye
or graphical user interface which is going to help us get things up and running quickly.
And it's one of the primary tools people use when working with a postgresql database.
So go ahead and go to w w w that PGE adamant that orch going to go ahead and jump to that my browser
now.
So PGE atom in the org should look something like this.
Go ahead and select download.
So you noticed you have various options here.
Go ahead and click here on Mac OSX and then get the latest version of PGE admin.
You'll notice you have some files to go ahead download the DMG file.
That's the PGR and files.
Go ahead and save that.
I'm going to go ahead and jump to when it's done saving.
And now that it's done it's go ahead and click on that file.
You'll get some license agreement.
Go ahead and agree to it and then you'll see it start working.
So once you have P.G. adamant three here what you're going to do is come down to Finder select new Finder
window.
And what you're going to do is take PGE adamant three and drag it into your applications and then let
it go there.
Once you've done that and you check your applications under your postgresql 9.5 folder you should CPG
adamant theory.
So then if you go ahead and double click that that should pop up.
And now you have the PGE admin 3 development environment.
So this is one of the main things we're going to be working in throughout the rest of the Course I'm
really working in a Windows environment.
So if you see me looking for files you will see a Windows Explorer you can just basically fall all of
the same actions in a Mac OS explore.
And what's really nice about PGE outman is it's basically going to let anyone they're using Windows
or Mac or Linux if you have PGE out of an available to you.
Everything is going to look the same.
So everything we're going to be learning about is going to be mpg absent.
So just keep that in mind.
OK.
So that's it for the basic installation.
What I encourage you to do now is check out how to restore a database in order to learn how to get all
the files and resources set up on your computer and have download the example database onto your computer
.
OK.
Thanks everyone and I will see the next lecture