Hello everyone and welcome to the Mac OS database setup.
So this lecture is going to show you how to use the zip file from the previous lecture and set up your
database for the course in order to open and extract the zip file you may need to download some free
software.
I personally recommend downloading WW.
Isaac Dotcom's file or software the AIs application that will allow you to open an extra zip files.
So again if you haven't already go back to the previous lecture and download from the resources section
the DVD rental that's it.
File.
If you're using a Mac and haven't downloaded it is it file or extraction software.
Could it delete WW.
Is it dot com.
Which I'll show you in just a second and download the isip program in order to extract zip files.
I should note sometimes the default archive utility won't work for this step meaning if you try unzipping
the file using archive utility the default for a Mac.
Sometimes it won't work.
So a quick note on the database are going to be using the common learning sample database.
This Aqeel a database known as the package.
Or put Jilla.
Depending how you want to pronounce it database for postgresql.
Couple of reasons why this is a great database one.
It's a really common database for examples and two it's really easy to use as a reference tool.
So that means if you look up online documentation more often than not they'll be using this particular
database to show off their examples.
Meaning since you've learned them this database throughout this course it's going to be really easy
to hop around two different examples.
If she's in a database you're already familiar with.
So this database kind of reflects a chain of DVD rental stores.
So it's also really easy to understand what each of the tables represents such as customers DVDs films
actors languages etc..
Ok once you've completed this lecture you can go ahead and jump straight to the lecture title challenge
restore a database to a couple of lectures ahead of this.
From that lecture onwards this course will be relatively Ogust at trial meaning whether using a Mac
or Windows everything should look exactly the same as far as the sequel queries are concerned.
With that being said lets go ahead and hop to my desktop and show you what you need to know and actually
go through the process of setting up our new database and filling it with the data we need.
I'm going to go ahead and jump to my desktop now.
OK so here I am at my desktop and what I wanted to show you that in case you don't have Zipp software
we should do is go to WW w the eyes dot com and scroll down and download for free.
This isip software is completely free so you don't need to pay for any sort of license here and it's
a really nice way to manage and unzip and extract information from that zip files.
Once you've done that go ahead and locate the DVD rental that zip file that you downloaded from the
previous lecture.
For me it's located right here on my desktop DVD rental.
That's it.
Go ahead.
Right click on it say open with don't use the archive utility default.
Instead go to other.
This will show you a list of all your applications.
Enable all applications.
Click.
I go down to the applications and then you should see isip after you've downloaded it.
Granted maybe you're using another Zipp software.
As long as you feel comfortable using that and everything works out the same as it does isip that's
OK too.
But let's go ahead and click open of isip.
And now we have DVD rental and you should see DVD rental tar.
That's exactly the file we need.
Everything's ready to go if he tried doing the same step with archive utility default.
You may have gotten a folder that looks something like this with a bunch of DJT files in a restore that
sequel file.
It's going to be a lot harder to use these files to restore the database.
So make sure that when you extracted the database it ended up giving you a tar file.
That's kind of important for the next step.
Again if you're getting something that looks more like this with the D 80 files and finally a restore
that sequel download I.
That's it.
And make sure you can extract it so that it looks like a duck tar file instead.
OK with that being said once we have that all set up on our desktop the next step is to restart database
mpg admin.
Go ahead and do command space and search for PGE admin then click enter to open it let's go ahead and
expand this a little bit so it's easier to see.
So this is a PGE admin should look like should have servers here.
Go ahead and double click on postscripts sequel 9.5.
You'll be prompted for your password.
Go ahead and put it in.
And if you don't want to be prompted for your password every time you can just click here and say store
password click OK.
They'll give you a warning about showing passwords.
Don't just say don't show this again and click OK.
All right.
Now we're ready to actually make a database where we can do is you can see already have a couple of
databases made here.
You will probably only have this post-crash sequel or postgresql database in order to create a new database
.
Go ahead and right click on database and click new database then just put in the name of the database
you want we'll call this new DVD database and then click OK once you've done that you should see the
new database pop up here.
Now if you go ahead and click on the dropdown menus you'll see schema public and then all the way down
here you'll see tables equals zero.
So that means what we do have a database.
You don't actually have any data in it.
So the next step is to do that is to use that tar file in order to fill out the data for our database
.
So we're going to do so if we go ahead and right click on new DVD database that database that we just
created.
Go ahead and click on restore.
You should see something like this pop up where format custom or tar and then file name what you're
going to want to do is go ahead and clear that.
And once you've cleared that file name go ahead and then click on these three dots.
And what you want to do now is figure out where a DVD rental the tar file is.
So for me it's on my desktop.
But if we actually look to where my desktop is it's actually presented as a drive or a device.
So it's going to be listed under devices here under DVD rental suffuse.
If you use the isip application program to do this they'll probably be under devices if you use something
else.
It'll be wherever the DVD rental that zip files located.
Go ahead and find the tar file.
If you can't click on it it's because you haven't enabled it as selectable.
So go ahead and go to enable all files and then you can go ahead and click the tar file here then click
open and then just click restore.
You should see some messages pop up and then if process return exit code 0 means you're done.
Go ahead and click on here.
And if we go ahead and refreshed this database so new DVD database go ahead and click refresh.
And now if we scroll down to the tables you have all the tables available to you and your database is
now full of data.
So just to make sure everything's working correctly.
Go ahead and click new DVD database or whatever you decided to name or database.
Click here on the little magnifying glass that says execute arbitrary sequel query.
You should see something that looks like this and go ahead and say select space Asterix from actor semi-colon
and you actually don't have to uppercase select and from and we'll show you how to do these sort of
queries later on.
But if you just go ahead and select this execute query this play button and if you get data output coming
out of this.
So down here if you get data output that means everything's ready to go and you're more than ready to
go ahead and tackle the rest of the Course now.
Now you can go ahead and feel free to jump directly to the challenge lecture and the child's lecture
is just going to ask you to basically repeat all the steps we just did in order to practice for storing
a database.
Go ahead and don't worry about saving that queery for now.
As a quick review let me just go over everything we just did to restore this database.
OK let's quickly go over all the steps you just did it for creating that database.
You had to download a DVD rental that zip file from the previous lecture download or already use your
favorite zip application file to extract stuff from that zip files.
I recommend going to w w w dot izip dot com.
Then open an extract DVD rental tar file from the DVD rental a zip file using ise it.
Then you had a search for PGE adamant three and open it.
Then you had a double click on postgresql 9.5 to go ahead and see those databases dropdown.
Then right click on the database's icon and then select new database and then you could have been naming
your new database and then you select one that was for creating a database.
After that we restored the database there.
To do that you had to right click on that new database and select restore you to find the path to the
DVD rental that tar file and remember to enable all the file extensions.
Then you have to select it and click on the restore.
After that we had to just click the refresh button with your database selected and then you should now
be able to see the table 15 in the dropdown menu of your database and you can test this like we just
did by executing an arbitrary siecle query on the database.
OK so all these steps are lined up for you.
In both the previous lecture and then the next lecture is a quick article summarizing what we just did
.
OK so if you have any questions go ahead and ask a discussion question.
Sometimes installing and restoring these databases can be tricky.
So always feel free to ask any discussion questions.
All right.
Thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next lecture.