Hello everyone and welcome to this overview on creating databases and tables section of the course in
this section of the course we're going to be learning how to create database and tables and manipulate
the data inside of them.
So previously in the other sections we've been mainly reading from tables or databases where the data
is already in there and it already exists.
We've been learning how to read data from them.
So in this section we're going to focus on is how you actually create those tables and insert data into
those tables and cells using sequel syntax.
So if your profession or job has some sort of analyst is going to mainly consist of just reading from
tables you're not actually ever going to have to input your own data through sequel syntax directly
.
This entire section may not be super useful but it will help you build a better understanding of how
these databases and tables actually interact with each other.
And Ill even give you a good understanding of how web application databases work.
So a quick note.
Many of the concepts in this section are interconnected.
Meaning it's a bit difficult to teach them in any sort of proper order.
And the what I mean by that is let's say there's concept a concept B there's no real order to cause
it.
A first is concept B second because you kind of need to learn both of them at the same time in order
to use one or the other.
So keep that in mind if a video alerts you to something that will be addressed in more detail in a future
lecture.
So if there's ever a situation like this you'll hear me point out don't worry we're going to learn about
this topic in a future lecture.
However I have tried my best in order to present all the data and all the lectures in a straightforward
and orderly manner so that straightforward and orderly matter is going to start like this.
We're going to start at understanding data types in a little more detail.
Now we're also going to go over what primary and foreign keys are in more detail then we practice creating
tables and manipulating the data rows inside of them and then we'll learn how to manipulate entire tables
.
And then finally we're going to end some more in view of some constraint concepts and we'll cover what
constraints are in a future lecture.
So quick note.
This section will really focus on challenges too much because a lot of the syntax in this section is
actually going to correspond exactly to what you would expect for normal phrasing.
So for example of a challenge question asked Oh create a table called Test table.
Well a lot of the syntax really matches up and basically says exactly what it does.
So the answer to that question would just be create table test table and you're going to notice that
as you go along.
Let's say there's another question that says oh insert these values into a table.
The syntax for that is actually going to be insert blank values blank.
So this entire section doesn't really lend itself well to challenge questions because the questions
that essentially just give away the answer.
So this entire section is really more to beef up your own knowledge and just build an understanding
of how databases and tables are created and how they work.
So as always feel free to ask any discussion questions for hints tips extra resources or information
or to clear up any confusion on any of these topics.
With that being said let's go ahead and get started.
Thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next lecture