Hello everyone and welcome to the data types lecture in this lecture we're going to learn about postscripts
sequel data types including Bulleen character number and a bunch of other data types.
So to be more specific postscripts sequel supports the following data types supports boolean data types
meaning true or false character data types number data types temporal data types such as date and time
related data types and then some special types which are like geometric data types an array data types
.
So we're going to need to specify what kind of data type a column should have whenever we are creating
tables which is why we're learning about data types.
More specifically right now.
We've actually already interacted with quite a few of these data types.
When we were looking at reading from a table.
Well let's go ahead and review them all.
So we can understand how to use them we're actually creating a table.
And the reason we have data types to begin with is to make sure that if someone is using your database
they're not able to insert the wrong data type into a column where it doesn't really belong.
So let's go ahead and start off the boolean data type the boolean data type and hold one of two possible
values either true or false.
And in case the value is unknown then the null value is used just a blank.
And you can use boolean or bool keyword.
When you declare a column that has a boolean data type so I'll be letting you know what the keywords
are that we'll be using when we declare a column.
Now I know we haven't actually declared a column yet or create a table.
So just keep that in mind.
Well we visit these words we're actually creating those tables that boolean or bull is the key word
for a boolean data type.
So when you insert data into a Boolean column post-procedure will convert it into the boolean value
.
So for example if you input a one a yes y or T are true.
Those are all converted to true.
And if you were to input a zero or no and false.
Those were all be converted to false data types in post-career sequel.
When you select data from a Boolean column postscripts sequel displays t for true F for false and a
space character for NULL.
Now about character data types postscripts sequel has three types of character data types.
One is the single character.
C H A R and then the second one is the fixed length character strings c h a are of some value and some
number if you insert a string that is shorter than the length of the column postscripts sequel will
pad spaces mean it is going to add some spaces there.
And if you insert a string that is longer than the length of the column post-career sequel issue an
error.
So the reason you may want to use a fixed length character string is to make sure that a user isnt able
to put in a string of characters that doesn't belong there.
So you may think of this as maybe you have a certain number of expected letters for some sort of ID
code and you don't want the user to be able to mess that up.
Then you also have variable length character strings.
The A R C H A are with some and number there.
And then you can stirrups two characters of variable length character strings and post-career sequel
does not have spaces when the string is shorter than the length of the column.
So basically the differences here between fixed length and variable if correct strings is fixed length
character strings postscripts sequence always going to make sure that they're all the same length either
it's going to pad spaces or the clear and air if the item you're trying to insert is longer than the
length that's allowed for variable length character strings you can store up to end characters of variable
length.
So end is just the limit.
And in that case postgresql equals not going to pad spaces so a variable length character strings are
really useful for people's names where you don't know how long they're going to be.
But you will set some limit so someone can't just write in a name of thousands of letters long.
So you can go ahead and revisit the like customer column and check out the variable character names
for their first and last name.
OK so moving along from the character data type we have the number data type and post-career sequel
provides two distinct types of numbers integers and a floating point numbers for integers.
We have three separate types of integers.
We have a small integer and the type you declare is just small ints and it's a two bite sized integer
that has somewhere between the range of negative 32000 768 and positive 32000 767.
Now we have an integer declared I N T which is a 4 by integer that has a range of those two numbers
there.
And my apologies.
Actually just quickly edited there was a typo there that should have been positive so from negative
this number to positive this number and this number is actually just 2 to the power of 31 saying go
out and check that out yourself.
And then the third integer type is cereal and cereals the same as integer except that postscripts sequel
will automatically populate values into the column automatically.
So basically what that means it's kind of similar to something US auto increments attribute in some
other database management systems but it's just a way to keep a running tally where the integer is populated
automatically so it keeps incrementing the pending how you define it.
And we'll explore that later on.
OK so for the floating point numbers we also have three types.
We have a float an ad that declares a floating point number whose precise precision is at least an up
to a maximum size of 8 bytes so that's the actual storage size 8 bytes in memory of the database.
Then the second type is real.
Or you can also use flow 8.
And it's a double precision meaning 8 by floating point number.
Then you have numeric or you can also use numeric P com s and that's a real number with P digits with
X number of them after the decimal point.
And if you want the exact numbers so pretty much perfect precision as at least as far as you can get
it you can use the numeric with the comma.
Nothing that's going to be the exact number.
OK so after that we have temporal data which stores date and time information or date and time related
data.
We have the date which stores date data or just time that stores time data or we have the time stamp
which is the one we've been working a lot which stores a date and time data interval stores the difference
and time stamps.
And we also have time stamped TC.
In other words we've been working with that stores both time stamp and time zone data.
So these basically just build off of each other so you combine day and time to get time stamp.
You can use interval to store the difference between time stamps and then you take time stamp and at
time zone data to it and you get time stamped.
TC OK.
So that's it for the data types.
Knowing them is going to be useful in creating tables or inserting data into tables.
So don't worry about memorizing all these right now.
Usually you just reference the documentation but we're going to slowly build our understanding of these
as we insert data into tables and create tables.
OK.
With that being said thanks everyone and I will see you at the next lecture