Hello everyone and welcome to the lecture on primary and foreign keys.
So in this lecture we're going to learn what primary keys are and what foreign keys are and what they
actually mean in a sequel database.
We're going to see some brief examples of using them to create columns of tables but we're going to
go over the table creation methods in much more detail in the create table lecture That's coming up
next.
So in the previous lecture we learn about different data types.
And in this lecture we're going to learn about primary keys and foreign keys.
And those are two concepts we're going to need to get down before we actually check out the syntax of
how to actually create tables in sequel.
So don't worry too much about understanding the sequel text examples in this lecture.
Worry more about just fundamentally understanding what a primary key is and what a foreign key is.
And these are actually pretty simple concepts.
So it should be pretty straightforward.
So let's talk about keys and start off a primary key a primary key is a column or a group of columns
that's used to identify a row uniquely in a table.
You define primary keys through pipe primary key constraints.
And we'll talk about what a constraint is and how that it relates to a column when you're creating a
table in more detail the next lecture.
But just to understand that you have to declare some sort of constraint when you're actually creating
the table so a table can have one and only one primary key.
It's a good practice to add a primary key to every table.
And when you add a primary key to a table in post-career sequel what happens is you create a unique
index on the column or a group of columns used to find the primary key.
So let me go ahead and discuss a little more hands on what this actually means as far as the primary
key is if you recall back to the customer table or like a payment table specifically in the Customer
table we had columns such as customer ID first name last name emails etc..
So the primary key for a table of that sort like a customer table would be the customer ID column.
And that's because that specific column the customer id value will uniquely identify that specific row
for the customer and that's different than the other columns because users can share first names right
.
So you can have one user name that John Smith and another user named John Roberts or something like
that.
And since they both share the first name John.
It's just possible the other customers also have the first name.
You don't want to use the first name as a primary key.
Instead you'll use the customer ID as a primary key in order to uniquely identify all your customers
.
And that's really the basis of what a primary key is.
It's designed to uniquely identify each row in that table.
And that's why it's good practice to add a primary key to every table in the database we've been working
with pretty much all the primary keys usually have some sort of underscore ID.
And another topic to think about when you're creating primary keys as far as data types.
A lot of times she'll be using a serial data type because it will basically auto increments.
When you add a new row to your table.
So that's something to keep in mind right.
You want to basically oh I'm adding a new customer.
This will be customer number two.
Oh another one.
Customer Number three four etc. so that ensures that you're going to keep them unique as you go along
.
OK.
So that's the main idea of a primary key is to uniquely and the that row in the table.
So let's go ahead and see a little bit of syntax.
What it might look like for adding it.
So normally we add the primary key to a table when we define the table structure using create table
statements.
Now I know we haven't actually seen this create table statement and we're going to go over it in much
more detail the next lecture.
But just think of this kind of like a preview of what it looks like when you're creating a table and
sequel.
Your basic syntax looks like this.
You say create table statement then you can put the table name.
You go ahead and just put in whatever table name you want.
And basically what the statement is going to start doing is it's going to say create this table and
then we have a set of parentheses here and then you're going to say the desired column name you on that
table the desired data type and then you're going to have a constraint.
So usually the very first column will be your primary key column.
So you'll have a primary key constraint and that basically says OK this column needs to be the primary
key of this table and there's other constraints such as like unique or not null.
And we'll go over those constraints in much more detail in the next lecture.
But I want you to kind of just get a sneak preview slash understanding of the sequel syntax that we're
going to see in much more detail next lecture.
But this is how you would at least show or define a primary key table when you're creating a table.
OK so moving on let's talk about foreign keys.
A foreign key is a field or group of fields in a table that uniquely defies a row in another table.
So in other words the basics is a foreign key is to find that a table that refers to the primary key
of the other table.
So what that means is just a foreign key is a feel or group of fields so a column or a group of columns
in one table that happens to be a primary key of another table.
So the table that contains the foreign key is called referencing table or child table and the table
which the foreign key references is called the referenced table or parents table and a table can have
multiple foreign keys the pending on it's relationships of other tables.
So that basically makes sense because let's say we have a table such as the payment table where we have
a payments ID that would be the primary key of the payment table.
So uniquely identifies every single payments but you may also have the customer ID in that same table
but you'll have many instances of the same customer making a unique purchase right.
So then that customer ID in the payment table is a foreign key because it's the primary key in the customer
table.
And that's basically it.
So that foreign key is a primary key of another table.
So it references another table or as a child of the other table and the other table is the reference
table or the parents table.
So in postscripts sequel you define a foreign key through a foreign key constraint.
And I know we haven't actually gone over constraints really well here but just keep that in mind it's
just to get you some vocab our vocabulary as you go to the next lecture.
So this foreign key constraint indicates that values in a column or group of columns in the child table
match with the values and a column or group of columns of the parent table.
So we say that a foreign key constraint maintains referential integrity between child and parent tables
.
So it's good to have these references in place.
OK so we know a foreign key is a field or group of fields so a column or group of columns in a table
that uniquely identifies a row in another table.
So let's go ahead and explore this just quickly threw it to table example.
Let's say we have a table named s o headers here on the right that stores sales order header's information
.
And let's say it stores information such as some sales order ID as the ID column A customer ID and a
ship to address column.
So we have some ID and we'll have this be the primary key of the S-O headers table.
And they have a customer I.D. and they shipped to a column and then we have some items table.
So we have some sales order line items table called SBO items that's a table here on the left.
And here we're going to have some other columns item ID sales order ID or S-O ID product ID some quantity
and some net price.
And so what happens here is we can create a reference in order to link these keys together.
And so what that means is we can basically say in this as Items table or the sales order items table
the column s o id or that Sales Order ID is going to reference the Primary Key ID s o headers and that's
really all there is to it.
So this ID is a reference to the Primary Key ID.
Here are the headers and then in the items table we have item id being a primary key S-O items.
And we can actually also have both of these be primary keys as a group so you can define both item id
as so id to be primary keys to two columns or that group of columns the primary keys of the items table
with SO Id still referencing the ID column of the S-O headers.
So Explora later on we're creating I am tables how to actually produce these how to make these constraints
work.
But the main idea here is just to understand how a primary key uniquely defines a row and a table and
then how a foreign key is just a field or group of fields in a table that uniquely than the size of
row in another table.
OK.
So that's really all there is to it as far as what we're going to cover in this lecture later on we're
going to explore how to expand the idea for references of keys when actually creating tables.
OK.
So that's it.
And I will see it the next lecture where we're going to actually go through the syntax and see some
examples of.
Create table statements.
Thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next lecture