Hello everyone and welcome to lecture on creating tables using the create table statements in this lecture
we're gonna learn how to create tables directly in a sequel editor by using the create table command
.
So previously you've already seen how to use the UI in the very beginning to restore a database and
fill in data.
And throughout this section we're going to learn how to actually use a sequel editor to interact and
add things to the database.
So here we're going to learn how to create a table.
So if you are using a direct sequel editor or you are using the command line to interact with your sequel
database you could use these type of commands in order to create tables in your database.
So to create a new table and postscripts sequel you use the create table statement and that's going
to look like this as far as the basic syntax you have create table than your table name.
And then in print seizure of say the column name then the type you'll have a column constraints comma
and then some sort of table constraint.
So and then you can also inherit from an existing table mean you inherit properties from an existing
table and we'll discuss this as we show you examples later on.
Bosko to break this down just a little more line by line.
So if we look at this first line first you specify the name of the new table after the create table
clause.
So for example if you're trying to recreate the customer table you would say something like create table
customer.
Next you're going to list the column name its data type and column constraint so you can have multiple
columns in a table.
That just means each column separated by a comma and I'll show you how to do that later on.
But basically you just have a bunch of these statements separated by columns and each are separated
by commas.
Excuse me and he said those have to be a column itself.
So the call constraints define the rules for the column and an example one is not null and we'll go
through the various types of column constraints and just a little bit but as far as this next step you
just listing the column name its data type and then its column constraint.
Then after the column lists you define a table level constraint that defines rules for the data in the
table.
So you have the column name the data types the column constraints and then some table constraints.
After that you specify an existing table from which the new table inherits.
So it means the new table contains all columns of the existing table and the columns to find in the
create table statements.
So you actually don't need to inherit from another table but sometimes it's a lot easier if you already
have a table to go off of to build a new table.
So just keep that in mind that last part is optional and it really depends what you're trying to do
and what kind of table you're trying to create.
So continuing on let's go ahead and go over some basic postgresql sequel column constraints.
So there's not NULL can be an example of a column constraint and that basically means the value of the
column cannot be null.
So if you're inputting values into that column you cannot input null.
So that's a great way to make sure if someone's using your database they can't skip or not put anything
into that column or that row.
Then there's unique and that's a common constraint meaning the value of the column must be unique across
the whole table so you can imagine that's useful when you need those unique values.
However the code can have many null values because post-career sequel treats each null value to be unique
.
So just keep that in mind that even if you have unique as a column constraint you could have many null
values because post-career sequel's treating each specific null value to be unique.
And notice that the standard only allows one null value in the column that has the unique constraint
.
And we have some more column constraints so we can use.
And those are primary keys one of them.
So this constraint is a combination of not Noal and unique constraints so you can define one column
as a primary key by using a column level constraint.
And in this case the primary key contains multiple columns so you must use the table level constraint
and we'll explore table level constraints.
After we finish all the options of column constraints.
So so far we have not null and that constraint is that the value of the column can't be null.
We have unique and that value of the column must be unique across the whole table.
And then we have primary key meaning this constraint just a combination of not Molen unique constraints
.
So you can define one column as primary key by using a column of a constraint and then moving on we
also have loops.
The check constraint and check enables to check condition when you insert or update data.
So for example the values in the price column of the product table must be positive values and then
you finally have references as a column constraint which constrains the value of the column that exists
in a column in another table.
So what that means is that basically use references to define the foreign key constraint.
So you can just think of references as defining the foreign key constraint.
And then as far as table constraints go they're basically similar to column constraints except that
they're applied to the entire table rather than to an individual column.
So again if you can say unique column list to force the value stored in columns listen inside the parentheses
to be unique and then you can say Primary Key Pass a column list to the find the primary key that consists
of multiple columns and then you can also use check in references in a similar manner.
So I think all of this may be a little difficult to digest if you're just seeing slides.
So we're going to do actually show you some examples of creating tables directly in a sequel editor
.
So that's probably going to be the most useful way to actually learn this type of information.
So we're going to go ahead and do is walk through an example of creating a table or we're going to create
the following tables will create a simple rule table which has a role ID and a role name and you can
note that the data types are defined there as well.
We'll have an account role table and then we'll have an account table.
So let's go ahead and jump to P.G. adamant.
Create a new database and then start creating these tables directly through the editor.
OK I'm going to go ahead and jump to you Adam now so we can get started.
OK so here we are at PGE admin and we're going to do is go ahead and you can create a new database for
these tables to go in.
Or you can actually just put them into the database.
We've been working with DVD rental so that's kind of up to you.
Let me go and review with you how to create a new database so we're just going to go ahead and right
click on database then click new database and let's go ahead and call this I don't know learning database
whatever you want to call it click OK we'll go ahead and create that database for you.
So here we have learning and then go ahead and double click it.
And then once I have it selected I'm just going to click here and execute arbitrary SQL queries and
now I'm going to go ahead and write the sequel queries to create the databases create the tables Excuse
me do we have our database created.
Let's go ahead and create tables for it.
First table we're going to make is that account table and that account tables can have a few columns
to it.
It's going to have a user id a username password email a created on column and then the last logged
in column.
So let's go ahead and get started.
So first thing I need to write is creates table and then I put in the table name.
So in this case we're going to call this table account and then I have an open parentheses and I'm going
to start putting in the columns.
So again the syntax for this is the column name.
So the first column will call a user underscore ID then we're going to have some sort of data type.
So the first data type we're going to use here.
If you recall from the integer data type lecture or the lecture on data types in general I'm going to
go ahead and use cereal and remember that one kind of auto increments or is the same as auto increment
and some other sequel engines.
So that's basically makes sense because when you add new users I want to make sure they have their own
unique ID and it keeps automatically incrementing so I'm going to use cereal there.
And I'm going to label this as primary key and then the next column we're going to have is username
and the user name is going to be some characters right so needs to be a character data type and we're
going to go ahead and say it's going to be variable characters since we don't know what people's names
are going to be beforehand.
We just need to set a limit.
So remember that was a R C H A R and then in parentheses you set some sort of limit.
Will go ahead and limit it to 50 characters and then we have some column constraints this call constraint
.
Let's go ahead and make sure it's unique that way we don't get user names confused so you can imagine
when you're logging into a web site.
Sometimes they say oh this username has been taken already.
So here if unique I can help that happen and then I'm going to go ahead and also put not null as a constraint
to make sure they just don't leave it empty.
And you can kind of start to get this idea of what these sequel database actually look like on the back
end of some sort of web service or application.
As you build and create these tables Let's go ahead and make another one.
Another column that is we'll call it password and password is going to go ahead and be let's say V-A
are some variable character again.
We'll give it a limit of length 50 and we'll say it just can't be not.
No it doesn't really matter if people's passwords are the same right.
We just want to make sure the usernames aren't the same.
So then we'll have their e-mail as another column and we'll also make this variable character else go
ahead and make this a lot longer.
These e-mails can be a lot longer we'll just say 300.
Let's say three in a 55.
Doesn't really matter for this case.
I mean it's up to you.
And let's go ahead and make sure they have a unique e-mail and that they don't leave it empty.
Just not know the will.
Let's go ahead and say we have to import all data types.
So we have created an underscore on a column and that's going to be a time stamp and we'll just make
sure it's not null.
Meaning we need to know when they created their account and we'll have a last log in column.
So we know when they last logged then and I will also be a time stamp data type and then we're just
going to close that parentheses and put a semicolon there.
Let's go ahead and run this.
And it said query return successfully if no result.
So that makes sense because we just created a table we're not actually asking for anything.
So let's go ahead and make sure this actually all worked.
So if I go back to P.G. admen and then on the learning if I go ahead and refresh that selected object
I'm going to extend schemas go to public and you'll see here that at tables we have a new table account
perfect so account table has been created.
And if we want to we can expand tables expand the count and actually see the column names that we just
created.
So that's how we can create a basic table.
We have some constraints in postgresql so you can realize it's actually really easy to work with post-career
sequel.
So again it's just create table the table name overprint CS and then you pass in your columns that you
want and it goes the column name the data type and then you're going to have the column constraint.
And then if you want Additionally you can have table constraints or inherit from another table.
But this is just the basics here.
You say create table the table name parentheses.
Then you gonna have a list separated by commas of all your column names.
Just expand that.
Notice here there's a basically a pop up here so you can like expand and contract this but you have
a user id the column name the data type for that column and then the column constraints and you can
go ahead and reference either the documentation or the presentation that's actually going to be as a
resource attached to this lecture.
OK.
So let's go ahead and creates another table.
So I'm going to go ahead and delete that and let's create the rule table that consists of two columns
just the role ID and a rolled name.
So we'll say creates table rule.
Open parentheses so I create my table a table name and then go ahead and think for a second before you
start typing this.
What is this actually going to look like.
Numbering in any kind of three things in this list.
I need my column name the data type and then the column constraint.
So will have role id enrolled name as column names so have role underscore ID as my column name space
the data type here.
Again I'll use cereal because it's convenient integer type that just makes sure I can increment that
roll ID and then them and go ahead and say primary keys.
So I'll have that be the primary key of this table and then I'll have another column called the roll
name.
And who knows what their actual roles name is going to be.
It can be like CEO janitor who knows.
Programmer et cetera.
So let's go ahead and make that a variable character length.
Let's say 2 5 5 and we'll make sure that they have a unique rule name and that the rule name is not
null.
Actually that's going to be it for the column.
So let's go in and close off that parentheses put a semi-colon in and go ahead and create that table
.
So queer returns successful if no result.
Let's go ahead and make sure that the table is created.
So if we go back to the learning database click here and refresh the selected object.
Scroll down a bit you'll see tables here.
Now we have the account table and the role table perfect.
So now we have the account table and the royal table and now we're going to go ahead and create our
final table which is going to be a count roll and we're going to introduce a couple of new things that
we haven't touched on yet just to show you as kind of an example of what's coming but we're going to
use constraints and references and updates on actions just to show you how you can actually create tables
that update on certain actions.
So don't worry if you don't understand everything for this final table.
But this kind of almost like a sneak preview of what you're going to be able to do.
So on a create table call it a count underscore roll up in parentheses here.
And let's go ahead and define the columns I'm going to say user underscore ID which is call it an integer
or say not no.
Also have the rule ID will say integer not in hopes not.
No.
And then we'll have a grants underscore dates
time stamp without time zone.
And what I'm going to do now is go ahead and then say primary key
user underscore the comma rule underscore Id close parentheses.
And now I'm going to go ahead and put in some constraints.
So I'm going to go ahead and copy and paste this.
And you can go ahead and check out the either the resources or the next lecture for all the actual code
that we're going to be putting in here.
But let me go in and paste that in and then explain it.
I don't actually want to type it out for you guys because we haven't covered some of this stuff yet
but I just want to explain just a quick example of another method you could create a table that's basically
connected to other tables so let me go in and copy and paste this in here and there it is copied and
pasted.
And it's an example of using constraints.
So let me go ahead and examine this statement in a little more detail bador or if you don't fully understand
this because we haven't gone over a few of these things yet.
The main part to understand is just the first two examples we did creating a table table name the column
name the data type for that column and then the column constraint so as long as you understand that
you're good with this lecture and you can move on.
Well I just want to show you if this is just a quick simple fix or more complicated example of stuff
you could actually do later on.
So it's good to examine the statement just a little more detail.
We have the primary key of the account role table consists of two columns user ID and role Id meaning
this primary key we have user ID and role Id.
Therefore we have to use primary key table level constraint to define the primary key like this.
So because the user id column references to the user id column in the account table meaning the user
id column here is going to reference the user id column and the account table we need to find a foreign
key constraint for the user id column.
And that basically is what's happening.
Fight.
Go ahead and space is up for you here.
So we're saying create or constraint accounts rural user id foreign key we define the foreign key as
user id show you the references of where it's coming from.
So it counts user ID and then we have some other statements there in order to make that happen which
we haven't gone over yet.
But I just want to show you what's possible here.
If you're already some sort of database administrator you see things like this before.
This may be helpful for you and just showing you how postgresql does this sort of work.
But if we look at the seconds statement here we have the rule ID column references the Real ID column
and the role table.
And we also need to find a foreign key constraint for the Real ID column and that's what happening here
.
So we stay basically for these two.
We set the constraints of the foreign key.
We base it off the column that we defined earlier here and then we give it the reference so the references
just references the table name.
And then the column from that table.
And then we have some more.
There are some more keywords here with some possibilities for actions in this table and you update it
in the other table.
Again don't worry too much of basically what these lines are doing.
I just want to show you this as a bit of a precursor to what's going to come into the future as far
as what you should have gotten out of this lecture.
It's just the basics.
You should have learned how to use create table say the table name and then parentheses say the column
name the data type and then some column constraints.
OK with that being said we're going to have a quick challenge excuse me a quick challenge.
Coming up next just to make sure you understand the basics of creating that table.
OK.
So again don't worry about all this stuff right here that codes available for you if you want to check
it out.
But don't worry about it because we're going to discuss a lot of those things later on.
OK.
With that being said.
Thanks everyone and I will see you at the next lecture