Hello everyone.
Welcome to the create table challenge solution.
So we're just going to go through the solution for creating the table as a reminder of what the task
was and from the previous lecture you had to create a table to organize our potential leads.
And we had the following information to organize.
We had a customer's first name last name email.
Some sign up date and then the number of minutes they spent on the DVD rental site.
And I also mentioned that you should have some sort of additional ID tracker for these customers or
potential leads.
So let's go ahead and jump to P.G. adamant and code this out.
Now I want to just make a quick point.
There's lots of ways and you had a lot of flexibility in how you could actually create this table.
So if you didn't choose the same column names or the same constraints as I did don't worry as long as
you're actually able to create a table in a way that makes sense for solving the problem then you're
totally fine with that being said let's go ahead and jump to P.G. admin.
OK so here I am PGA minute already opened up a sequel Ed. And I opened it up in the learning database
.
You can see here I'm on learning.
But you can open it up in whatever database you want.
You can go out and make any database for challenges doesn't really matter.
So first thing you had to do was say create table statements so hopefully that was pretty obvious and
then you had to name your table.
So we'll choose leads as the new over a table and then the next step was to create a set of parentheses
brackets.
So my colon here.
And what's going to go in between all this are the lists the column names the data type they are and
then the column constraint.
So again we had to have some sort of user ID that was the very last thing specified but it should be
here the primary key column.
That's what it makes the most sense and given based off the other examples we saw earlier when we're
creating tables it makes sense that your ID column should be a serial data type in order to increment
and make sure that we add more IDs as we get more Sign-Up users.
So let's go ahead and specify this to be primary key comma and then we're just going to continue this
pattern for adding more columns.
So the next column and go ahead and call it first name.
This should probably be a variable character and it's up to you how long you want to define it.
Let's just say 50 as a standard really depends on your work environment as to what end values you're
going to choose.
You can go ahead and check documentation online or talk to your manager as far as what are acceptable
and non-acceptable and values there because there's a lot of flexibility there.
Your first name and let's go ahead and do the same thing for the last day in column of these potentially
so variable character let's call it 15.
And again I'm saying not no because I want to make sure that we still have those values as we go along
.
And then the next column we had an e-mail from the potential customer.
Let's go ahead and also have that be a variable character.
Well a bit larger right because it's an e-mail address not just the first or last name.
And for this I'm going to make sure that it's unique in addition to being not null.
And the reason for that is because I want to make sure we only get one Sign-Up per e-mail address so
I don't want multiple people signing up on the same e-mail address so you should have at least hopefully
realized that it should have probably been unique.
It's not it's not a huge deal but it's good to keep that kind of thing in mind when you're creating
these tables for a database.
Next up we wanted to track the minutes that the person is going to be there.
So for that we could have said something like minutes column.
Just call it a simple integer.
You could have auspice specified eight specified as some sort of floating point number.
This was up to you.
You have a lot of flexibility on this one because it was pretty vague as far as what the actual requirement
was for this.
Just the same minutes as an integer.
Make sure it's not known.
So we actually keep track of it.
And then finally we have a let's say Sign-Up dates.
Let's go and say it time.
Sign up TS for a time stamp and this should have been some sort of portal data type time stamp if you
wanted to add a time zone data to it.
That's fine too.
And let's go ahead and make sure this is not as well and that should basically be it.
So we go ahead and run this make sure it works out.
And here query returns success with no result.
So that makes sense since we just created the table.
So now we have our leads table with these columns with the specified data types and constraints.
So that was a simple example of how you could have done it again.
You had the flexibility could have changed the end values for the characters but hopefully it gave you
a general idea of what kind of things you should be accounting for beforehand.
So in general creating these tables in databases you really want to make sure that key elements of this
is that you kind of predict problems that may occur in the future before they actually occur.
So you want to predict things like people having the same e-mail address or people trying to put in
the same password or making sure that you have not Knolles in places where you don't expect where you
don't want there to be no values et cetera.
So it takes a lot of patience to kind of develop this attitude of OK.
Think of all the ways that user can mess up beforehand.
But that's kind of a big part of creating these databases and these data systems so keep that in mind
.
All right.
With that being said.
Thanks everyone.
Hope the challenge is pretty straightforward.
If not you can review the create tables lecture for a review.
OK.
Thanks and I'll see you at the next lecture.