Hello everyone and welcome to the inserts lecture.
So in this lecture we're going to learn how to use the insert command and then we're going to see some
examples.
So when you first create a new table it doesn't have any data inside of it yet.
So we've seen the create table command but after we create the table the rows are still empty.
So we've defined the schema that we need as far as the data types and the columns.
We don't actually have rows of data in it.
So the first thing you often do is insert new rows into that table and sequel provides the insert statement
that allows you to insert one or more rows into a table at a time.
So the actual syntax is pretty straightforward and you can see here at the bottom you have the insert
into table then some columns and then you have values so first you specify the name of the table that
you want to insert a new row after the inserts into clause.
So you always start off with inserts into then the name of the table you want inserts and you row and
then you follow that by a comma separated column list to start with some parentheses and then you have
the name of the columns.
Second you list a comma separated value list after the values clause.
So you're going to say insert into table a comma separated column list then you'll say values and then
the value list must be in the same order as the columns lists specified after that table name.
So for example in this in the example here below we have Column 1 column too.
So then value 1 should be expected to be inserted into a column on and then value 2 should be expected
to be inserted into column 2.
So the order there needs to match as you would probably expect to add multiple rows into a table at
a time.
Use the following syntax so we basically have a list of lists and those values say insert into table
.
The list of columns that you say values and then by parentheses you have a single list than then comma
Another set of prints is for another list of values and so on.
OK so to insert data that comes from another table you can use the insert into select statement as follows
.
You can say something like this.
You can say insert into table and then you'll say selects certain amount of columns from another table
and then you can also add some where condition.
So let's well see an example of how to actually do this later on in P.G. out of it and the sequel Ed.
.
So it'll probably be more clear when we actually see a written example of this.
But just keep in mind that you're allowed to insert data directly from another table.
So now that we've done that let's go ahead and go to PG admen to explore the insert statements.
I'm going to go ahead and open a PGE admin and open up a sequel Ed..
All right.
So here I am at PG admin.
Let's go ahead and review how to create a table in order to create a table for the insert into demonstrations
so it's going to review how to create a table we're going to say create table call this table link keep
an open parentheses.
And now we're going to have the column name the type and then the constraint.
So it's going to be this will be the primary key of some ID.
So we have the primary key to common there to separate that column also have a u r l and we'll say it's
a variable character 255 characters we'll call it not no.
But a common there will make another column called name have be a variable character will pass in 255
also call it not.
No.
I have another column called description.
Let's have it be a variable character 255 again 225 two fifty five doesn't really matter we'll have
no constraints on that one.
And then we'll have one more called Oriol.
Maybe that's a relationship or something and then we'll we'll have that be a variable character just
make that 50.
Again no actual constraints on that.
So we're going to create this table called Link.
It's going to have a couple of columns have an ID column as the primary key then a u r l column a named
column description column and and Ariail column.
So go ahead and run this.
Make sure it works out.
All right.
So looks like we created the table let's go ahead and make sure by saying select everything from link
and looks like we're good here so we have the idea that your real name is scription and this Ariail
column or well call them.
So let's go ahead and explore.
I actually use insert into the syntax.
Again looks like this.
I'm going to say inserts into the name of my table link and then the name of the columns actually want
to insert into.
So in this case all inserts a u r l and a name.
And then I'm going to say values and then I'm going to pass in a list of values here.
So we're going to say something like W.W. for the oral Google dot com.
So just a string there is a variable character.
And let's go ahead and then the name of that is just going to be Google.
Finish that list put a semi-colon at the end of it.
Go ahead and run it.
And looks like it worked out.
And keep in mind it's a reminder to insert a character data type.
You must enclose it in those single quotes if you're doing a number data type.
You don't need to do that.
You can just use a plain number if you omit any columns that accepts a null value in the insert statement
.
The column will take its default value as null and you can actually specify what default values it should
go to.
If you don't want NULL to be the automatic default value.
Let's go ahead and make sure this worked out.
Let's go ahead and say select everything.
All columns from link again are all rows I should say all columns in rows.
So select everything from link.
If I run this looks good here we have an ID integer a u r l and the name.
So remember that Id integer was a serial data type so it automatically put a 1 in there.
And if we do another one or do another insert automatically put in at 2.
So it basically automatically increments that value.
OK so that was a very basic example of insert into.
Again we just had to say insert into the table pass in the list of columns and then say values and pass
in the list of values.
Let's go ahead and do this one more time just to make sure we really understand it.
So I'm going to say again inserts into linked table.
We'll put in a u r l and a name again.
It's those columns.
Now we're going to say values and then we're going to pass in a list of values so let's put in another
web site let's just go ahead and say Yahoo dot com and then we'll call this name Yahoo.
Semi colons.
And that is go ahead and run.
That looks like it worked that out.
It's one row affected.
And let's go out and say select all columns from link.
Make sure it works.
And there it is again and note that that I.D. which is a serial data type automatically put in a to
value increments off of one from the ID.
So now we have the R L in the name.
So that's looking good and we have no values here since it defaults to know if we don't actually assign
a value to a column for that particular row.
Now let's take a quick look at how we can insert multiple rows at a time that can say something like
this will say insert into link.
Again let's just do the your all and name column values.
And in this case we're going to insert its multiple values or multiple rows I should say.
So let's go ahead and say that w that being that column and we'll describe that as being.
Let's go ahead and put in another list of values.
Let's go ahead and say W.W. Amazon.com and we'll call that name Amazon semi-colon there go in and run
.
That looks like it affected two rows.
And again confirmed that it worked by saying select everything from link.
And if we scroll down here at the bottom we have Google Yahoo and being Amazon on there.
So that worked out great.
Now to end this lecture.
Let's go ahead and see an example of inserting data from another table.
So in order to do this we'll have to create another table that is like the linked table and it's actually
really easy to do this in post-career sequel.
What we can do is we can say create table and the name of the tape table will say this is link copy
and then what I could do is again put in all the column values that data types the constraints or if
I wanted to be the same structure as another table.
There's actually a really nice shortcut for this and it's going to be say like.
And then the other table you want to basically copy the same structure from.
So I'm going to say create table link copy that's the name of the table we're creating.
And if you pass in parentheses like in another table name it will automatically create the table with
the same structure as the table you say like.
So if I go ahead and run this the query worked out.
So then let's select everything from the link copy table select everything from Link copy.
And you notice here we have the exact same structure as the linked table.
We don't actually copy any of the data from it but we do copy that schema of the structure of that linked
table.
So again that's just a really easy way of doing it.
All we have to do is say create table some new table name and then you say like in parentheses you put
in some old table name and that's the basic command for essentially just quickly copying the same schema
structure of an older table into a new table really convenient function.
Post-career sequel.
So I would suggest using that if you're planning on copying tables or what makes your life a lot easier
.
All right so now let's go over how to insert rows from another table.
So we'll go ahead and do this.
We're going to say inserts into it let's go ahead and insert into the link copy table.
And now we're going to have a select statement so we'll say select all the columns from link and let's
go ahead and add a where statement or where clause.
So we'll say where and let's go ahead and specify a particular road to put in.
So we know like we have being in there.
So let's go ahead and do that.
We'll say where we'll say where a name equals and we'll pass in being semi colon Let's go in and run
this.
Make sure it worked.
Looks like it worked out.
We affected one row.
So let's go ahead and delete this and we'll say selects Asterix from and we'll say link underscore copy
and if this all worked out we should have copied being and being that.
Notice that the ID integer here though got copied as well so even though we have one is that index the
ID integer was also copied from the original link table.
So keep that in mind.
You're going to copy that information as well.
Even if it's a serial data type.
All right.
So that was basically it.
As far as inserting into a table and inserting data from another table.
So let's go over real quick.
Everything that we just did.
So we said insert into suffer a basic insert into example or you can say it was inserts into and then
you had a say the name of the table you wanted to insert into.
So again to do that we could have just said insert into link then you pasand the list of columns you
want to insert into such as your name.
Use key word values and then you can passen imprint sees a list of values that lines up with the column
names.
So I'm going to go ahead and put in a couple examples here so we WSS say 8..
Now we'll have that be titled A.
Actually don't know what these Web sites are.
And then let's go and show you another example if I want to insert multiple rows.
You can do that.
Ampacity be there semi colon to go ahead and close that off.
We run that.
That's fine.
So that's how you insert values or multiple values into a table.
And again a quick review of how to insert data from one table into another.
You just say insert into and instead of doing this you can say the tape table you want to insert into
and then you have a select statement so you'll say let's go in and just select everything from Blink
.
Not even a word statement there so we're going to say insert into the link copy select everything from
link.
If I run that that should have affected all the rows and link copies.
So if we go ahead and check that out we'll say selects everything from blank underscore copy run that
.
And so now I have fully copied in again and I noticed I going to have repeats here because I basically
ran some of these twice but here's the a dominant B the value.
OK.
That's really all there is as far as using Insert into the field is probably unlikely that you're inserting
individual rows by hand but you never know more likely than not you're going to be using this knowledge
of how to insert into A postscripts sequel when you're thinking about database design in some sort of
application like a web app or something.
And it really depends on what your situation is what your application is and what you're trying to get
out of the database to how to how you're actually going to use these commands so in real life it's probably
unlikely that you're manually inputting or inserting individual rows.
But it is good to understand these basic syntax.
That way if you want to make some sort of automated call then you can actually build off your knowledge
of the syntax to put it in some code like maybe a Python script or something.
OK.
So that's it for this lecture.
Again go ahead and re watch it and review in case anything was unclear of how to insert into just individual
rows into it table or many rows and values into a table or from another table.
OK that's it for the lecture.
Thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next one