Hello everyone and welcome to the update statement lecture.
So in this lecture room to learn how to use the update statement to update existing data in a table
.
So we just learned how to use inserts into claws in order to insert data into a table.
But now we want to update it or use a condition to update that data in the table.
We can use the update statement along with a SET statement in order to do that and then we'll see some
examples in PGE admin of how to actually go about doing it.
But first let's go ahead and walk through the syntax so to change the values of the columns in a table
use the update statement.
And what I mean by change the values of the columns I'm talking about the actual rows so the rows are
the values of particular columns.
So in order to do this you can say update the table name and then use the set column equal to some value
.
So for example if you have update let's go back to the link table that we were working with throughout
this section.
You can say up they link sets.
And for instance we have the name column.
So I can say update link set name equal to and then I can put in a string there for some generic name
such as my name or my underscore name as a string.
Now add up all the rows are all the values of that name column to be equal to that string that my name
string.
Or you can also add a WHERE condition to that in order to only update certain rows.
So let's go in and walk through the steps one more time.
First you specify the table name where you want to update that data after the update clause.
So you have update and then you specify the table name.
Second you list the columns whose values you want to change in the set clause.
So you say update table set and then the columns he actually want changed the row values of.
And then third if you want you can determine which rows you want to update in the condition of the WHERE
clause so you can set some sort of where condition in order to only update certain rows of that table
or that column.
So let's go ahead and see some examples with the link table from the previous lecture.
If you don't have the linked table go ahead and go back and quickly create the linked table using the
sequel syntax from the previous lectures in this section.
OK.
So I'm going to go ahead and hop to PGE admen and check out the link table that we made earlier.
All right so here I am at Peachi admen I opened up the editor and I ran select Asterix from link in
order to select everything from link.
And you see here we have the URLs the names.
And we had that serial ID integer.
So let's go ahead and walk through a couple of examples of how to use the update clause in order to
up the data in this table.
So let's go ahead and explore something like this.
First they are going to say is updates.
Then you have the table names so going to update the link table and then you say set and then you're
going to have a column name.
So for instance we have the description column which is actually full of just nulls right now.
Empty.
So give us a set description equal to.
And now this just put a string here so I'll say.
Just let's go and say See Description
and then a semi-colon.
So what this should do is should update the link table and it's going to set all the values of the description
column equal to empty description.
So if we go ahead and run that it work.
So now let's go ahead and say select everything from LinkedIn.
So say select Strix from link and now if I check out my table you'll notice every single value of the
description column has been set to the empty description string there.
So you can imagine this is pretty useful if you want to update data.
Now let's go ahead and do an update using a where statements in order to specifically only update certain
rows of a column.
So let's go ahead and update the name column.
If the name starts with an A.
So capital we have Amazon and dot com and dot com and the names are Amazon.
So let's go ahead and update those specific descriptions so I'm going to again say updates the table
name this case the table name is link and I'm going to say set and let's go ahead and set the name column
actually that's go ahead and set that description column sorry we'll set that description equal to.
Let's go ahead and say name starts with an A.
As the whole string for that description.
And now I'm going to say well where the name column.
And let's go ahead and say where the name column begins and a.
So I'll say it were name like remember we have to use these wildcard operators so I'm going to say where
it has an a percentage sign.
So this basically means where the name is like and starts from a somewhere.
So what we should see is that you are Elle's in name values of WW II Ada a an Amazon Amazon.com Amazon
the description should change to say name starts with an A.
Let's go ahead and run.
That looks like it returned successfully.
So let's go ahead and check out what happened by selecting everything from links on them to say selects
Asterix from link.
Go ahead and run that if I start scrolling down you'll notice here in my description column for those
specific name and you are Ell's at the site that started with an A.
The description now looks like this says name starts today.
So now I can use conditional statements to update certain rows of my data so you can imagine that's
super useful depending on what your use cases are.
But I can conditionally update things in the table.
So not the data is not permanently set.
I can go ahead and update it and more conveniently I can update it based off a certain condition.
And one more thing I want to show you is that you can actually update the data of a column from another
column within the same table.
So let's go ahead and show you how we can do that.
That's going to be really similar except we'll just pass in the name of a table.
So I'm going to say update again the linked table and I'm going to set the description column set description
equal to and I'm going to go ahead and set it equal to the name column.
And as long as these two data types match up I shouldn't have any problem here.
So they're both very in character strings.
So let's go ahead and update the link.
We'll set the description column to be basically matching the name column.
So we'll go ahead and run that.
Looks like the query returned successfully.
So now let's go ahead and say select everything from we run that and now you'll notice that the Name
column and the description column are the exact same.
OK great.
One more thing I want to show you is that you've noticed after I run the update usually just in the
data output says Kurri ran successfully.
We can actually add a keyword term known as returning in order to return columns of the updated entries
so we can go ahead and show you an example of how that works.
So I'm going to go ahead and say update the table name which is link.
I'm going to go ahead and set that description column.
So set the description column equal to.
Let's just make it equal to some string called the new description.
And let's go ahead and specify where it's going to specify where ID.
So where the ID column is equal to 1.
So basically where the ID column here the ID integers equal to 1.
We're going to go ahead an update or update the set scription equal to new description.
So that should effect basically that first Google dot com entry.
And if we ran this just by itself it would have just said oh queries successfully run or run one entry
affected.
If I actually want to get the results back of the updated entries I can add another keyword and that
keyword is returning and I can go ahead and then state columns that I want to return.
So I can say returning ID you rl name description and that's just going to return those columns themselves
.
So let's go ahead and check this out.
And there it is.
So now we've able to instead of just seeing queries successfully run one row affect that etc. we can
actually get returned results and verify that the entries are updated.
Let's go ahead and verify this another way.
Again the key word is returning.
I'm going to go ahead and verify this another way just by saying selects Asterix from link.
And if I run that selecting everything from link if we look for Google here at the bottom we have Google
dot com Google and Lotus description instead of being the name it still need description.
So that returning did work and it did return the updated entries.
All right.
So that's really all there is as far as updating sequel.
Again as I mentioned earlier with the insert statements and other statements here in this particular
section of the course more likely than not you're not going to be doing these things manually.
You're going to be using this in conjunction with some other larger program or automated scripts.
But it's essential to understand how to do these things manually.
So you can later automate them.
OK.
So that's it for the update section.
Feel free to post any discussion questions in case you need any clarifications.
Thanks and I'll see you at the next lecture