Hello everyone and welcome to lecture on the delete statements.
This lecture we're going to learn how to use the delete statement to delete rows of a table.
So to delete rows and table you can use delete statement as follows.
You basically just say delete from the table you want to delete from and then you can actually have
a WHERE condition to specify what you're going to do.
So let's go ahead and break this down step by step.
So first you specify the table where you want to delete the delete from clause.
So say delete from the specified table.
Second you specify which row to delete by using that condition in the WHERE clause.
If you omit that where clause than all the rows in the table are going to be deleted.
So if you just type and delete from table ill delete all the rows again.
Delete the rows in a table you just delete statements like this.
So continuing on the delete statement returns the number of rows deleted.
If no rows are Athleta the delete statement is just going to return 0.
So you all know how many rows were deleted after you run your query or your delete statements.
So let's go out and see some examples in postgresql sequel.
It's pretty basic to get the hang of well let's go ahead and hop to PD admin and open up a sequel editor
there.
OK so here we are its sequel editor.
I'm going to go ahead and mess around the linked table that we've been playing with.
You can use any table for this but the link table is the one where these these examples are actually
going to work.
Now the delay statement is pretty straightforward so you shouldn't have any problem understanding it
at this point in the course.
So here I've selected everything from links so it can take a look at it.
And let's go ahead and just try to delete anything that starts a B.
So I'll say any DLI anywhere where the name column value starts B capital B that is.
So I'll say deletes from link so delete from the table name and then you have your WHERE statement for
some sort of condition and will say or name like and we'll just have it begin with a B.
So we have that wildcard in there.
Remember how to use that.
So let's go ahead and run that and so you'll notice Ill say quick return successfully two rows affected
.
So Ill tell you how many rows it actually deleted.
That's what it means by affected.
So all you had to say was delete from the table name and then some sort of where condition.
So if again we'd select everything
from link.
When you go ahead and run that you'll notice now I don't have anything that started with a B in the
Name column so I deleted all those rows and that's basically all there is to it.
As far as using the delete statements if you actually want to return the rows instead of just returning
the number of rows you can do that using a returning statement.
So we've seen a returning statement before.
Let's show you how to use it for delete from before we end the lecture.
Some of them do a simple example and let's go ahead and delete that.
Ada comment tree is something to say delete from a link and will say Where name will go ahead and say
equal to A so we don't want it to be like it was just because it on Dilley Amazon or anything we just
wanted.
There'll be no way that a dot com that row so I put in the condition and then I'm also going to put
in returning and I can request which columns to return.
So I can request something like your L name etc..
If I just put an asterix ill return all the columns for the row that was deleted.
So if I go ahead and run this it returns the row that was deleted.
So here I've seen this row is now been removed from my linked table.
So just to make sure that it was deleted if I select everything from Link run it.
Notice I don't have that A-road there anymore.
OK so that's really all there is to for a delete.
You want to check out some more complicated delete statements like using values from another table.
You can go ahead and reference the documentation for that.
OK thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next lecture