Hello everyone and welcome to the altar table lecture in this lecture room with Discover how we can
change existing tables structures even if the table already exists inside of a database and we can do
that using the ALTER TABLE statement.
So the syntax of the ALTER TABLE statement is as follows.
It's Boulter table the name of your table that you want to alter and then some sort of action statement
.
And there's quite a few different types of action statements.
So postscripts sequel in particular provides add remove or rename column actions you can set default
values for columns and check constraints to a column or rename the table itself.
So some of the keywords were going to be exploring our add column drop column rename column add a constraint
and rename to.
So these are all actually best explored through example.
So let's go ahead and open up a sequel Ed..
Make a table and then try altering it as we go along.
So I'm going to go ahead and jump to the editor now.
OK so here I am at the sequel editor Ed. Let's go ahead and create a table to work with.
So let's go ahead.
You may already have a table called Link.
If you have it go ahead and drop the table.
So say drop table if exists and link.
So if you have it or not this should work.
So I already deleted the or dropped the linked table so it says Link doesn't exist.
If you had it from some of the previous lectures go ahead and run the statement in order to get rid
of it.
Because what we're going to do is create a table called link so we can play around with it.
So we're going to say create table link and I'll just add three columns this table we're going to add
an ID column link ID that's going to be serial Primary Key going to add another column called Title
and there will be a variable character column.
Let's go ahead and just go off some byte sizes souls say 512 variable character size.
No.
Let's go out and have a u r l.
And again the sizes don't really matter that much of what we're passing in is a variable character.
And here in passing and some come column constraints.
So I just created a table called Link.
It has three columns link ID which is the primary key of this table and it's a serial data type meaning
it's like an auto increment data type.
Then I have the title column.
It's a variable character string data type with up to 512 characters in that string and it has the constraints
of being not null so it cannot be null.
And then I have the u r l column and it's also a variable character string.
Quite a few more characters are allowed and it's not nil.
And they also all have to be unique so they all have to be unique addresses.
So let's go ahead and discover how we can use alter table to play around and mess up or play around
and mess around with this table.
So to add a new column to a table you use the add column action.
So you're going to say ALTER TABLE the table name ALTER TABLE link and then you say add a column and
then what you're going to do is go ahead and add the column names so let's go ahead and make a call
a name called active and then you add the data type of the column.
So I going to say that it's a Boolean type column.
So if you are Ellas active or not you know true or false.
So if I run that we went ahead and said alter table the name of the table link at column the active
column and then we made a boolean data type for that column.
So if I go ahead and check this out let's go and explore it and go ahead and say selects all from link
and we shan't get any back.
We should get at least the column names.
So if you noticed on here now I have active boolean type column.
So I was able to alter the table that already exists.
So that's awesome.
Now let's go ahead and explore how we can drop that column.
And that's just going to be alter table the name of the table.
And you say drop call them and then the name or whatever column you want it drops so it's good it dropped
the active.
So it should return successfully if no results.
And if I just go ahead and say selects all asterisks from Link run that notice the active column is
no longer there.
So you want to rename columns.
We can do that as well.
So to say I have that title column there in the middle we can go ahead and rename it so we can say something
like alter table link we can say rename column and then use you pass in the column you want to rename
.
So let's go ahead and rename the title column.
Use the keyword to and then whatever you want to do so will say like new title name and go ahead and
run that.
So you say ALTER TABLE the name of the table you say rename column title to the new title name.
So if we go ahead and explore this let's make sure that actually work by selecting from the linked table
and notice now in the middle we have that and you title name column.
Great.
So let's go ahead and explore just a couple of more actions.
So one of these other actions we can take is actually going to affect the whole table.
So instead of just affecting one column we can actually like rename the entire table.
So if I say select all from Link run that I get that Beletski wanted to rename the linked table I can
say alter table link and then use the Q word rename to.
And this will rename the entire table so I can name this your L table your underscore table.
Run that.
So again it's alter table the name of the table renamed to and then the new table name.
And then we can go ahead and say selects Asterix from.
And if we try to do it from a link you'll notice link doesn't exist anymore because it's being renamed
to the real table.
And then we get the actual results.
OK.
So that's it for the basis of using alter table.
You can think of it as a nice way to alter columns and rename the table itself once a table already
exists in your database.
All right thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next lecture