Hello everyone and welcome to the drop table lecture in this lecture room to learn how to remove or
drop tables from a database in post-crash sequel.
So the syntax actually really straightforward.
If you want to remove an existing table from a database you use the drop table statement as shown in
the following below.
So you're going to say drop space table.
There's an optional if exists term and then you input the table name so that if exists term is an optional
statement which will help you avoid errors.
If a table doesn't already exist in your database.
So if you try to just say drop table some table name and table actually in your database you'll get
an error if you say drop table.
Table if exists and then some table name.
And even if that table is not in your database you won't get an error out.
So this is best shown by a couple of simple examples in postscripts sequel.
So I'm going to go ahead and hop over to a sequel editor from PGE adamant so we can explore this just
a little further.
All right so here I am at PGE.
Adam and Eve opened up a sequel Ed..
Let's go ahead and create a table real quick we'll say create a table the name of the table.
Let's go ahead and call this.
We'll just say it's called test to we'll name that.
Well let's go to like that and does it really matter in the table as long as it doesn't already exist
in your database.
So create this symbol table will have it have a column called Test Id just make it a serial column have
it be the primary key of the table.
So call and run that looks like it returned successfully.
So it does create in that table test to real quick.
And now let's go ahead and just make sure it actually exists will say select Asterix from when it was
called Test 2.
OK.
So notice we don't get any rows back but we do get that test ID column back so we know that table exists
.
Let's go ahead and explore how to drop the table.
So it's actually quite simple.
The syntax for dropping table again is just drop table and then the name of the table test too.
Now I want to go ahead and run that.
So looks at the query returns loof no result.
So let's go ahead and make sure the tables actually dropped by saying selects Asterix from test to run
that notice.
We get an error down here.
So it says error relation to underscore does not exist which makes sense because we just deleted or
dropped that table from our database so the drop table statement worked out perfectly.
Now I want to show you what happens and how to use it if exist statement.
So imagine I try to drop this table again so that the tables not in the database.
So we should get some sort of error here.
If I just say drop table.
So if I run that I will get the air table test to those not exists.
So they'll give you an error back if you just try to drop the table if you want to avoid getting this
error.
You can say if
exists test too.
And now if I run this query it will say a notice instead of a full error will give you a notice saying
table test 2 does not exist.
Skipping.
And then also a clear return successfully.
So it will execute the query give you a quick notice telling you that the table doesn't exist but it
won't throw back an error.
So if you have this sort of statement somewhere along in your code somewhere you won't just disrupt
your program.
It'll keep on going.
So again that's stropped table if exists.
All right.
That's basically it for the drop table.
You can check out the documentation.
There's another key word that's actually already automatically input but there's a key word that you
can put after your table known as restricts.
And basically what restrict does is restrict refuses to drop the table if there's any objects dependent
on it.
So postgres sequel use restrict that by default.
So just keep that in mind if you want to move.
Remove this table that has dependencies on it and you want to remove the dependent objects together
.
You can put in the keyword cascade.
We'll discuss cascade and restrict a little more because it has the pins a little more in like views
and constraints that actual tables themselves.
So just keep in mind if you want to drop a table and your table has constraints or the pendency is on
that or other objects that the pendant on that table you're trying to draw or it's use in some sort
of view that we haven't actually discussed yet with the view section is enough.
Further a section of course you can put in cascade.
So by default restricts will always be there so you don't actually have to say restricts if you don't
want to.
OK.
So you can go and explore documentation for a little more info on Cascade and restrict.
But right now all you need to know for this section of course is just say drop table if exists.
And then the table name.
OK that's it for this lecture.
Thanks everyone.
I'll see you at the next one.