Hello everyone and welcome to the lecture on the check constraint.
So a check constraint is a kind of constraint that allows you to specify a value in a column must meet
a specific requirement.
We've already seen constraints such as not know or unique use but check is a really useful constraint
to use on your columns.
The check constraint uses a boolean expression of some kind to evaluate the values of a column if the
values of the column passed that boolean check.
So it's going to be some sort of true or false check then postgresql insert or update those values.
Otherwise Ill return some sort of error.
This is actually really best shown through example.
So we're going to do is go straight to some examples by creating a table and applying those checks.
Let's go ahead and go to PG admin and I'm going to open up a sequel Ed. And we'll go ahead and make
a table.
All right.
So here I am at my Sequoia Ed. And what we're gonna do is go ahead and create a table and then we're
going to while we're creating the table we're going to add some constraints to some columns.
So it's going to create a table we'll call it let's just call it new users.
You underscore Users table you can really call it whatever you want and go and add some columns to it
.
So you always want to add a primary key to a table.
Let's go in and make a basic one which is called Id have it be a serial data type meaning it's an incrementing
data type and will have it be the primary key of the table.
Then what we're going to do is create a first name first underscore Name column that will be a variable
character string.
And let's go ahead and limit it to 50 characters and I need to put a comma here between that column
and that column passing a list of columns.
Let's go ahead and also put in a birth dates as a column and the birthday is going to be a date.
Type in Warga do is.
Now we're going to put a constraint on it.
So the constraint is going to be a check constraint and then we are using a check constraint you have
to pass some sort of boolean expression in parentheses here on that check.
So I can do something like this.
I'm going to say that birth underscore date meaning that column value needs to be greater then.
Let's go ahead and say 9900 the first day so January 1st meaning if we get a new user and the input
their birth date they have to have been born before after 9900.
So you've probably actually already seen this used in real life when you're reaching for a web site
and they ask you to input the year of your birth.
They usually can't go below 9900 which makes sense because it's extremely unlikely that anyone still
alive if you're born in 1899 or earlier.
So let's go ahead and explore how else we could do a check.
So imagine we have a nother column called join date and that's also going to be a date type column and
then I'm going to have a constraint on that as well.
I'm going to check that the joint date value is greater than the birth date value.
Whoops let me go to that typo.
The birth date value and what that's going to do is it's going to make sure this new user has joined
after they were born which makes sense you don't want those dates mixed up.
And finally let's go ahead and add another column just to keep showing you examples of how it could
use these date check or at least check constraints.
Let's go ahead and add a salary value.
We'll go ahead and have it be let's say an integer type just some number of their salary.
And we're going to check that that value salary is going to have to be greater than zero so they can't
make $0 or less.
So these are the kind of examples of what we can do with a check statement or a check constraint.
So again we put in the column name the data type of that column and then we add constraints to it.
And one of the constraints or folks on this lecture is that check constraints.
OK.
Let's go in and run this and let's say you have a syntax error and it's probably because I have an unbound
set of prints C's meaning I need to finish off that set of princes here.
Let me run that again.
And looks like we have our new table set up.
Let me go ahead and explore this by saying selects from New users apps new users.
And here we have ID first name birth date join date and salary columns.
So looks like those are all good.
Let's go ahead and try to insert a new row into the employee or into the new users table.
And what we're going to see is if we get errors based off our checks.
So again to insert into a table we say insert into we have our new users table and I'm going to insert
there.
Let's go ahead and sort of first name a birth date a joined dates
and some salary
and then we're going to do is save values.
So now we pass analyst values we're going to insert the values we're going to answer let's just name
this person Joe.
Let's say they were born in 1980.
February 2nd was really matter.
And then we were going to do is go ahead and pass in their joint date.
Let's say they join 1990 some other random dates of the year.
And what we're going to do is specifically impose a salary that doesn't make sense but try to put negative
10 as a salary and see if that works.
OK.
So here we get an error and it says new row for relation new users violates a check constraints and
it looks like the check constraint is based off what we were trying to input here on the salary check
.
And something that's really convenient about postscripts sequel is it automatically names the specific
constraint and it does it by it basically concatenates the table name new users with an underscore of
the column name.
And then it specifies check.
So immediately you have a good idea of what check it's failing.
OK.
So to review this entire topic let's go ahead and just create one more table add a simple check constraint
to it just so we fully understand.
So again you just say create table will have this be called check test whatever you want.
And then we're going to do is pass on a column name.
So it can say something like sales and this will be.
Let's go ahead and say an integer is the number of sales someone for that month and then we can just
say check and then some sort of check constraint.
So say sales has to be greater than zero.
So that's one example of a simple check constraint and something I wanted to point out is earlier I
mentioned that post-procedure will automatically conveniently named constraint check constraints for
you.
You can actually name these your own personal name and you can do that just by adding a keyword constraints
.
And this allows you to name constraints.
So we'll say we can call this constraint
positive sales and then the name of the constraint afterwards.
So if we go ahead and close that off so just create a table called check test has one column and it
sails into your type and I use the cuarto constraint to name my constraint that is this check constraints
to make sure sales is greater than zero.
So if I go ahead and run that then what we're going to do is go ahead and inserts into that check test
or that sales excuse me that check test table.
So I'm going to say inserts into check test and then what we're going to do is answer some valleys into
us into this table.
So let's go ahead and do that.
We can go ahead and say inserts into the sales column and then just the values we're going to do.
Let's go ahead and try to insert a value that is correct.
Make sure that works.
So it looks like one rose effect that that looks correct.
And let's go ahead and then try to put in a negative sales value column and notice when we get the air
they'll say violate checks constraints and now it's the name of the constraint that we chose.
Positive underscore sales.
So that might be a convenient feature for you if you're checking on later and you get an error.
You'd immediately know based off your description what kind of constraint error wasn't met.
OK.
So let's go ahead and just finish off the lecture there.
You can go ahead and check the documentation for check constraints.
Case you want to figure out how to use it in whatever application.
Try and develop whatever database you work with.
All right.
Thanks Ron and I'll see you next lecture.