Hello everyone and welcome to the not no constraint lecture in this lecture we're going to learn a little
more about values and the not null statements so in database theory no is unknown or missing information
is where you don't actually have a data point and that's different than an empty or a zero.
For example we can ask for the email address of a person.
And if we don't know we can input a null value there in case the person doesn't have any e-mail address
.
We could have also marked it as just an empty string.
And so that's kind of the difference between empty and no or a zero and null.
So for example if you have zero sales for the month that's different than just not knowing how many
sales you have for a month.
So there's a difference between that empty or that zero value versus a null value because the no value
just means it's unknown and it's missing information where you just have no idea if it's a hundred or
zero or empty or a thousand etc..
So that's really what NULL stands for in database theory.
The fact that you just don't know about that missing data point.
So postgresql provides the not null constraint to enforce a column that must not accept no values.
And we've actually seen this already before.
And basically what that means is that whenever you insert or update data you must specify a value that
is different from the null value.
Like I mentioned we've seen a constraint already used a few times foolishest explore a little more in
the editor and we're going to create a quick table and see what happens when we say the not no constraint
and try to add something that is a null just to get a better and quick understanding of how it really
works.
OK I'm going to go ahead and jump to the sequel Ed. now.
OK.
So here we are at the sequel Ed. Let's go ahead and create a table.
We're going to go ahead and say create table and you can name the table whatever you want.
Just make sure it's not already in your database.
We'll call this create table learn.
Let's just call it learn.
Underscore null because we're going to use it to learn null and it's going to have just two simple columns
.
The first one will be some first name call.
Let's say it just takes and someone's first name as a variable character string data type and the next
one.
Let's just say it's going to be some sales number and we always want to make sure that we always know
the sales.
And with that we don't have any missing data points there and what we're going to do then is put the
constraints on top of it that it's not.
No.
And so those are all columns we close off those parentheses.
Let's go ahead and run that.
So again we just said create table learn on the score nulls name of the table and we have two columns
a first name column which is a variable character type string and then we have a second column which
has a sales integer not null type string.
So now let's go ahead and inserts into that table.
So insert into learn.
Underscore no.
And then what we're going to go ahead and do is say let's go and insert into that first name column
.
But notice I'm not actually going to insert into the sales column.
So then we put in some values and I want to put it in my list of values in this case let's say this
person's first name was John and that's it.
So let's think of a second before we run this what's actually going to happen.
I'm going to say insert into learn null just into the first name column where values is the first name
John.
Now remember we also add that sales column and that had a constraint that it could not be null meaning
if I just insert this value here post-career sequel is going to try to fill in the rest as null values
because I'm not providing that data.
It's a missing data point here.
So I actually try to run this go ahead and run this.
Notice I get an error I get a null value in Column sales violates that not null constraint and that
failing RHO contains.
And you can see here how postgresql has filled it in as John and null.
So that's not no constraint is going to make sure that when you're inserting values into this table
as rows if you have a null value or a missing data point that not no constraint is going to throw up
an error if you try to do that.
So don't we actually put in some sort of integer for his sales number let's say sold 12.
If we run that notice Ill say more than target columns because when you specify appear the sales column
.
So now I want to say insert into learn null the first name column sales column.
So I have two columns matching two values John and 12.
So if I run that the query did return successfully one row is affected.
Let's go ahead and make sure by saying selects Asterix from LEARN.
Underscore null and there it is.
There's John offis 12 sales.
So really the main point is understanding two things from this lecture.
One is the difference between a null point in your database or just having a null as unknown or missing
information versus that the no value.
How it's different than just an empty or a zero value.
So that's one of the main things I want you to get out of this lecture.
How null is different than just an empty or zero.
Because if no you don't know you have missing information there versus an empty string or a zero you
actually have information.
It just happens to be empty or zero.
And then the second thing and once you get out of this is an awareness that if you put that constraint
of not null in a table when you insert something where you have a missing data point it will throw up
an error then that's the whole purpose of that not null constraint.
So it can be incredibly useful to make sure you're not missing any information when you're trying to
build some sort of larger application where users are putting in information into a table or a database
somewhere.
OK.
So that's it for a little more on the not.
No constraint.
Thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next lecture.