Well everyone and welcome to the unique constraint lecture.
So in this lecture we're going to learn a little more about the unique constraint which allows us to
make sure that the value in a column or a group of columns is unique in a table.
Sometimes you want to ensure that the value in a column or group of columns is unique across the whole
table such as like an email address a user name an employee I.D. etc..
PostgreSQL provides you with the unique constraint to make sure that the uniqueness of the data is maintained
correctly with the unique constraint every time you insert a new row.
Post Chris sequel's going to check if the values already in the table if it found that the new values
are already there it would give back an error message and reject the changes.
And the same process is carried out for the update existing data methods.
So let's go ahead and show a quick example in the sequel editor by creating a table specifying a column
to be unique and then seeing what happens when we try using the insert statement along with that.
Going to go ahead and jump to the sequel editor now.
All right so here I am at the sequel Ed. What I'm going to go ahead and do is create a table and let's
just go ahead and call this table.
Let's call it Persons.
Well let's call it people and just go ahead and give it an ID columns so we'll say Id cereal how that
be the primary key of this table.
We'll go ahead and have this person have a first name that just be a variable character string.
Give it 50 length Max and we put some commas here to separate these columns.
And the next thing to do is just go ahead and play it and finally email will have that variable character
.
Go ahead and have 100 link.
But the thing we're going to do is add the constraint that needs to be unique.
Make sure you spell this right unique.
OK.
So we have here is the ID column the first name column.
And this email column that unique constraint and that's going to make sure that every single value under
the email column is going to be unique.
So let's go ahead and run that.
So we execute that code looks good.
And now let's go ahead and try inserting a new row into the People table.
So we're going to say inserts into well good people and the columns we have to insert are the ID the
first name column and then the email column and we're going to email or excuse me we're going to insert
values and we're going to answer a list of values.
Let's go ahead and give them an idea of what we can actually leave this blank if we left that cereal
so we'll just put one was.
Go ahead and say first name is Joe.
And then let's give them some e-mail address.
We'll give them Joe Joe that come.
OK.
So we have that if we go ahead to run it.
Sic one rose effect then.
So let's go ahead and check that out.
So it's going to select everything from people so selects all columns from the people table and there
we have one.
Joe Joe Joe Lockhart perfect.
OK.
Now let's try to see if we insert some more of the same e-mail.
How would that work.
We should get an error.
So we're going to say insert into people go to specify the columns Id first name and email put in values
.
And we're going to go ahead and say to give this person another name will say we'll give this person
named Joseph and they're going to have the same e-mail address or at least attempt to have the same
you know e-mail address.
So we'll put a stream in here.
We'll give it Joe.
Joe come in if we go out and try to run this.
So notice that that e-mail is the same as Joe's e-mail.
So Joseph has the same email so if I tried to run this I get an error.
And now this is actually unrelated.
I need to put an s here undervalues.
My apologies.
So here I get it.
The real area that we're looking for which is the e-mail already exists.
So it will actually tell you that duplicate key value violates the unique constraint people email key
.
And then I'll give you a little more detail saying.
Email ECOs Joe.
Joe that already exists.
And that's really the basics of using the unique constraint.
We've already seen it use quite a bit.
Well hopefully this lecture just showed you a little more clearly and specifically how you can use the
unique constraint on a column.
OK.
That's it for this lecture.
Thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next one