Hello everyone and welcome to your second assessment test.
So for this second assessment tests we're going to be doing is working in a new database and schema
for this assessment test.
So you're probably a little tired now of using that DVD rental schema so often.
So in order to freshen things up we're going to use a different database schema.
So go ahead and download the exercise file from the resource section of this lecture and the next we're
going to do in this lectures go through a quick walk through on how to restore that database from the
exercises file.
Now remember this should be a review we should have already gone over how to create a database and restore
a database based off a backup file.
But just in case you need a walkthrough for the assessment test this is what this lecture's for.
OK with that being said the next lectures actually have the list of questions for the assessment test
and the lecture.
After that one will have the solutions.
Let's go ahead and go to PG admen.
Set up the exercise file and set up the database so you can go ahead and get started on the second assessment
test.
I'm going to go ahead and get started with P.G. admin now.
All right so here I am at PG admin we're still going to do is go ahead and connect to your post-career
server.
Just go ahead and double click on it and then you should see the list of databases you probably don't
have.
All of my databases here but you should have at least a DVD rental database.
Well we're going to go ahead and do is right click on that databases and go ahead and create a new database
and call it exercises then click OK.
That should have created a new database for you.
See a little X on it.
Go ahead and click on it in order to connect to that database.
So then we're going to do is restore the data to this database.
So good and right click on that and click restore.
That should open up this restore window.
And what you're going to do is then input the file name here or the path to the file name for the exercise
file that you downloaded should just be exercises.
So again make sure you have customer Taar you can click on these three dots and go ahead and search
for wherever you save that file from the resource section of this lecture.
Remember when you are looking for the file to specify that you're not just looking for backup files
but you're looking for all files in order to find it there.
OK.
If you need any more reference on how to do this go ahead and go back to the restored database lecturers
or the installation lectures where we go through this whole process in much more detail.
But for now all you need to do is set up this in path and then just click restore.
It should give you a bunch of code saying what it's been doing and then a return an exit code of 0 say
done and then with exercise selected go ahead and click the refresh the selected object and expand that
database.
Check out the schemas.
No you'll have a CD schema and a public schema.
We're actually going to look at the CD schema for this and then make sure you have three tables here
.
OK.
Now I wanted to to show you how to actually do a query against this particular database.
So if exercise is selected go ahead and click and execute an arbitrary sequel query and what you're
going to do here is just make sure everything's working by saying selects Asterix from.
And we have three tables in this database for the assessment test you have bookings facilities and members
.
So let's make sure we all work.
If you just do the table name itself you will get an error.
So if you just try to say select Asterix from bookings you'll get an error because it says relation
bookings does not exist.
And the reason for that is because it's not in the public schema.
It was in that CD schema.
So you have to specify schema dot the table name.
So now if I say select asterisks from CD that bookings you should get all the data output.
So let's go ahead and make sure that works for everything.
COSC the bookings.
You also have facilities.
So here are the facilities.
And then you also have
members.
OK.
So let me go ahead and walk through very quickly what each of these tables has inside of it.
So here in the Members table we have a surname for the member and then a first name for the member as
well as a member ID number.
Then you have an address and know it can be guessed as a value.
So just keep that in mind and then you have some other possible information such as a zip code a telephone
recommended by now that's an integer and then a join date as a time stamp.
So that's the Members table.
And we also have the facilities table and and the facilities are the facility ID number the name of
that facility.
The member cost.
The cost for a guest column known as initial outlay and then a monthly maintenance column.
Okay.
And these columns will be more clearly described when you actually get to the assessment test when it's
asking you for what you actually are trying to get.
And then the last one we have is the bookings table.
So the bookings table just has an ID for that particular booking facility ID integer a member ID and
a start time and then something known as slots column.
All right.
So what these tables are basically representing is some sort of club or fitness facility where you have
a bunch of facilities and members or guests or booking time at those facilities and paying for it.
OK.
With that being said Make sure you have everything ready to go as far as able to write these statements
and select from the database and those tables.
Remember you had a say CD because this in particular is not a public schema.
Its under the CD schema.
All right.
With that being said feel free to post any discussion questions if you're having trouble with this.
But coming up next is an article type lecture where you going to get a list of questions to answer along
the way.
OK.
Thanks everyone.
And best of luck on your second assessment test.