Hello everyone and welcome to the AS statement lecture.
So gonna be a really short lecture just introducing how to use as which is going to be really useful
when we learn about Joines.
So again let's just quickly learn about as that's a guess and how do you use it so that as a statement
allows us to rename columns or table selections with an alias name.
So it's really easy to show this.
If we just go straight to admin and just go through some quick examples again going to be a really short
lecture because it's a pretty simple tool to use but it'll be really useful when you go ahead and jump
straight to Peachi admin now.
OK so here I am at PGE admin and for instance I have selected everything.
So Asterix from payment means all calls from payment returning all those rows.
So let's go to show you how to use as.
So one the simplest way to do it is just by saying something like this select payment's ID.
So you have some column as and then you go ahead and type whatever name or alias you want for that actual
selection.
So in this case I could say slick pavement.
The as my payments column is go out and put from on a new line there.
And then if you run this you'll notice it basically returns that payment ID column but it returns it
as this alias name.
So my payments my underscore payment underscore column and that's really all there is to as it just
go ahead.
It just goes ahead in the an alias name to whatever your selection was.
And we'll see this use not only on columns but also on like aggregate functions grouped by statements
table selection that cetera.
But it's actually just a pretty simple concept so let me go to show you one more example that might
make a little more sense than just renaming a car.
Again I'm just going to go ahead and say select all from payment's run that in five to run that let's
go to do a group by statement because this might be a better example of how to use it.
Let's say I want to say Customer ID sum the amounts from payments and then let's go ahead and group
by customer right.
So we've seen this probably a few times now.
Certainly during the group by lectures.
But basically this just tells me how much each customer spends.
Right.
So if you notice here and you've noticed earlier throughout all or aggregate functions we just get the
aggregate function itself as the name of the column.
So it would be really nice if I were able to rename it and I can using the as statements I'll say some
of the amounts as and here I'll say total underscore Spens and notice you're basically just typing it
out there's no strings or quotes or anything you're typing it out as if it was a column name that already
existed there.
And now if I go ahead and execute this query here my column has been renamed to total underscore spent
.
OK.
So that's all there is really to as we'll see it later on we're doing joins and other group by statements
.
Truly useful just to keep track of what you've requested and what you've selected and you can go ahead
and name stuff that is useful to you.
That way you can remember what you were actually doing when you see the results in the data output.
Okay.
Thanks everyone.
I hope that all made sense to you.
Go ahead and review and try out your own statements in case you're still a little fuzzy on it.
But coming up next we'll learn about joints.
All right.
Thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next lecture