Hello everyone and welcome to your first lecture on Joines.
So we're going to learn about joints and a quick note Joines can be a bit tricky at first especially
for beginners.
So after seeing this lecture if you're still fuzzy on some stuff check out the additional resources
section of this lecture.
So just click that resource link for more links to different explanations of joints.
OK.
We will try to take it slow and straightforward though so hopefully you don't need those extra resources
but they're there just in case you need them.
So so far you've learned how to select data from a table choosing which columns and rows you want maybe
grouping stuff or sorting stuff so your resulting set gets in a particular order and you get exactly
what you want.
Now it's time to move on to one of the most important concepts in the database called jointing and that
allows you to relate data in one table to the data in other tables.
So you may have noticed that in one table we have customer IDs and then customer names and then in another
table we have customer IDs and then some other information but we don't actually have the customer names
in that table.
But joining is going to allow us to do is join data from other tables so we can match up something like
first name and last name based off the customer ID to the payments that the customer made based off
the customer ID and the payment table.
Now we're going to see examples of that later on.
Let's go ahead and first discuss just the basic syntax of a joint statement how it works and then we're
going to see a lot of examples so you can really flesh out this idea in practice.
OK.
So there's several kinds of joints including inner join outer join and self-join.
This lecture is going to first focus on the most basic join which is INNER JOIN.
All right.
So let's get some context here.
Suppose you want to get data from 2 tables names A and B the beat table has this FKK a field and we'll
have that stand for some foreign key feel that relates to the primary key of the table.
So an example of this is let's say A is the customer table and the primary key is going to be the customer
ID number.
So it's an integer and then see one character that other column.
Let's say it's going to be their full name.
And then in column B let's say that's our payments so that key is going to be something like the actual
payments ID character let's say the store they went to and then a foreign key is going to be the customer
ID.
So we have some different information here.
But we have two corresponding columns or keys so I'm going to refer to them as keys and we'll see later
on why.
But you can just think of them right now as just columns and basically the main point I'm trying to
make here is that you have two columns that are the same and a and b.
So they may have other columns that are different but you have two corresponding columns so a has some
custom write the column and B has some custom write the column and this case will say a day's column
that matches up is PKP that primary key and B's column that table that matches up is FKK that foreign
key.
So that's just some terminology but you can really just think of it as having two columns that match
up and you want to join these two tables based off the fact that those columns match up.
All right so the syntax for getting data from both tables you're going to use the inner join clause
and select statement as follows.
You're going to say this you'll say selects and the table names so a dot member or table names are a
and b dot the column you want.
So here's basically the list of columns we want.
So P.K. C-One PKB C-2.
So if we go back real quick just go ahead and show this.
Here are the column names.
PKK C-1 PKB C to F K.
And what you do is just like any other select statements.
You say select the columns you want separated by a comma except in this case the additional information
is what table the column is from.
That way sequel knows what column you're actually referring to.
So you're going to say the table name in this case or table names are a and b.
So in this case a dot and then the column name in the table.
So you have the columns you wants and you also specify what table you're actually referencing.
So you say Select the table name dot the column name and then you list all the columns you want in this
case we just want that Piquet column that primary key column C-1 column primary key column and then
C-2.
Then you say from a.
So you specify what table you want so the initial table you want to join on and he'll say inner join
.
Be on to a doc.
PKK equals b f k and so what that does is it basically corresponds to the two columns you want to match
up together.
So let's go ahead and break this down a little further.
So first you specify the column in both tables from which you want to select the data in the select
clause.
So that's just our first line here.
And notice we have here at the bottom the entire sequel's statement.
So you can reference it.
But first what we're doing is we're specifying the column in both tables from which we want to select
that data in a select clause.
Second you specify the main table.
In this case a in the FROM clause.
So the main table you're looking at is a third you specify the table that the main table joins to.
So be in the inner join clause.
And in addition you put a join condition after the on keyword.
And in this case your condition is going to be a.
PKK equals be that FKK.
So you want these two columns to be the joining on.
So again the syntax is selects table that columns you want that list from the main table you wants and
then in this case since we're doing inner join and we'll discuss what an inner join is specifically
in a little bit you'll say that whatever joint's me want inner join the second table be on and then
the actual statements you want to join on.
OK.
So for each row on the table what post-career sequel's doing is it scans the B table to check if there's
any row that matches a condition where these two columns are the same.
So we can imagine if we have the customer ID in the table in the customer ID in the table it goes down
those tables and checks Oh the customer the column value here in table A match the customer the value
in table B and then it's going to go ahead and match them.
So if it finds a match it combines the columns of both throws into one row and then adds the combined
wrote the return resultset.
All right.
Quick couple of notes here.
Sometimes a and b tables have the same column name.
So we have to refer to the column as table underscore name column underscore names so some yet to specifically
say table name column name to avoid ambiguity.
And in case the name of the tables is long you can use a table alias and in this case I just corrected
the spacing issue.
But in this case I'm going to say and sort of table underscore name.
I'm just going to say CBL and refer to the column is TBO column or square name.
And you can use that alias using the as statement that we just learned in the previous lecture.
But don't worry we'll see plenty of examples in just a second.
So let's discuss what an inner join.
Specifically is the inner join clause.
Returns rows in the table the have corresponding rows in the B table.
So wherever there's a match it's going to return those results so the stark and spot of the Venn diagram
here.
So table a table B where they have corresponding matches in both tables.
So let's go ahead and go to PG admen and then work through some examples.
OK.
Go ahead and jump the PGA admin now.
OK so here I am at PGE admin.
I went ahead and opened up the sequel editor.
And what we're going to do is go ahead in practice some inner join statements and if what we just previously
discussed isn't too clear yet that's OK.
These examples should make it much clearer.
All right so let's do some hands on examples so we can better explain what's going on here.
We will look at the customer and the payment tables in the sample database.
First off let's go ahead and look at these tables.
I have a customer id column a story the first name last name email etc. and then some time stamp information
and some address information.
But what I really want to know is this customer id column.
So I have this custom write these columns and that defiance basically what customer id let's say this
person Jared Ali has now go ahead and take a look at everything from the payment table.
Go ahead and run that.
So here I have my payment I.D. and now I also my custom right.
All right.
So I have my customer I.D..
But in this particular payment table I don't have any other information about the customer but I do
know I have that customer I.D. information in the customer table.
So we're going to try to do is join these twos to establish some sort of link between the two tables
and the link is going to be that customer id field or column.
So each customer may have zero or many payments and each payment belongs to one and only one customer
.
So for example this payment I.D. seventeen thousand five hundred three belongs solely to customer 3
for one.
So let's go ahead and use an inner join clause to join the customer table to the payment table.
So let's go in and review this sort of syntax and had actually do it.
So I'm going to say select in the first part of this joining and select statement is going to be the
actual columns I want.
So I want the customer ID column but I'm going to have to specify which table it's from or specify that
it's from the customer table because I going to join the payment table to the customer table so customer
table is going to act as my a table from the example previously shown in the payment tables going to
act as my b table.
So I say select customer that customer and the comma and then I'm going to say first name now you might
be wondering oh do I have to also specify customer first name.
Well you could and you won't receive any heirs but you actually don't have to.
And the reason for that being is because the first name column only exists in that customer table.
So if we look down at the payment table here there is no first name column so sequels going to know
to look for the first name column in the customer table.
So it's optional to specify customer that first name.
Hello.
Go ahead and not do it because as you become a more advanced sequel user you tend to not actually specify
the table if the column name is only in one table.
Customer ID column however is in both tables so I specifying that I want the customer the customer ID
column here so we'll say customer that customer or the column comma the first name column.
And let's go ahead and start putting these on a new line so we go in just make this kind of a list here
.
So I want customer that customer the first name comma go ahead and grab the last name comma will grab
the email amounts and payments underscore dates.
All right.
So I know earlier I kind of made a big fuss about specifying the table not the column name but again
as you become more of an SQL user you'll realize that all the columns I just listed here are unique
to whatever table they're from.
So first name last name and email.
Those are all unique to the customer table.
And they don't show up in the payment tables so I don't actually need to specify that they're from the
customer table.
And then likewise the amount column and the payment date column are unique to the payment table.
So I don't actually have to specify what table those are coming from either.
The only one that I had to actually specify was the customer ID column.
So I said customer which is the table name that customer ID.
OK.
Again you can always ask discussion questions in the forum in case anything is unclear here.
Let's go ahead and say from remember the syntax is from that a table.
So in this case from customer table and then here comes the new part that we haven't actually really
done yet.
It's going to be that inner joint statement going to say inner join and we say the table in this case
payments on and then we say what column and B we want to join to column an A.
So I want to join the payments.
Thoughts.
Customer ID column and B to the customer customer id column in a so I'm saying inner join the payments
table.
So from customer inner join with the payment table.
So from a table enter join unbe table or inner join.
The payment table on.
And then the on statement is what actual columns or fields you want to match up.
This case I want to make sure that the customer ID columns from each table lineup.
So how to execute this and see what we get.
OK.
So here we have the columns who requested.
So we have the customer IDs.
Notice there are several instances of those.
And that's because they made multiple payments and I went ahead.
If we scroll to the right here now we can see the various payments they made.
So the actual amounts they made and the payment dates they made those payments on.
And we also have their first name last name and e-mail information along with that.
So we successfully joined those two tables getting the information from both tables.
OK.
In the next lecture we're going to do is cover some more joint examples specifically inner join examples
.
So you really make sure you have a good understanding of what's going on.
But what I want to do now before we code totally finish off this lecture is just show you how to use
like where clause or order by clauses.
With this sort of join this query here.
So we just join these two.
We got everything we wanted.
Let's say we wanted to actually order by the customer ID number.
So in this case the customer ID number looks like it's out of order.
What I can do is go ahead and add an ORDER BY statements and roomer we use that order by the column
.
So in this case I'm going to say order by the customer the customer ID column.
So the only difference here is I have to specify what table to take the column name from.
If I wanted to sort order by first name we can go ahead and try that.
So for instance here if I run this I went ahead and ordered by the customer right.
So Mary Smith's first if I wanted to order by the first name
and I ran that notice I don't get any sort of error or anything and that's because that first name The
reason I didn't have to specify the table it came from.
So the reason I have to say something like customer the first name is because that first name column
only exists in the Customer table.
OK.
So that's how you would do something like an order by after joining two tables and you could also do
something like where to filter based on some sort of condition.
So for instance I could say where.
Let's just say we're looking for one particular customer.
So I'd swap for Customer ID number two or something.
I can say where customer thought customer ID is equal to two.
And if I run that I just get only the results where the customer I.D. was due to this case.
Looks like Patricia Johnson.
So you get all of Patricia Johnson's payments here which is nice.
OK that.
Remember how to specify customer that customer I.D. because a customer id column is in both tables.
If I was only doing something like let's say just want for some weird reason where the first names start
with an A.
I could say where first underscore a name like capital a per cent sign single quote semi colon and if
I run that now I get the payment information for all the first names that start off in a.
And that's how you can do that.
OK.
So no one more time.
I didn't have to specify the table for the table but first name because first name only shows up in
the Customer table.
Now if I went ahead and said that customer the first name and ran that's You'll notice I won't get any
errors or anything which is fine if you're kind of a beginner at sequel's Sometimes it's really helpful
as far as keeping track of what table this column came from to actually specify customer that first
name.
This is where you'll kind of find out your own style of school selection.
When I was first starting off with sequel I really made sure to specify what table each column came
from.
But as you go on you'll won't want to type as much so you'll end up just kind of dropping these out
if they only show up in a single table.
That's kind of your own style choice.
It's up to you if you want the most readability possible.
If you come back later then you should probably be putting in the table name.
If it's kind of obvious what table it came from.
So for instance you might think it's kind of obvious that first name and last name are coming from a
customer table based off this joint statement.
Then maybe you don't need to actually specify the table name.
All right.
So in the next lecture we'll go ahead and explore some more examples of join just to make sure that
all the students coming up to this part of the course are all on the same page.
OK thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next lecture where we're going to go through a bunch of examples
of join.
Thanks and I'll see you there