Hello everyone and welcome to this lecture we're going to show you just a few more examples of inner
joins just to make sure everyone's on the same page.
You can remember back in the very early lectures we're showing you the database in general.
We gave you this diagram here that showed all the tables in the different relationships they had of
each other and we were going to do now is U-joints to take advantage of those relationships.
So just to walk you through a couple of examples here we can see for example the language table and
the film table are related to each other because we can see here that the language ID column is also
present in the film table under language ID and this little key sign basically means the primary key
of this table is language ID.
OK.
So there's some other couple of connections here that we'll continue to explore.
Things such as staff Id also being present in the payment table and your staff ID.
And let's go ahead and just jump straight to P.G. adamant and show you a couple of more examples of
how to use inner joins and then later on we'll learn about different join types.
What's different about them and why inner join will always be the best joint to work with.
Even though it will be probably the most common join you use.
Let's go out and jump straight to P.G. outman now.
OK so here I am at PG admin.
I went ahead and just select the first five rows from the payment table.
And so here we see we have a payment ID column A customer id column staff ID rental ID amount and a
payment date.
Let's go ahead and explore joining the payment table with the staff table.
So if we go ahead and take a look at the staff table notice we have a staff ID from the payment table
.
But if I go ahead and run the staff table I can actually get their first name and the last name of those
two staff ID members.
So that's Mike and John let's go ahead and combine the two tables so I can see Mike and John's name
along with the payments they processed.
So I'm going to go ahead and say select the payments ID the amounts and then first name and last name
.
Now again I could specify the tables that I want this from.
So I could do something like this.
STAFF The last name.
But in this case again I don't have to because last name is only present in the staff table so sequels
not going to get confused on what table or what column you're talking about from which table.
Now if the ID or that column is present in both tables then you do need to specify what table you're
talking about.
So I'm going to select this from my table in this case that's the payment table and I'm going to go
ahead and do an inner join with staff on payments dot staff underscore ID is equal to whip's staff staff
Id call them.
So Michael is going to run that.
And so now I get to see the payments ID column the amount column and I get to see the first and last
name instead of just the staff ID so I could see John in Mike's name throughout my output data.
Couple of things I want to note here.
In most pretty much all sequel engines you can go ahead and not have to specify inner join just writing
join.
By default it will go to an inner join.
Now I know we haven't specifically discussed yet the differences between various joints but just keep
that in mind for inner joins.
You can just go ahead and write join usually throughout the course just to be really explicit.
All say inner join but probably in the real world.
If someone's doing an inner join let's say you're at work and someone else is writing sequel you are
reading their sequel queries.
More likely than not if you're doing an inner join they'll probably just write join.
OK so let's go ahead and do another example.
Let's go ahead and show the inventory table so selects everything Asterix from inventory it's going
to limit that to just five rows.
So here you have an inventory ID column a film Id column a store Id column and a last updates.
And let's go out and see what we have in the film table.
So I notice that a film ID in the inventory table and I also have a film ID in the film table and facts
in the film table.
That's its key its primary key is the film Id.
Let's go out and join those two in a matter like this.
We're going to go ahead and say select let's say title
from inventory and we'll go ahead and say inner join member I could just write join in her drawing film
on inventory thought film ID equals film dot film ID and then I'm going to go ahead and select the story
.
The column as well.
So let's go in and say store ID columns so story the title from inventory INNER JOIN film on inventory
equals film Id.
Let's go in and run that.
OK.
So what do we have here.
I have all the instances of that particular title being at a store.
So in this case the movie Academy dinosaur there's four copies at storeyed the one.
So if we scroll down to another example I have guys Falcon title is store three times that story the
one.
So let's call it and ask ourselves let's say a typical business task.
I want to know how many copies of each movie are at store ID number one store ID number one how can
I do that.
Well first let's think what I want to do.
I want to filter by store ID one meaning I'm going to go ahead and put a where statements and they say
we're store ID is equal to one.
And now let's go ahead and see what happens if I run that.
All right.
So now I have all the instances of story the one and the various instances of the title movies there
so Academie dinosaur again is four times present.
So there's four copies of that movie as story one.
Now what else can I do here if I want to actually get the counts.
So instead of having the actual title here I want to get the count of the number of instances that title
shows up.
So that makes sense so far.
But remember if I'm doing an aggregate function I should have some sort of group by function as well
.
And in this case I just want to group by the title would it makes sense to group by the story idea because
there's only one story the story the one.
So then if I grouped by the title here I'm going to run this whoops.
Let's go ahead and fix that.
Notice here my error is that I'm still asking for story which doesn't really make sense since the story
is equal to one I'm not grouping by it.
I should be selecting the title column.
So now if I take a look at this.
These are the actual counts of each movie.
So how many copies of each movie are at store ID equals one.
So that means a movie like Frontier cabin is has two copies that story the one and again let's go ahead
and use as to clear this up.
Scientists say from inventory count title as let's say copies at store 1 and then if I run that.
So here we have two columns tidal copies at store one and it shows you the title and the number of copies
are at store 1 and then we can continue working on this let's say let's go in and order this order by
title.
So now I have this in alphabetical order.
And now we're seeing what a real kind of powerful query looks like.
Now I can instantly say OK how many titles of Agent Truman do I have at store one and I can quickly
do a query here and see that I have three copies that store one.
And these are the real kind of queries you'll be looking at in a business setting.
Probably not for a rental movie database but whatever database you're using at your place of work.
OK let's go ahead and build off of one more example.
So I'm gonna go in and clear all this Ale's go it and use the film table cells because you get a reminder
of what's in the film table we're going to say select Asterix from film we'll say limit to just two
rows and I have a film Id title description.
Really Sidey.
And what's interesting here to me is I have a language ID so I have a language ID but it's just a number
it actually be really nice if I could translate that number into an actual word.
So for instance language anyone would be English etc..
So now take a look at the actual language table.
So if we look at the language table language in run that I have the language ID column and the actual
name that each of these language ID numbers corresponds to.
So for example language ID number one corresponds to the English language language ID two two Italian
etcetera.
All right so now what I want would be really nice to see the title of the movie and then the language
that it's in.
So let's go ahead and do that.
That means I'll need to join the film table with the language table.
So I wanted to say something like this selects title and let's go ahead and make this really explicit
.
Granted I don't have to do this because title isn't in the language table but it's still might be nice
for reference later on.
And then we'll say the
language that name so select film title language that name from film and we're going to inner join on
language inner join language on language start language ID is equal to film
language ID.
OK so let's take a look at this again.
I was going to run it.
Make sure it works.
OK so we have the title of the movie and the name of the actual language it's in.
So let's go ahead and say call this
movie language.
Whoops.
So it's a little more readable.
Right so let's take a look at what it did here.
I said select the title Colum from the film table and the name column from the language table as movie
language from the film table inner join language on so inner join the A with the beat table on the column
where they match up and in this case it's the language ID column.
OK.
So again I didn't actually have to specify these tables because these column names are unique.
Are these field names are unique to the actual tables they're from.
So if I go ahead and run this I'll get the same results.
Again the reason I didn't have to do that was because title only shows up in the film table and name
column only shows up in the language table.
OK.
So continuing on with this let's go ahead and keep working with this and showing you basically what
this would look like if you were getting closer to just typical workplace sequel.
So if in a typical workplace you probably wouldn't see the interstates and you would just see join.
So if we go ahead and do join here run this again you'll know you get the same results.
And also what people tend to do if the table name is really long.
So for instance language is kind of long here.
What they will do is they will shorten it using an AS statement.
So they'll just say from film join language and then they'll say as something like Eliane which is a
lot shorter.
And then they can call that table Eliane here.
So they use that alias name here.
Then if I run that notice I get the same results.
So I say select title name as movie language from film join language as alien on alien language ID equals
film that language ID.
OK.
And we can actually take this even further through reduction and a lot of times in a real work environment
.
People don't use the as statement and this kind of one of those quirks of sequel.
So which can actually do is just have a space instead of an as statements and it will still work.
So if I go ahead and just have a space select title comma name movie language from film join language
.
Eliane.
So I remove the as statements go hand and run this.
And you'll notice it still works.
So you don't actually need to explicitly put the AS statement there you just need to put a space.
Now it's really up to your own personal style whether you like putting an ADD statement there or not
.
I personally always put in as statement just because to me it's a lot more readable.
Now if you for some reason think it's more readable to not have the statement there or you just like
the shorthand form better.
Feel free to not put as statements but throughout the course more likely than not we will be using as
to explicitly rename either tables or column selections.
Now again you don't have to use it and if you look at someone else's sequel queries they may not use
it.
It's not soup.
It's not super typical to use it depending on what kind of work environment you are in.
But personally I would always recommend that you use it just for readability sake.
Ok so I hope that those couple of examples of using inner join.
And remember that can be shortened to just join are useful to you.
Coming up next we're going to learn about different join cases and we're going to learn about outer
join right join.
And why would we use those and what actually is the difference between the various joints because you
might be thinking what happens if certain rows or certain columns don't exist in table B.
Had the sequel actually rectify any missing values there and that's really where the different joints
come into play.
OK with that being said I hope those inner joins were useful to you in discussion.
What I would recommend doing if you still feel a little uncomfortable of the inner joins is to hop back
to this table hear me go in and do that.
So again hopping back to this table go ahead and see if you can do your own inner joins based off the
connections from the tables themselves so see if he can do some inner joins between like address and
staff or city and country here.
So for example or be a couple of good exercises would be to join the columns from the city table with
the country table based off the country Id column or that country Id field and again might be fun to
do that with store and staff payments and customer etcetera.
So practice your inner joins.
Basically you just set the follow these lines.
And again if you ever need to reference this diagram you can either download it from the resource section
here or you can just google search Keela database in Google Images.
So this diagram is available for you as a resource.
It's just the PMG while free to take a look at.
Again I would really recommend that you check out your own joints based off this diagram here.
OK.
With that being said let's go ahead to learn about some more joints in the next lecture.
Thanks everyone and I'll see you there.