Hello everyone and welcome to the overview of join types.
Lecture this lecture is going to begin to help build our understanding of the various different types
of JOINs of vailable to us in sequel and just a quick note.
This presentation is a resource for you in this lecture.
So if you go ahead and click that button that says extra resources or check resources for this lecture
this PowerPoint is available to you.
So as we learn more about the different types of joints it's going to become really useful to reference
Joines as a Venn diagram figure.
So these are actually really easy to find via a Google image search.
So if you just go to Google and then click on images and search for sequela joints that's Eskew L-Space
joins you should be able to find a diagram that looks really similar to this one.
In fact most of the results will actually be the specific diagram.
What's really nice about this diagram is it shows the sequel joints as Venn diagrams and this really
helps your understanding of what you're going to receive back when you do specific joins.
Now this one here in the middle this inner join is the one we just learned about and it's the most common
join but one hour we're going to do is expand our understanding to the rest of these joint types and
below each of these Venn diagram figures you're dealing with two tables and B and then you have the
actual sequence period.
And what it would return based on the Venn diagram.
OK.
So in order to discuss the various types of joints that are available to us what we're going to do is
use some example tables.
So in this case we have two example tables table A and table.
So table is on the left Table B is on the right.
And when you're using sequel and joins left and right are going to signify what you use select from
first versus what you're joining on them.
So the left in this case table A is going to be used as select columns from a.
And that's going to be the left table and then you're going to say joint on the right table which will
be Table B.
So if we look at right now what table in Table B have they both have two fields to them ID and name
.
So if we look at these two tables in combination we actually have essentially four unique columns a
id a name b ID and B that name.
So keep that in mind as we look through the various examples of Joines.
So something else to note here is that and these two original tables we have some items that are present
in both tables.
So throughout the various joint examples we're going to be joining based off the name column.
So if we take a look at table.
We have four rows with four names.
Pirate monkey ninja and spaghetti and if we look at Table B The name's pirate and ninja are in both
tables so those are marked read in Table B the names Rootabaga And later are only in table B.
So that's important to keep in mind and we'll have an image of these original tables throughout the
examples of the various joint types.
So let's go ahead and review the inner join the join that we just learn about.
So to put it a little more formally inner join produces only the set of records that match in both Table
A and Table B.
So if we look at our original tables left as on table a right is Table B.
We're going to say select all columns from table a inner join with two table B on the table a thought
Name column equal to Table B that name column.
And what that is going to return is the a id a name and the B ID and the B name.
And you'll notice here the only things that are returned is where there was a match for that column
in both A and B.
So in this case there's only two rows in the tables that match all the Name column that's going to be
pirates and Ninja.
So we have a thought Id say that name and B that ID and B that name as returns only where there was
a match in both tables so pirate and Inja and we could see that here from the Venn diagram.
So here the Venn diagram is going to fill in or highlight what's actually return.
And in this case if an inner join and a quick reminder You can also just type in join and it will automatically
do an inner join.
So an inner join again produces only the set a record that match in both Table A and Table B.
OK so let's go ahead and explore a different type of join a fool outer join with a full outer join does
.
It's going to produce the set of all records in table A and Table B with matching records from both
sides where available.
If there is no match the missing side will contain a null.
So again this is important to know that the full outer join produces the set of all records and table
and table B with matching records from both sides where they're available.
And if there is no match where the missing sides are going to contain a null So basically you're going
to try to return everything from both tables and if there wasn't a match you're just going to put in
a null meaning empty.
So again let's go ahead and look at our A and B tables.
So the only places where we have a match on pirate and Ninja.
So if we go ahead and look at the result.
So we're saying select all columns from table a with a full outer join on Table B meaning that's going
to be returned the 8th that ID column A Name column B that ID column B the name column we're going to
get back the rows where there was a match.
So a pirate pirate ninja ninja and then for the rows where there is no match the side that was missing
is going to contain a null.
So here we have two Monkey No for spaghetti nil nil.
And then and this is what makes a full outer join unique.
It goes ahead and takes it from the right table and puts in left table as nails as well.
So you have known all one Rootabaga normal three there later.
So again the full outer join produces the set of all records in table a table be with matching records
from both sides where they were available.
And if there was no match the missing side is going to contain the null.
So we can show this through event diagram as basically returning absolutely everything and will have
nulls where we weren't able to find a match.
And that's known as a full outer join.
And again the syntax for that is just full outer join.
OK let's go ahead and move on to another joining syntax example.
And that's going to be the left outer join with the left outer join does is it produces a complete set
of records from table a with the matching records where they are available in Table B if there is no
match.
The right side will contain a null so we can basically think of this as a full outer join but we're
only confined to the left table.
In this case table a.
That first table that you're actually saying from 2.
So we're saying select all columns from table a left outer join table B on the name columns.
So that's going to guarantee that you get all the rows from table a for the column you're specifying
the match on.
And if there was a match with table B we go ahead and fill it in and if there wasn't we fill it in with
null.
The difference here between a left outer join and a full outer join is that we don't return results
where there was there would be a null value in table.
So notice here.
Table B then is empty in this Venn diagram.
So if we go in and go back the difference here in the full outer join would have been these last two
rows where we go ahead and return the full records from both Table A and Table B in the case of a left
outer join.
We're only producing the complete set of records from table a where there was a match and then we check
there was a match available in table B.
And if there was the match we went to clonal.
OK.
So again go ahead it's possible you maybe rewind or check the sequel Venn diagram charts and really
make sure you understand the difference between a full outer join and that left outer join and the critical
part is really these two bottom rows of the full outer join and make sure you understand the reasoning
of why these are present on the full outer join but that they're not present on the left outer join
.
OK.
Now something I want to discuss is there's also a right outer joins.
And that's basically going to be the exact same thing except in this case instead of highlighting here
table a will highlight table B where they match and we'll see some examples of that later on.
But let's go in and go with left outer join with a where statements and you might see this commonly
used.
But this allows you to produce the set of records only in table A but not in table B.
You're going to perform that same left outer join then exclude the records.
We don't want.
From the right side via a where clause.
So I'm going to show you how this is working.
So if we look at this table a here imagine that we only wanted to get in return the rows monkey and
spaghetti meaning we only want to produce a set of records that are in table A.
But not present in table B.
In that case you can use a left outer join with a where statement to check if records are null.
So you will go ahead and exclude the wrecker's you don't want from the right side via a where statements
or where clause.
So the syntax is this.
I'm going to say select all the columns from table a buffet left outer join on Table B.
Where we going on table a thought name equal to table B that name.
And then here's the specific part where we say where table be the ID is null meaning where the idea
was no.
So there was no match on the names there.
And that basically returns the set of records only in table A but not in table B.
And this is what this Venn diagram is trying to show here.
So the records that are only in table A but not in table B.
So in this case it's going to be munky and spaghetti.
And again if you wanted to do this the other way around meaning only records in table B but not in table
A.
You could have said right outer join again with the WHERE clause there and that would have been only
on Table B if you said on the right.
So go ahead and reference that original sequel joint diagram because you can basically think of left
and right statements as just symmetrical to each other basting one table off the other.
And the reason they're symmetrical is because you could also just change the order and instead of saying
Right you could just change this wherever you see table a change table B.
So that's really a matter of preference there whether you like to use both left outer joins and right
outer joins or you just like to only use left outer joints and specify table orders yourselves.
OK let's go in and move on to a full outer join with a where clause.
So imagine you wanted to produce a set of records unique to table A and Table B you can perform the
same flawed or join and then exclude the records we don't want.
From both sides via a WHERE clause.
So with this specific query which you're going to return is only the wrecker's unique to table a table
B.
So basically are the records where they don't match up.
So in this case we don't want pirate or a ninja.
And the way you do that is with water Joyal whole where clause.
So we're going to say select all columns from table a full outer join table be on table a that name
column equal the table be that name column where Table 8 that ID is NULL for a table B that ID is null
.
And what we're going to see back here is monkey spaghetti.
Those are unique to table a.
And then Rootabaga in there later and those are unique to table B.
And then the other columns are fields for that specific row are filled in all final statements.
OK.
So just a quick review we've learned about the various join types in the next couple of lectures we're
going to focus on showing you examples of these various joint types.
So we already walk through a bunch of examples of inner join the next couple extra we're going to do
is to show you some basic examples of the left outer join our full outer join just to build our understanding
of the various join types and see them in action.
Again I highly recommend that you check out a sequel join the Venn diagram Azure watching these lectures
to help build your understanding of how that Joines work.
OK thanks everyone and I will see you at the next lecture