Hello everyone and welcome to this lecture on outer join.
So we're going to do here is take a quick look at a specific example of an outer joint statements.
So we've actually already seen examples of an inner joint statement and then after that in the previous
lecture we saw a bunch of syntax and Venn diagrams describing the various types of joint statements
so the inner joins the outer join it's full of drawings etc..
And so we're going to do this lecture is take a more specific look at outer join.
And to be even more specific than that we're going to take a look at the LEFT OUTER JOIN.
So remember for a left outer join it's going to return all the rows in the left table.
So we can say if we remember that Venn diagram that would be Table A.
So return all the rows in the left table a that are combined of rows in the right table B even though
there's no corresponding rows in the right table B.
So that's sometimes also known as just the left join and we'll discuss that in a little bit.
But each row in the film table to be specific to our rental DVD database may have zero or many rows
in the inventory table and each row in the inventory table has all has one and only one row in the film
table.
So again just to rephrase that.
We know that each row in this film table may have either zero or many rows in the inventory table because
you have only one title of a film.
Right.
But you can have multiple copies of inventory in each row in the inventory table has one and only one
role in the film table.
So in the film table is that kind of list that unique titles of the films and the inventory table is
how many copies of those films you have in a specific store.
All right.
So let's go ahead and see a use case for an outer join.
Then again in this case we'll do a left outer join in a quick note in sequel's syntax.
Remember we were doing the inner join.
We could have also just write written join in for left outer joints and outer joins in general.
You can also just write left join or right join siecle automatically know if it refers to an outer join
because the left is specified and will go ahead and touch back on this when we see the examples in Peachi
admin.
With that being said lets go ahead and jump to PGE admin and check out our DVD rental database.
Then go ahead and go there now.
OK everybody so here we are at the sequel editor.
I already open the PGA outman and execute an art literary sequel query.
Now we're going to do just explore the tables we're going to be working with.
So let's go ahead and select all columns from the film table and let's go ahead and limit this to five
.
And you notice actually already ran this previously so my data output is the same.
But the important columns to look at here we have a film ID and a title of the film.
So those are the ones we're going to be most focus on as far as the film tables concerned.
And if we take a look at inventory
and limit that to five we have a Inventory ID and a film Id And so we know that we have this film ID
in both tables and we also have a store ID and a last update.
So the most important ones here in inventory are going to be Inventory ID and film ID.
OK.
So let's go ahead and use a left outer join clause to join the film table to the inventory table and
that's going to work as follows.
I'm going to say this I'm gonna I say select
and I will say the table name table name dots the columns that I want back.
So I want fill ID back.
And the reason I have to specify again the table here so film that film ID is because film ID is present
in both tables and then I'm going also say film dot title column and again since title isn't actually
present in both tables.
So it's kind of up to you whether you want to specify film not title but I like to specify the actual
table name.
And then let's go ahead and say Inventory ID sell say inventory underscore ID and Ira I won't write
inventory that Inventory ID just because it's a little long and I want to save screen space here since
I'm showing you this.
So then we'll say from our table in this case going to be film.
So that's the left table here and they're going to say LEFT OUTER JOIN inventory on inventory and remember
the film ID column is where we're going to join the months on an essay film underscore ID equal to film
film underscore ID semi colon and let's go ahead and run that and see what we get.
Okay great.
So we have our results now.
And let's go in and take a further look at them.
So right now we can see we have multiple outputs of the same title which makes sense because you can
have multiple copies of that film in inventory.
But we want to know now is what do we have a film in our film database that no stores have in inventory
that would mean we would have a null for the Inventory ID.
So if we look at this data input and slowly scroll down if you go all the way to the bottom you'll notice
you have blanks here for the Inventory ID integer.
That means you have a null value there which makes sense because some rows in the film table do not
have corresponding rows in the inventory table.
And then that means the value of the Inventory ID is going to be null.
So in this case we kind of display it as a blank depending on what your operating system is and what
your settings are.
You may not get a blank here you may actually show in parentheses null in usually a lighter great text
so just keep that in mind.
So you have a blank or an else statement there that's fine.
OK.
So let's say we have this business case and we want to order films that we don't have in any inventory
.
So a customer is going to request a film and we want to know that we have every single copy of films
So that means we need to specifically ask well where is that inventory I.D. going to be null and we
can do this by adding a WHERE clause to select only films that are not in the inventory.
And there's a couple of ways to do this but here's a kind of an easy way to think about it.
So we're just going to go and add a where statement to this.
So I'm going to say where
inventory the film underscore.
ID
is null and if you go back to the previous you show that syntax examples there's a couple of examples
of Joines that use this sort of where is null statement to filter things out.
So if we go out and run this now we have a copy of all the movies that are not in inventory.
So notice here we're asking where the inventory fill my column is null off of this left outer join in
another no.
Again we can further refine this query if we want to order by a different column.
So here we're ordering by title so we can say Order By then we can go ahead an order by the film Id
So it could say something like.
Order by film by film underscore Id run that.
And so now we've ordered it by the film ID.
And if you notice it actually is pretty much the same thing because the film ID has to do is correlated
to the title in alphabetical order so you could also set order by title or whatever you want.
So quick note if this inventory that film ID is NULL is confusing to you.
Maybe you can think about it as just selecting stuff off our original combination of these two tables
.
I'm going to go ahead and show you another way to do this exact same query that maybe makes more sense
to some users out there.
So again this is where we came up with after we joined them.
We have the film Id several instances of the title which makes sense and then their inventory ID integer
.
So here's that film Id.
There is the title of that film and then theres the inventory ID for that specific copy and we can think
of this basically as this Inventory ID the one stands for a specific copy of the Academy dinosaur movie
.
And again for inventory 82 thats another physical copy of an academy dinosaur.
And then if we scroll all the way down we notice we had some null values here that we wanted to take
care of.
So another way we could have done that instead of specifying inventory that Phil might be we could have
just said the name of this column right here which is inventory underscore ID so I could have said this
where inventory underscore ID is null and if we go ahead and check that out and run that then we get
basically the exact same output as we did when we specified inventoried that film ID is null and I can
go ahead and work that even more just to say order by in lets go I said go ahead and say order by the
title and now you notice that we'll have the exact same results if we scroll down here you can see we
have 42 rows going from walls artists back to Alice Fantasia.
So that's the exact same queery not the exact same syntax of the query but it will return the exact
same results.
And sometimes this makes a little more sense to people if you just specify the columns that you were
asking for from here.
And if case you want to come back to this you can further specify things like filmdom title.
And if we run this this will be the exact same thing.
So you know the sequel tends to be pretty flexible as far as when you specify tables dot the column
name.
Or if you don't specify a table name it really depends on what your two tables look like and if they
have repeated column names between the two.
So just keep that in mind and keep in mind what works best for you personally and what's going to work
best for you if you were to come back the same query a few weeks later.
It's always better to have something like film but title instead of just title by itself because it's
a little more readable in it.
Say a nice reminder when you come back to it later on what table you are actually requesting this column
from.
So keep that in mind.
This will eventually become your segue into your own personal style of sequel queries.
Some people really like to do it the specific way so the second way I showed you this inventory underscore
the title.
Some people really like that and some other people really liked the first way I showed it using something
like inventory that film Id is no.
So it's really up to you.
You'll discover your own style as you do more and more sequel queries so just keep that in mind that
there's definitely more than one way to get the right answer for a lot of these questions.
OK.
With that being said that's the end of this outer join lecture.
You can go ahead and play around with right outer joins if you want to go ahead and explore that a little
further.
But it's basically the exact same concept as the left outer join except you're specifying the B table
versus the table to hold all the rows.
OK.
With that being said Thanks everybody and I will see at the next lecture