Hello everyone and welcome to the union lecture.
So and this sucks we're going to learn how a union statement works how it's different than just the
typical joint statement and then we'll see a quick example of a union in some slides.
We won't actually code anything out because the concept of a union is actually very simple.
So what happens is the union operator combines result sets of two or more select statements into a single
result set and the following illustrates the syntax of what the union operator would actually look like
.
Z would have a select statements so something like select column one column to from some table in the
say union and you'll have another select statement.
Select column on column 2 from some table.
So notice you have these two select statements and you're going to perform a union between them.
So there's two major rules you have to follow here.
When you're going to use union statements the first rule is that both of these selects queries must
return the same number of columns and that makes sense Sophi jump back to the previous slide we have
column 1 and column 2 and column 1 and call them to MBO if select statements.
So we're turning the same number of columns so far that makes sense.
And the second rule is that the corresponding columns in the queries must have compatible data types
.
Meaning if we go back here if select column 1 column on your first select statement is some sort of
integer.
Then select column 1 from your second select statement from the second table must also be an integer
.
So this column data types need to match up.
So you might be wondering when am I ever going to use a union statement.
Well the union operator removes all duplicate rows unless the union all is used in an union operator
may place the rows in the first query before after or between the rows in the results.
The second query.
So because you get this mixed up order you can sort the rows and the combined result set by a specified
column just using the order by clause.
But now we understand union and union also again the union operator just removes all the duplicate rows
unless a union all is used.
Then we often use the union operator to combine data from similar tables that are not perfectly normalized
.
And what I mean with that is basically you have two tables with the exact same type of information inside
of them.
But you want to just join that information together.
So a typical joint statement doesn't really work in that sense because you basically just want to take
all the rows from one table and all the rows from another table and just almost like concatenate them
or mix them into a single table.
So those tables are often found in the reporting or a data warehouse system.
Let's go through a quick example and this will be a little more clear.
So take a look at that example now measure we have two tables.
We have sales 2007 Q1 and sales 2007 Q2.
And these are stores sales data in quarter one and quarter two of 2007.
So we're going to have the name of some sales associate in each table and then the amount that they
sold.
So you'll notice here we have Mike John and Mary and then Mike John and Mary.
That makes sense we have the same employees in quarter one quarter two of the year 2007 and we have
amounts that they sold for that particular quarter.
Some things to notice here is that the amounts for Mike and John changes from quarter one quarter to
.
But Mary sold the exact same amount in both quarters.
That's something to take note of.
So how will we actually put a union to work here.
Well the union is going to allow us to just combine this information in case we want to have a table
that said something like sales 2007 first half of the year quarter one and quarter two we just basically
want to concatenate these two tables together.
So the syntax would look something like this.
We say select everything from sales 2007 Q1 Union and then select Asterix so all columns from sales
in Q2.
So if we take a look at what happens after this we get this result.
We have John John Mary and then Mike Mike and we have their name the amounts and here Mary only shows
up once.
And that's because she had the same value for both quarters.
So as you mentioned earlier if you just use union it's going to delete duplicate rows.
And what a duplicate row means is that every single column in both of those rows is exactly the same
.
So if you want to make sure that doesn't happen you use a UNION ALL statements.
So you use a UNION ALL statement here.
Then I get both instances of Mary in this resulting table.
Now I know I've been using the term concatenate which basically means just a stick or glue these two
tables together.
But notice that they're not an order here.
So later on if you wanted to you could say order by name or order by amount if you wanted to order this
table.
So this is really useful if you want it to then do some sort of group by name and then some the amounts
.
This table that gets returned to you for calculating the total amount of sales or particular custom
or particular employees.
OK.
So that's really all there is to a union.
Again you can basically just think of it as completely combining tables together with the two rules
being that you need to have the same number of columns and those columns need to have the same data
type.
So really it's almost always used when you're combining two tables that haven't been normalized yet
.
Me you don't have all the information together in one table.
OK.
So with that being said we're coming to the end of that joint section and there's no challenges for
the join section specifically.
Instead we're going to revisit these topics for the second assessment test and this test is going to
come right after the next section which goes over just a few more advanced sequel commands that we need
to learn in order to take full advantage of everything you just learn in the joints section.
So don't worry.
Hang tight.
You will get tested on all the joints and everything we just covered here.
But I want to cover a couple of more advanced sequel commands that we we can really challenge you in
the second assessment test with some great questions.
OK.
With that being said.
Thanks everyone.
And I will see at the next lecture