Hello everyone and welcome to the min max average in some lecture and these are all what are known as
aggregate functions.
And we're going to be using every functions a lot when we learn about group by in the next lecture.
So I wanted just to introduce to you some of these aggregate functions we've actually already used one
of them called Count counters another example of an aggregate function and aggregate functions do is
they basically take a lot of information or a lot of rows of data and aggregate it or combine it into
a single value.
So you can imagine what a some aggregate function does is it adds up all that data combines to a single
value.
And in the same way minimax an average take in all these rows of data and combine it to a single value
.
A lot of these are really self-explanatory in their use.
But we're going to go ahead and show you quick simple examples of all of them.
There will be a challenge because these are all pretty easy to understand.
So let's just go ahead and dive straight into PGE admin and see examples of all these.
OK so here we are at PGE admin.
I'm going to go ahead and click on DVD rental execute arbitrary SQL query and what I'm going to do is
just show you quick examples of all those aggregate functions.
So let's go ahead and use the payment table to do this on the say select Asterix meaning all columns
from the payments table.
And it's going to limit this just to five rows so you don't get a whole bunch stuff back.
OK.
So let's look for a nice numerical column.
It looks like to me a nice to work column to play around with as far as the aggregate functions would
be the amount column.
So how much that amounts payment was actually four.
So we have a bunch of dollar figures here.
So 7 9 9 189 et cetera.
And we're going to do is go ahead and mess around with the agri functions for them.
So aggregate functions are used a lot with the group by statement.
And what we're going to do is just show you how you can use them without a group by statement.
So it is common to do this without a group by statement because I agree it functions really show their
power with GROUP BY together.
But maybe you do want to just get a general idea for the entire data base you have.
So let's say we want to know what's the average amounts paid.
I would just say the average amount from payment and let's go ahead and delete this limit line even
though we should only get basically one number back.
So if I just say five here and that's the average amount paid $4 and 20 something cents notice I get
a lot of decimal points back.
And if you want to reduce the number of decimal points which I've actually just jumped to and shown
you here but I haven't actually put that code in yet you can use the round function.
So let's go in and run this again.
So notice here and have a bunch of decimal points in a kind of jumped in the video.
This isn't editing.
But let's go ahead and reduce this so we just get it to two decimal points since this is money that's
really all we care about up to the second decimal place.
So to do that I can use round and I can say select and then I have round that I'm going to go ahead
and pass in the average amounts that number that I want around Khama.
And then the number of decimal places I want around too.
So let's say just want around to two places pass the decimal and if I go ahead and run this then I get
four dollars and 20 cents here for one more decimal points.
I can just add in a different number here.
Run it it'll give me that many decimal places past that point.
So in this case I put in five and we can use round in order to round that average or a man or Max whatever
the aggregate function is two more decimal places.
OK so we won't be using round too often just because you can call it if you need it and it's just faster
for demonstration purposes or for doing stuff just to go ahead and run it like this and then call the
average here with all the decimal places.
Usually I'm not going to need that many decimal places but throughout the course we won't be using around
too much just because it's a lot faster to type out average.
And now that we know how to use round you can do it on your own.
So again if you want to use round you just take the numerical column amount that you're trying to pass
type in around and it basically takes in essentially two arguments here.
The first is the number you actually want to round and then you say comma and put in the number of decimal
places you want around 2.
So for instance two decimal places five to run it.
And I have that round that number.
OK.
So let's go ahead to learn about couple more aggregate functions.
Another useful one is men for minimum.
And if we just say select men and let's go in and select the minimum rental or payment rates.
And that would be the amount column.
So I want to select the minimum amount anyone ever paid and or process can go ahead and say five here
.
And that's interesting the minimum amount was $0.
So that might be something we might want to check into.
So let's go ahead and check into that by saying selects amounts.
And let's go ahead and order by the amounts ordered by amounts and see if we can find out a little more
about this so if we order by amount you'll notice we have actually a lot of zeros in the beginning.
So that might be an interesting question to ask ourselves later why are there so many zeros there and
let's say we actually want to count how many there were.
We could say select counts which is another aggregate function.
So count the number of occurrences amount from payments and then we're going to say where Count is equal
to.
And let's say hosers or and notice we get an error here and that's because I wasn't paying attention
and this should not been count that should have been amounts got confused there for a second because
they rhyme.
But here we go we have 24 instances of the amount being $0.
So that's interesting.
Pay attention to this because you may asked something similar in a challenge later on.
So just a quick hint there.
Anyways let's go ahead and continue on.
So we have min and max.
So if we just go ahead and check the max amounts anyone ever paid from payments max amount was $11 99
cents.
OK that makes sense.
We already took the average amounts.
And one of the last ones I want to show you is some and what some will do is just basically add all
those amounts together from payment.
So the entire sum.
So all the payments sum together is sixty one thousand three hundred twelve dollars and four cents.
OK.
Those are the real basics of Agri function.
So let's just go ahead and review what we learned we learned about from just going to type them here
.
We learned about men Max some average and we briefly again went over counts which we've seen before
So we went over minimax some average count and then we also learned how we can use round.
So let's go ahead and redo that so I can use round two round numeric values so I'm going to say round
first argument you passen is the column that's going to be a number.
Then you say comma and you put in the number of decimal places you want.
So in this case say I want one decimal place.
If I run this I will go ahead and chop off that 4 and run that down to zero.
OK.
Thanks everyone for listening to this lecture.
Again pretty basic stuff just the aggregate functions minimax some Furch count and then how to use round
.
Coming up next we'll learn how to use GROUP BY which is going to use a lot of these functions to be
our source for really powerful sequel queries.
OK thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next lecture