Hello everyone and welcome to the group by lecture.
So you just finished your general challenge and now it's time to take our understanding of sequel to
the next level.
Have some more to Fance features like group by group is going to be the first introduction to these
more advanced sequel functions.
It's a really common one but it's definitely still a level up from what we've been doing before.
So we're going to learn about the GROUP BY clause and or function of in how you want to call it.
And we'll see a few examples in action.
It's best explained through example but we'll go over some basic syntax first.
So the GROUP BY clause can be a bit confusing for beginners so make sure you take your time with this
topic.
And again it's one of the most useful tools in sequel.
So is the group by clause and how does it work.
The group by clause divides the rows returned from the select statement into groups so groups them by
a certain function.
So for each group you can apply an aggregate function and with an aggregate function does is it basically
aggregates all your information into a single value.
So for example calculating the sum of items is an example of an aggregate function it aggregates all
the item counts and gives you back a sum which is going to be a single number or count the number of
items in the groups.
That's also an aggregate function because it counts the specific number of items and then returns single
count values.
So basic group by syntax may look something like this.
You say select column 1 some sort of aggregate functions such as some are count and we'll learn different
aggregate functions throughout this lecture and you'll put it on another column you'll say from the
table name and then you'll group by a certain column.
There's many variations of this.
You don't actually have to call an aggregate function in order to do a group buy.
But most commonly you're you will be calling an aggregate function.
So we're really going to focus on just going through as many examples as possible of various use cases
that group by to really fully understand how to use it.
So with that being said let's go ahead and jump to P.G. admen because group buys really best learn through
example.
OK.
Go ahead and jump to PGA admen now.
OK so here we are at PGE admen.
We're going to go ahead and scroll up here click on DVD rental and click on X Q. arbitrary sequel queries
.
Go ahead and move this guy here.
OK.
So here we are at our sequel Ed..
First I want to show you a group by looks like without an aggregate function.
So we're going to focus on the payment table right now and then to say select let's just select everything
from the payment table and it's going to limit that to just two rows.
And this is just so we can get a reminder of what the payment table has.
So remember the payment table has a payment ID a customer id a staff ID rentals the amount and payment
date.
So you'll notice that if we go ahead and select couple more rows here and run this they are repetitions
of the customer ID right.
So here are a three for one.
So there's many entries of that specific customer making several payments.
So that makes sense.
So you have the same customer coming back.
So they have specific customer I.D. and are doing various payments.
OK.
So let's go ahead and use GROUP BY without applying an aggregate function first.
So we'll go ahead and say select the customer ID column from payments and let's go in just separate
this into a new line.
So it's really clear what we're doing we're saying select customer id column front payments and then
we're going to say group by and noticed there's a space there.
It's group space by.
And then we'll group it by the customer ID and so that is going to do it's going to group all your results
by the customer ID for the customer ID column.
And what that basically does is it just acts like you based like you just called the stinks on it because
it's only going to return the distinct customer ID's so it's grouping everything by the customer ID
.
So all those instances of multiple customers get grouped by into a single result.
So that's a group by looks like without an aggregate function.
It kind of acts like a distinct call.
So you won't be using it too much in this sort of syntax but this is just to begin our understanding
of how you can use GROUP BY.
So again GROUP BY here by itself without using an aggregate function basically acts like a distinct
clause.
So we get back five hundred ninety nine rows if we went ahead and didn't do that group by call.
Let's go in and see how many rows we get back we would have gotten back around over 14000 rows.
So you notice that group by function here or the group by clause what it's doing is it's grouping by
that customer id value.
So we again have group by here these various instances of duplicate customer IDs are getting grouped
together.
And then we have this return.
So it's basically acting like distinct here.
OK.
So more importantly the group by clause is really useful when it's used in conjunction with an aggregate
function.
Remember that aggregate function just aggregates a bunch of results into single values.
So for example to get how much a customer has been paid you can use the group by clause to divide payment
tables into groups and then for each group calculate total amounts of money by using the SUM function
and this sort of query and we're actually going to introduce you to the sum function.
So there's various aggregate functions and we've already seen something like counts and now we're going
to learn about some.
So let's say let's go ahead and say select customer id comma and then we're going to say some
amount we'll say from the payment table and then we'll say group by customer underscore ID.
So Michael let's go out and run that and then break down what it's doing.
So group by is doing here is the group by clause sort's the result set by customer ID and adds up the
amount that belongs to the same customer whenever the customer ID changes it adds the road to the return
result sets.
Now before we continue on here it should be noted that postscripts sequel is pretty flexible with what
you can call in the select statement versus what you can group by other sequel.
Engines have really specific rules when it comes to group by as far as you must select or you must call
an aggregate function on the same column that you're grouping by.
So for instance if I just go out and delete customer id table or column from the select statement and
run this it will still work.
It just won't report the customer ID to other sequel engines will have an issue with that and kind of
like when we are discussing order by the require you to specifically input the column you requested
and in the group by statement as well.
So it's good practice to always say select the column that you're grouping by or at least call some
sort of aggregate function such as some on the column you're grouping by other sequel engines will complain
if you don't have an aggregate function.
So remember earlier we did something like this just going to cut that out we lips.
Let's go ahead and delete that comma.
So earlier we did this which acted kind of as a distinct statement so just return the stink customer
IDs some sequel engines will complain and require you to put an aggregate function somewhere in your
select statement.
So just keep those rules in mind and kind of the pen than what sequel engine you're using.
Postscripts sequel's really flexible which is some something that's really nice about it.
OK so let's go in and go back to our original statement here saying select customer id comma some amounts
from payment's group by customer ID.
So again let's break this down as to what's actually happening here.
What we're telling sequel to do.
So here we're telling sequel to select the customer ID column.
So here's our first column customer ID and then we're saying Take the sum of the amount column from
the payment table grouped by the customer ID.
So what's that saying is for every customer id go ahead group by the customer ID and then some that
specific customers amount column.
So customer ID for instance our first volume customer ideas 2:51 and the same values 100 dollars and
seventy five cents.
That means the total amount that that customer spent or was paid ended up being $100 and 75 cents.
So that's basically just taking the sum of all their amounts and kind of condensing it or aggregating
it into a single value.
All right let's go ahead and Bill on top of this so you can also use an ORDER BY clause with a group
by clause to sort these groups so that I could say something like this.
I could say after saying group by the customer ID I could say order by the sum amount which is going
to be basically that some call them.
So I could say order by that some out.
Let's do it in descending order.
If I run this.
And so now I can see what customers have basically spent the most money or done the most payments.
OK.
So we kind of saw a basic example of how to use some with a group by statement.
Let's go ahead and go back a bit and see if we can use something like a count function of a group by
statements.
So let's go ahead and review what all the columns are in the payment table.
Gonna delete all that.
Well say select Asterix means select all columns from payments and also select all rows in this case
.
So we've got a payment idea customers the staff the rental the amount and payment date.
So let's say I wanted to count the number of transactions each staff has been processing.
I can group the payments table based on staff ID and then use the Count function to get the number of
transactions that each staff has been processing.
So if we kind of briefly scroll through this database there ends up being just two staff ID numbers
number one and number two.
So we have two staff members here and they're the ones that are processing the orders.
And I want to find out who's been processing the most orders and how much has each staff member been
processing.
So I'm going to do this using a group by statements.
So I'm going to say select staff underscore ID comma and Megami use count.
And I want to count.
Let's say the payments ID column from payments and I'm going to say grouped by staff ID loops that underscore
the semi-colon.
So if I run that I get this result.
So what's going on here.
The group by clause is basically getting that results that by the staff ID so it keeps a running total
of rows and whenever the staff changes it adds the road to the correct returning result set.
Now again back when we were discussing counts you notice or you should have noticed that it didn't really
matter whether you put a column name here or you put an asterix name here.
You'll get the same results.
And the reason for that is you're just counting the number of rows that your statement is returning
back.
So let's go ahead and break this down.
So I'm saying select the staff by the column and just count the number of rows returned from payments
.
When you group by the staff underscore ID column.
So it's taking all these instances of staff ID grouping them together basically aggregating them by
count and that is saying OK staff Id had 70000 CFIT to have 7300 for transactions and by the one process
seven thousand two hundred ninety two transactions.
OK.
So let's go ahead and go through a couple more examples the group by to really make sure we understand
it.
Let's go ahead and play around for another table will say selects Asterix everything.
So all the columns from let's go to say the film table and we'll say limit just five so we don't get
everything back.
OK.
So remember the film table has the titles of the films the description text the release year etc. but
I'm kind of interested in is figuring out how many films of each rating type do we have.
Some of that's RPG 13 etc..
So let's break this down.
Think about how we can do this.
So what I want to do is say selects the rating column from Phil and then one I'm going to do is also
say counts the rating from film and instead of saying limit five what I'm going to do is I'm going to
say group by the rating column something to take all the films in the database grouped them together
by their rating and then what I'm asking for back is the rating column.
And in that case it's actually just going to be the rating types so GBG P.G. 13 are in NC 17 and then
it's going to return a count of the number of occurrences for that rating.
When you grouped it together so count here is that aggregate function.
It's aggregating the counts of the different rating types.
So let's go ahead and run this is what we get back.
OK.
So if we look at the results here we get a column with the rating and then a count of the number of
occurrences where each of those ratings occurs.
OK so let's go out and see another example.
Let's go ahead and count the rental durations.
So we'll go ahead and say select just say select all columns from film limit one just so you can get
a quick overview of what the columns are again.
Quick scroll a little bit to the right you'll notice we have a rental duration column as well as a rental
rate column.
Let's say now I wanted to know the counts of the various rental durations so I could say something like
this selects rental underscore duration.
So that's how many days they took the movie out four and counts the number of those occurrences rental
duration from film.
And in this case I'm going out to say group by the rental duration group by rental duration.
So what question is this answering to.
And going to answer.
How many counts of occurrences are there for each of these rental duration periods.
So if we kind of take a quick scan at this it looks like five and seven day rental duration periods
have the lowest amount of occurrences and the highest amount occurrences is a six day rental duration
period.
OK let's go ahead and do one more group by example before we head on to the challenge for the byes.
And if we go ahead and selects the rental rates call them and let's say the rating column from film
and let's not group by anything else just take a quick look at them say limit let's say five and run
that.
So it's a quick sampling example.
We have the rental rates and the rating.
Let's say I wanted to know the average rental rate for a movie's rating.
What I can do is say group by the rating column and almost all go ahead and ask for the rating column
and then I'm going to take the average of the rental rates.
So I'm going to say select the rating and the average rental rates of the various rating types from
film group by rating.
So if I go ahead and run this I should get quite a few decimal points.
But because it is taking it pretty exact average so there are a lot of decimal points there.
But basically I can see here if there's any sort of trend that different rated movies have different
rental rates.
Looks like they're pretty even across the board with the highest average rental rate being P.G. movies
and the lowest average rental rate being Jeem movies.
OK.
So we already seen a couple of examples how we can use GROUP BY with area functions and without aggregate
functions in order to solve various problems you're really going to be tested on grouped by and challenged
on it in the next group by challenge.
So hopefully they'll test your understanding and group by Take your time with this topic.
Sometimes a little tricky to get a hold of.
But basically once your mind makes the switch to understanding how to do a group buy you'll find it's
really intuitive to use later on in the course.
OK thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next lecture.
We'll have the group by challenge and just a quick note in that group by challenge.
I will just be giving you the solution on a slide.
We'll actually be coding it out together just to really make sure you understand the group by concept
.
OK.
Thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next lecture