Hello everyone and welcome to the group by Challenge lecture.
We're going to keep things pretty simple in this lecture.
Just three basic challenges.
They're all going to be kind of similar to what we saw in the large group of examples in the previous
lecture.
So hopefully you'll be able to reference and rewashed that previous lecture in case you're still having
trouble with the group like concept in order to tackle these challenges that we're about to face.
OK.
So again General challenge tasks we're going to utilize all the skills you've learned so far.
Except in this case each of these challenges needs a GROUP BY statement.
You're going to get hints.
The challenge right after you get the problem statement and then instead of just showing you a solution
since GROUP BY sometimes is difficult for beginners.
I'm going to walk you through a solution and actually type it out myself with explanations in Peachi
admen.
OK.
Again these challenges are going to be difficult.
So try breaking down the problem into individual tasks.
Your first challenge is this.
Here's the situation.
We have two staff members with staff IDs one and two and we want to give a bonus to the staff member
that handled the most payments.
So your question is how many payments.
Each staff member handle and how much was the total amount processed by each staff member.
So you have those two questions to solve.
And coming up next are some hints good and positive do you now see if you can solve those two questions
for the challenge in order to figure out who should give our bonus to certify the one or step ID to
.
Coming onto the hints you're going to ease the payment table.
And remember to use some sort of aggregate function with that group by statements.
OK.
So here comes the solution for it.
So the solution is this select CFIT count amount some amount from payment group by staff ID.
Let's go ahead and jump to P.G. admen so we can work this out fully.
OK.
Here I am at PG admin.
I actually already have the sequel Ed. open just went ahead and ran an arbitrary sequel on the DVD rental
database.
So again we had to figure out who are we going to give bonuses to.
So if we just say select let's say staff underscore ID and the amount column from the payment table
we can get an idea of what we're working with here.
So we have the staff ID will notice it's just two in ones Iligan Group By to verify that.
And then we have the amount column and what we want to do is figure out two things the total amount
of transactions and the total sum of that amount.
So here's what we're going to do.
We want to do is group by the staff ID.
Right.
So we know that's a necessary step here since we want to get all the information just by staff.
So it's going to group all the instances where staff ideas to an audience answers were staff ideas one
.
And then we want to do two separate aggregate functions.
One is to count on amount and that's going to count the number of instances of that amount for that
specific staff ID.
And then it's going to we're also wanting to some the amount because we wanted to answer two questions
.
One was who did the most transactions and then the other one was who did the most total in the transactions
OK so let's go in and run this in now we have these answer columns so we have the staff ID tune one
.
We have the counts.
So it looks like here staff ID number two made the most transactions.
Not a whole lot more but they edged out staff ID number one and they also had a larger sum of the total
amount of money processed and that makes sense because they did more overall as it counts.
Okay so just to break that down again we had a group by that staff ID and we had added to aggregate
functions count and sum.
Now you may have actually done this as two separate queries you may have done first count and then have
done some but its actually okay to do both of these counts amounts and some amounts.
All right.
But that being said let's go ahead and jump back to that presentation and see the next challenge.
Okay.
Here we are at the presentation again.
And your next challenge is this corporate headquarters is auditing our store and they want to know the
average replacement cost of movies by rating.
So for example R-rated movies have an average replacement cost of $20 and 23 cents.
So the challenges we want to know the average replacement costs of all the movies by their rating.
So what are the average placement costs for P.G. movies P.G. either teen movies are movies etc. and
the quick can't they should all be pretty close.
You shouldn't see any huge discrepancy in the average replacement costs of these movies by reading.
Kind of makes sense.
OK.
Coming up next is some stronger hints.
So that and possibly enough you want to do a few hints.
Here come the hints it's OK.
So quick Kintz you need a film table.
And remember again you need to use an aggregate function with the group by statements.
All right good and positivity.
Now take another stab at it.
Here comes the solution.
So here's the solution you had to select rating average replacement cost from film and group by rating
.
It's good and jumped the PGA even one more time and really walk through this.
OK.
Here PGA admin.
Well we're going to do is go ahead and say selects rading remember wanting to get the average replacement
cost by rating so we can actually kind of almost translate that question directly into sequel so what
are we looking for.
We're looking for the average replacement cost by rating meaning I need I already know I need to have
just the rating column because I want that in my results.
And if we keep translating that basically English sentence into a sequel I also said I wanted to know
the average replacement costs.
So the aggregate function for average is just a veggie and I'm going to pass in the replacement cost
column from the film table and I wanted to group by rating so that basically aggregates the replacement
costs as an average for the films by rating.
So here we go.
Here the results are rated movies.
You can see here is $20 and 23 cents and it looks like G NC 17 mpg 13 all basically around $20 and maybe
a little surprisingly P.G. was about a dollar less than everything else.
OK.
So just a quick reminder we had the round function that we could also explore.
So in case you didn't want this many decimal points you could have also done this have said passen round
here.
I remember the first argument in surround It's just that column and then you put a comma to pass and
the second argument which is the number of decimal places you want after that.
In this case I just want two decimal places and it's money.
And then here we have rounded off to two decimal places.
OK.
So let's go ahead and then tackle the third challenge for you in that group by Challenge lecture.
I'm going to go ahead and jump back to that presentation.
OK so here we are at the last challenge.
And so it's going to be a little tricky especially if the group by statement.
So what we want is to send coupons to the five customers who has spent the most amount of money at our
store.
So the five customers that have done basically the most payment amounts by money.
So not by count but by the actual sum of how much money they've made.
OK.
So what I want to do is get me the customer IDs of those top five spenders.
OK good and positive.
Now coming up next are some hints.
So here are the hints.
Go out and show them.
So a couple of hints.
You're going to need to use the payment table and you're also going to need to use a group by and an
order by that order by is going to be useful for trying to get the top five of something.
And what I want you to do is pay careful attention to what you actually want to order by.
That's probably what you're going to have if you do have trouble of this that might be what you're having
trouble with is what are you actually trying to order by.
Is it a whole column or is it some sort of aggregate function just keep that in mind.
OK.
Let's go to show you the solution now.
So the solution is this.
Select the customer ID column some the amount column from the payment table group by customer ID and
here's kind of the trick to it.
You had to order by the sum of the amounts not just by the amounts and in descending order.
I also put in limit fives and so only one of the top five.
Let's go ahead and jump to pediatrician and walk through the solution.
OK.
Here we are PGE admen.
Let's go ahead and check out the solution to this.
So again what do we want to know.
We wanted to know the top five customers spending money at our store.
So we're going to say say select
customer ID and then we want to know how much they were spending.
So some of the amount column from the payment table.
And then we wanted to group by customer ID and that makes sense because that's what we actually want
to sort by order by right.
Or excuse me that's what we actually want to know.
We want to know which customers have spent the most.
That's what I want to group by and then getting on the order by statement.
This is the tricky part.
So what you wanted to order by was not the amount column but we wanted to order by the sum of the amount
column and you would have got an error if you hadn't put the some in there and we'll have in descending
order because we want to get the top 5.
So from highest to lowest in descending order in order just to get five of them I can say limit's 5
.
So if I run that off those are the customer IDs and that's how much they've spent.
So looks like customer IDs 1:48 5 2 6 1 7 8 1 3 7 1 4 4 are the customers we should send those coupons
to.
Again let's break this down one more time because it's a little tricky especially if this order by some
.
So we wanted to select the customer ID column that makes sense and we wanted to sum the amount column
per every customer.
So we want to aggregate all that amount that the customer spends into a final sum for each of those
customers one do that from the payment table and then we want to group by the customer right in order
to do those aggregations for each customer.
The tricky part was what you actually wanted to order by you wanted to order by the sum amount column
and remember you can really only order by columns that you're selecting.
Here in postscripts allows you to not do that but it's good practice and just logically it makes sense
to only have order by options of the columns you select.
Right.
And so we basically have two options here.
You want to order by the customer.
Or the one order by that some amount.
In this case it makes the most sense to order by the same amounts as we want to get the top five spenders
.
And then we specify in descending order to go from highest to lowest and then we limit 5 just to get
those top 5.
Okay.
So and back to the presentation real quick I want you to note we're going to see group by show up a
lot so don't worry if you feel like you kind of got these but wasn't enough examples for you.
You're going to see group by over and over again and you'll eventually feel extremely comfortable with
that and it's just going to it's going to there's something of a trigger in your mind or are you just
going to start thinking of things in a group by syntax so don't worry about it you're going to see it
plenty of times ahead.
So I don't think that right now we're just going to stop showing group by forever.
You'll see it happen over and over again.
We're going to learn now and the next lecture is how do you use the having clause and the having clause
is basically using a where statement if you have something gripped by.
OK.
So even that doesn't make quite a lot of sense now.
They'll make a lot of sense than an ex arguing over the having clause.
All right.
I hope these challenges are helpful to you and I will see if the next lecture.
Thank you everybody.