Hello everyone and welcome to the having lecture.
So we're going to learn about that having clause how to use it and then we'll see a few examples in
action.
It's actually pretty straightforward once you get a good understanding of group by.
So we'll basically just go almost straight into the examples after showing you the syntax here.
So we often use that having clause in conjunction with the GROUP BY clause to filter group rows that
do not satisfy a specified condition.
The way I like to think about the having clause is it's almost just like the WHERE statement or that
where clause.
Except you're using it with a GROUP BY statement.
So it kind of looks like this is a syntax.
Notice is basically almost the same syntax of using a group by Except if you want to do filtering by
some sort or condition instead of a where statement you say having and then some sort of condition here
so you can say for instance select column 1.
Let's say you are angry a function was a sum or something you say so at column 1 some of column 2 from
table name grouped by column 1 and then the having condition would be something like having some of
column to greater than $200 something like that.
And we'll see plenty of examples to show you this.
So again the having clause sets the condition for group rows created by the group by clause after the
group by clause applies while the WHERE clause sets the condition for individual rows before the group
by clause applies.
And this is really the main difference between the having and the WHERE clauses.
So they're really similar but the WHERE clause sets the condition for individual rows before you call
a Group By.
Whereas having sets that condition after you called the Group By Let's go out and see some examples
so we can flesh out our understanding of this topic.
Me go ahead and jump to PGA admen now.
OK so here I am I already open the sequel editor from PGE admen.
Again this is arbitrary or opening that execute an arbitrary sequel query editor.
So let's go ahead and show you just a quick example of a normal group by statement and then we'll apply
the having clause to it.
So a typical group by statement may look something like this select customer id call a comma than some
the amount.
So this should look familiar basically just trying to say what customers has spent the most money etc.
from that payment table group by customer underscores ID.
So we've already seen this before.
Let's go ahead and run that.
OK so here we have the customer ID that actually ID number and the total amount that they spent.
Now I can apply a having clause to selectively filter out these groups and let's say I wanted to only
select customers who have been spending more than $200.
So I would do this.
I would say having And now the having clause I can do filters based off my group by statement.
So and that what that means is basically I can filter off things such as these aggregate functions that
would only work given that I had a group by.
So I could say having the sum of that amount greater than $200.
And then if I run that those are my two customers who are spent more than $200.
OK.
Let's go in and look at another example of the having clause this time with let's say a count every
function so we can get a good idea of how it works again.
So it's going to clear all this.
And let's go in and explore the customer table a little more will say a select store underscore ID column
and then we're going to count the number of occurrences of the customer ID.
So this going to return the number of customers per store then we're going to say from the customer
table group by the store ID.
So I basically just want a count of the customers force per store.
So that kind of makes sense.
And here they are we have two stores store ID one story of the two.
And there we have the count of the customer IDs.
OK.
So now I can filter this again using a having clause.
And again key point here is that the having is doing the filtering after the group by statements meaning
I can do a filter based off these aggregate function columns.
So I could do something like this.
Having count of the customer ID so that count column.
And let's say I just want to know who has more than 300 customers.
So that should only really return one row right.
Store Id won here.
So it's going to run that.
And there it is.
OK.
So hopefully I was pretty straightforward.
Again it's really similar to where except again you're having claws is going to perform that filtering
.
On that specific conditions on this case the condition is that the count's customer ID is greater than
300 based off of your group by statement.
OK.
So let's go ahead and do one more example just to really make sure we understand this and then we'll
set you off on the challenge.
Go ahead and clear all this out in a way we're going to do here show an example of using where and having
just to further illustrate their points.
And why would you use one versus the other.
So I'm gonna go to say selects Let's go in and select everything just so we get an idea of what columns
we're working with from the film table and it's going to limit that to just a few rows so we don't spend
a lot of time.
OK.
So again here's a list of all our films the columns we're going to be focused on right now.
Is this rating column.
That's the RPG Picchu thirteen etc. and the rental rate column.
So that's how much it actually costs to rent that movie.
So let's go and specify those two euros.
So raiding rental rates let's go dance put son in line from film and let's say I wanted to only grab
certain film ratings.
Let's say I'm only interested in R G and P.G..
So how would I do that.
I would use a WHERE clause and say rading I remember since I kind of want a list of ratings I'm going
to use in in passing a list of ratings so r g P.G. semi-colon run that.
OK so now I have my list of movies where the rating is either R G or P.G. meaning the rating was in
this list.
Again the list is just parentheses and commas separating each of these what are essentially strings
with these quotes here and then a semi colons and that.
So here's my list of all the movies here.
So it doesn't have PGE teens or NC 17.
And now let's go ahead and do a group by
rating and let's do that group by rating for it to make sense.
What I'm going to do is go ahead and put an aggregate function here for the average Rensil rate.
So now what I'm going to do is select the rating of the movie and figure out the average rental rate
for that movie.
Given that rating.
So it's going to do that.
OK.
So I run that the school look at the results here.
I have the movie ratings RPG and GI because they filter those based off my where statement and that
makes sense because I'm doing that filtering before I do any group buys.
Right.
I'm not calling any sort of aggregate function on the rating column.
So it makes sense that I'm able to actually use where to do some filtering out here.
With that rating in our EPG.
All right.
So now what's the use case for having.
Well the use case for having would be doing some sort of filtering on a condition after the group by
statements.
And so that would really mean filtering on some sort of aggregate function column.
So in this case that would be the average rental rate.
Let's say I only want to get the rows back where the average rental rate was less than $3 then I could
say having average rental rates less than three semi colon may go ahead and run that and now we get
a nice final result.
We get the movies that are in RG P.G. so that rating where they are where the sorry excuse me the rating
that was an RG NPG were the average Rensil rate was less than $3.
And we had it all in the group by statement.
OK.
So go ahead and pause a video really focus and make sure you understand this entire sequel query.
I think what's really impressive about where you are now in the course and the sequel query is if you
had just started the course not knowing anything about programming or how to use sequel this would have
looked like a really intimidating query.
But I think now even if you had just learned about the having clause in this lecture you're actually
able to really read and understand this query.
So it's going to break down one more time before we and the lecturer will say again we're selecting
the rating column and the average rental rate because we're grouping by rating were selected from the
film table and we're using a where clause first because we're filtering out the rating column which
doesn't have an aggregate function on it.
So we're saying we're rating in our g mpg group by the rating.
And then we're going to use having which is going to filter after the group by statement is going to
say having and it's going to do a filtering off the error function.
So average rental rate was less than three.
OK again make sure you can type this out.
Play around with it.
Explore your own examples.
But coming up next are going to be a few challenges just to make sure you really understand that having
claws.
All right thanks everyone and I will see it next lecture.