Hello everyone and welcome to the having challenge lecture.
So again we're going to have just general challenge tasks utilizing all the skills you've learned so
far but each challenge in particular is going to need a Having a statement going to be two challenges
in this lecture.
Once the challenge or business task is presented to you you'll get some hints of the challenge and then
a walk through solutions that challenge so the challenges are going to be difficult.
So try breaking down the problem into individual tests.
OK.
Here's your first challenge.
We want to know what customers are eligible for a platinum credit card program and the requirements
are that the customer has at least the total of 40 transaction payments.
So that's the count of the transaction payments.
What I want to know is what customers by customer ID are eligible for the credit card again.
Basically just find me the customers that have at least a total count of 40 transaction payments.
OK.
Let's go ahead and give you some hints.
So the hint is you'll need to use the payment table and don't want to give too much away here but remember
you going to have to use some sort of aggregate function with a group by and the use of a having clause
.
OK.
Coming up next the solutions are good and positivity enough if you don't want to see it yet.
OK here it comes.
So here's the solution you need to select the customer ID column count the amount column from payments
and then group by the customer ID then what you had to do is filter that counts amounts by the conditions
specified by the credit card which was at least 40 instances or 40 transactions.
So that means you had to say having count amounts greater than 40 some might call in.
OK.
So hopefully now that you see a solution it's pretty straightforward.
Basically just using that group by and again using having to filter out based on some condition after
you've done the group by statements let's go ahead and do the final and second challenge.
So when grouped by rating what movie ratings have an average rental duration of more than five days
.
Again when you group them by rating what movie ratings so the films have an average Rensil duration
of more than five days.
OK here come the hints hint is you'll need to use the film table.
And again remember you're gonna have to use some sort of aggregate function of group by and the use
of the having clause.
OK.
Coming up next is the solutions to good impassivity enough you don't want to see a solution.
All right here it comes.
So here's a solution.
You had to select the rating column and then select the average rental duration.
So then you had to say that from the film table in group it by rating.
After that in order to figure out what by group by rating what movies ratings have the average rental
duration greater than five days you had to use that having clause.
So you have to group by rating and say having the average rental duration be greater than five.
OK.
So that's really all there is to it.
And hopefully by now you're seeing and getting a sense of how to use having.
It's it's really not that tough.
Once you understand that you're basically filtering the condition just like a WHERE clause except you're
doing it after you've done that group by meaning most common use cases are going to be on some sort
of aggregate column function.
OK.
So great job on the group by section.
Coming up next is an assessment test to fully test everything we've learned so far without giving you
any specific hints on what specific clauses to use.
OK.
So thanks everyone great job on the group section and I will see you at the next lecture where we go
over that assessment's us