Hello everyone and welcome to the lecture on the windows.
Post sequel installation.
First thing you're going to want to do is go ahead and open a web browser and go to w w w post gress
sequel dot org.
So let me go ahead and jump to my web browser so I can show you what this looks like.
Ok so I'm at my web browser now and something I wanted to point out is you can actually just google
search postscripts sequel and the very first thing that will pop up as far as non ad links is going
to be post gresse sequel.
So go ahead and click that link and it should take you to a page that looks like this.
And then the next thing you're going to do is go ahead and go to download.
And once that's loaded you'll see postgresql sequel court distribution and you'll see some prebuilt
packages which are going to do is click on Windows and then you're going to go ahead and download the
graphical installer.
And what this is going to do is going to really make the process of installing super straightforward
and it's actually very quick and fast and it's also going install a very important graphical tool called
PGE admen three.
So let's go ahead and click download here and I'll take you to a new page.
Go ahead and not register and what you're going to do is go ahead depending on your computer download
the latest version.
Right now it's nine point five point one for me.
And depending on whether you have a 32 bit or 64 bit here in your computer is probably going to be 64
bit.
Go ahead and click the download that's appropriate for you click it and your download should begin shortly
and the pending browser using just see it.
Come over here.
All right.
So go ahead and jump to the end of that download.
All right so I went ahead and jumped to the finished download.
Go ahead and click on that executable file.
Go ahead and say yes and you should have the graphical installer jump up.
OK.
There it is.
Let's go ahead and all you do is click next.
Save it if you want to whatever directory but I'm going to choose the default under program files.
PostgreSQL sequel.
Nine point five.
Go ahead and click next.
Go ahead and store your data under the Data folder.
That's fine too.
And this is the important part.
You're going to want to provide a password for a database.
Super User.
So we'll go over later on.
What a super user actually is.
But make sure you remember whatever password you type in here.
So let me go ahead and fill this out.
OK so I filled that out.
I'm going to go ahead and click next.
And go ahead and leave the default port.
It should probably be five four three two or a very similar number that is default.
Go ahead and leave this location for the database cluster's default.
And then now you're ready to begin installing so.
Go ahead and click next and you'll notice that actually installs very quickly.
Again make sure you're write down your super user password somewhere so you remember it will be going
over that later on what it actually means.
But basically you may need that password later on to access and create tables as a super user.
All right.
I'll go ahead and fast forward to this finishing.
So we're actually almost done that only it was a jump of about 20 seconds.
He should the whole process should only take up most just a few minutes.
You'll notice it's going to initialize the database cluster.
Say this may take a few minutes depending on the speed of a computer.
That speed may vary.
OK so once that's done initialising you'll notice he has a stack builder option.
Go ahead and just click that off.
You don't need it for this course and then just go ahead and say finish and that's it.
All right.
In the next lecture I will show you how to load the sample data into your newly created Postgres sequel
installation.
Thanks everyone and I will see if the next lecture