Hello everyone and welcome to the lecture video for the sample database installation.
Walk through this lecture is going to be walking you through how to download and install the database
that we're going to be using throughout the course.
First thing you should know is in the previous lecture it was just an article and had the resource on
where to actually download the files so if you go to the previous lecture and check the resources for
that lecture you'll notice there was two files to download.
One was a PMG file and the other was a zip file that PMG file is just a picture diagram of what the
database looks like and the DVD rental that zip files the important one that contains the actual database
and that's from the previous lectures.
So go ahead and check that out.
You should have downloaded it and keep track of the actual file path where you downloaded it to.
Next thing you want to know is if you're just a beginner in the program before then you definitely just
want to watch this video in its entirety first and then go back and implement the instructions as you
watch it a second time.
There's going to be a few key commands that are a little complicated.
Nothing too crazy but it might be better if you're just a beginner to watch the entire video first and
then go back a second time to follow along as you implement the instructions.
Last thing will cover all the commands you see in this lecture and future lectures so don't worry about
fully memorizing all the commands as we type them out.
So for instance there may be a command where I say select everything from a certain table.
Don't worry about memorizing that or learning it.
That's just to check if the installation of work.
So all the commands you're going to see in this lecture are just to check if everything's installed
and working correctly.
Again that goes for the command lines and the sequel prompts so don't worry about those We're going
to cover everything in future lectures.
Everything you see here in this particular lecture you have to type out and copy it exactly as I'm putting
it in.
But don't worry about memorizing those particular commands because we'll go over everything later on
in the future.
OK.
With that being said I want to go ahead and jump to a browser real quick so I can give you a little
bit of background on the actual database we're using for this course.
All right.
So I wanted to show you was the Wikipedia or Wiki for the postgresql sequel sofrito wiki that post gresse
sequel dot org slash wiki slash sample underscore databases.
You'll have this sample databases page and the one we're using is based off of my sequel's classic database
which is called Sakia.
But for postscripts they renamed that to Gila.
So just keep that in mind.
And the reason we're choosing it is because this is probably by far the most common sample database
to use when instructing someone about sequel commands or any particular syntax of sequel or particular
database which uses sequel.
So that's why we're using it that way you can use these skills and immediately just quickly transfer
them to any other tutorials that use the Akila database which is by far the most common database used
.
So it's an extremely famous database.
It's inspired by DVD store.
So if you went ahead and downloaded the PMG file from the previous lecture you'll notice you have this
picture and this image essentially shows what the database actually looks like as far as relationships
and its various tables.
So we'll go over everything later on and tackle these tables one by one as we begin to learn the sequel
commands.
But just keep in mind if you ever need an overview of all the tables are what's actually going on from
a bird's eye view of the entire database.
You can reference that pinchy file.
OK.
So once you get more advanced with sequel and postgresql sequel you can check out these other sample
databases to play around with.
All right.
So we have our DVD rental that zip file downloaded and you have your top PNB file downloaded what you're
going to do is go ahead and go to the location where you saved that zip file.
OK.
So I went ahead and jumped to the location where I saved it.
You'll notice it was a compressed zip file here.
So you had to do was right click this and either use 7 zip or when rar whatever your extraction program
is.
Go ahead and extract it all here.
And then you should either end up with a winner or file or some tar file.
But you should have extracted it to some other file.
But you want to do is go ahead and remember where ever you saved it what the path to that file was.
So if you're in Windows you can go up here and if you click it you'll see a path here.
So here it's C program files postgresql.
So yours would probably be straight in downloads.
If you didn't move it anywhere but I move mine to postscripts sequel so you can go in and follow this
if you want.
But after unzipping it now I have my tar file and I know it's full file path location that's going to
be important because we'll reference this later on when we tell postscripts where it actually assembled
a database from.
OK.
So we've done so far as you've downloaded the DVD rental that's it and you unzipped it and gotten the
tar file out or some sort of when rar file.
So you've answered it and you're ready to go.
Next thing you're going to want to do is go ahead and open up PGE adamant.
So go ahead and search for it so I'll search for PGE admen and then I'll go ahead and open it up.
All right.
So now I have PGE outman and it looks a little something like this.
Notice we don't have many commands available to us because we haven't really started anything.
So the next thing I want you to do is go ahead and check it out.
You have postscripts sequel whatever version you downloaded and the local hosts should match what you
had during the installation.
So in our case it was 5 4 3 2 which was the default.
And if you go ahead and wups click on that you'll notice you have some properties start showing up and
you actually get some abilities here on the toolbar.
So that's a single click.
What I wanted to do now is go ahead and double click and then enter the password that you put in would
remember that was your super user password that try to memorize.
You can go in and store the password in case you don't want to have to worry about it later on.
And then click OK we'll give you a warning about saving passwords.
If you're the only one operating on the computer that's totally fine.
And so this is the toy database you should be totally fine.
All right.
So you went ahead to use your super user password and we'll talk about super users later on.
But that was the password that you had during the installation process so put it in there just go ahead
and check off that it remembers it.
So you know to constantly be putting it in and you'll see you have a tab on databases and you'll see
post graphs and you also have table spaces and log in rolls.
So continue along with this next thing you want to do is double click Post postscripts and you'll see
it expand.
You'll have catalogs event triggers extensions schemas and if you expand schemas you'll see public and
if you expand public let's go ahead and make this a little bigger so you can view everything.
You'll notice you start having tables trigger functions views etc..
So eventually want to do as we finished the database installation process is essentially fill out this
with the DVD rental tables that we saw in that image.
So right now everything 0 which makes sense because we haven't actually create anything or populating
anything.
Next thing you're going to want to do is go ahead and open your command prompts if you go to search
and say C and D.
This is your command prompts.
So you go ahead and open it up and it should look something like this.
Now that we have a command prompt open the next thing we're going to do is change the directory of the
command prompt to the bin folder of postscripts sequel.
So by jump back here and go to postscripts sequel and click 9.5 bin.
So this is where I want to be in my command prompt So this is the path I want see Program Files postscripts
sequel 9.5 bin and it should look really similar for you.
Maybe a different version 9.6 for using this in the future et cetera.
So going to go ahead and copy that.
So again just keep that in mind.
That's exactly what we're going to do right now as far as the command line where we're going to change
to or the directory change to at the command line.
So if I go ahead and bring back my command line what I'm going to type in is CD D and that stands for
change directory.
So right now if you notice if I just take that out I'm just under users in my user name going to CD
to change their rectory and then go ahead and copy that line that you just had as far as the directory
to the benefit.
And you'll notice if I just showed you but if I do control Viets to paste it's not going to work.
So you're going to want to do is right click and then do paste.
All right then click enter and now your command line is that the.
Been file.
So again what you're going to do is check up here.
Go to see Program Files postscripts sequel 9.5 slash been know where that directory is and then go to
your command line and at your command line what you're going to do is type CD for change the rectory
and then right click and paste in that entire file path OK.
So just to review I've done so far.
You've downloaded that zip file.
You went ahead and unzip it.
Now you have a winner or tar file and then you went ahead.
Open up your command prompt with ACMD and then you change directory using CD to that Ben file of postscripts
sequel.
All right.
Next are going to do is hop back to PGE admen.
OK so here I am at PGE Addleman.
And what we're gonna do is if you just collapse all this post gresse so selecting post gress.
Go ahead and click on here which is execute arbitrary sequel queries.
Click that and you should get another window pop up that looks something like this.
Let me go and expand it.
So it looks a little cleaner.
So there you have this and what you're going to do is give a very basic sequel query and we'll go over
these exact queries later on.
But for now just go ahead and copy exactly as I type and what I'm going to do is say creates
database
DVD rental semi colon and that's it.
And then I'm going to go ahead and click here to execute the query.
And then once it's done executing You should see queery return successfully with no result in some amount
of time.
So that makes sense.
It should return no results because right now all this is doing is creating the database.
And just to reiterate we will go over all these commands later on before right now just go ahead and
copy exactly as I'm typing.
To fully install everything so we just create space database DVD rental semi colon and then go ahead
and run and execute that query.
OK.
So once you've run that go ahead and minimize that.
And if we go back here to databases or your PGE admin go ahead and click refresh.
And after you refresh that you should see your DVD rental database.
Now keep in mind you should have clicked and highlighted database and then click refresh if you just
highlight post gresse and click refresh.
Nothing happened.
So click databases and refresh and you should see the DVD rental database.
And if you expand it you'll see schemas public and again right now we have no tables or anything.
So basically what we just did was created an empty database that has not been populated yet.
The information that we're going to populate it with is contained in that zip file that we unzipped
earlier but so far all we've done is just you executed that sequel query which was create space database
DVD rental.
So I call and then you went back to P.G. admen.
So just go ahead and minimize that.
Go back to PGE admin click on database's click refresh and once you've done that you should see that
DVD rental.
They'll have a little X on it basically meaning that there's nothing there yet you haven't clicked that
yet.
OK so now we've got to do is populate this.
All right.
So now the trickiest part that we're going to do is actually populate this with some tables.
So go ahead and go back to your command prompt.
I'll open it up right now and at your command prompt.
Remember you should be in Ben what you're going to do is basically type out exactly what I am typing
up.
You're going to say PGE underscore restore space.
So that stands for postscripts restore.
So essentially what we're doing on a very basic level is restoring an old database.
Next thing we're going to do is specify a user or we're going to do that with Dash uppercase you post
so users postscripts another space go Dasch D which stands for database.
And we're going to Taipan DVD rental which was rumored that that was the database we just created using
that secret query.
And then finally what you have to do is put in the path of where your dot tar file is.
So let me go ahead and show you how to do that.
So if we go back to Windows Explorer here remember I have postscripts sequel.
I have this tar file so I can go ahead and do is if you want you can go to properties and it will give
you the location path.
So that's one way of doing it.
Either way of doing it is if just click here.
Remember you can always use edit copy.
OK.
So I have that.
So I know where my tar file is going to go and go back to my command prompt.
And now that I'm back on my command prompt what I'm going to do is paste.
So if you notice I have a dot dash DV The space DVD rental the file path and I'm just going to add to
it the DVD rental dock tar and I'm going to click enter.
All right so you probably noticed that I got an error here and this is a common error.
Ill say too many command line arguments.
And the reason for that is because of the space between program and files here.
So we're going to either put some escape characters in order to make the PGE underscore or restore operate
correctly.
If you're just in download slash DVD rental that tar you probably didn't get this error.
But the reason it shows is because if you accidentally or on purpose placed your tar file and zip file
into a file path that ended up having some spaces in there you may get some errors.
So to fix that what we're going to do is go ahead and put some escape characters for those spaces.
I'm going to just go up on my keypad and that will restore all the lines that we just written out so
don't type them again.
And what I want to do is take care of this space here.
So one thing you could have done is a backslash escaped that particular character but we're going to
do instead it's a little easier is go ahead and just in case this whole thing in quotes.
So I put a double quote there and Wessling going to put a double quote at the end.
I'll click enter.
Now you notice it's actually running.
And there's no air.
So let me just go again and reiterate what we just did.
So I said PGE underscore restore space dash you for a user.
So that's basically a minus sign that dash capital you space postscripts space minus the dash sign D
for the database.
Remember we created the DVD rental database and then you're going to go ahead and put in the file path
to your tar file if your file path.
A space in it.
So for example programs space files.
You'll get an error that will be too many command line arguments.
You won't get the error if you did everything correctly and just had to in downloads so ignore this
information if it's not applicable to you.
But if he did get the error you can either put an escape character here which is just a backslash before
files or the easier way to do it is just in case everything in either single quotes or double quotes
so that entire file path here put a double quote for C double quote after tar.
Then click enter and everything should work.
So now if you go back to PGE admen and click refresh on DVD rental boom you'll notice.
Now we have our tables here.
But the actor the address the category city etc. We have our views trigger functions and functions.
So I know that was kind of a long and complicated process.
So let's go ahead and just review everything we did.
All right.
So for a very quick overview of everything we just did.
You had to download the zip file for DVD rental extract the tar file from DVD rental.
That's it.
Open up P.G. Aardman and then go run that query that we showed which was create database DVD rental
.
So Michael and then you had to open your command prompt you could do that by searching CNID you to use
CD to change the victory to the postscripts bin folder like we showed and then you had to use the command
PGE underscore restore that you postscripts the DVD rental and then encapsulate and quotes the file
path to your doctor file.
All right.
So I know that was really complicated and we kind of did a lot there.
I promise it will get a lot easier in the future and we'll see much better ways of doing and creating
the database and restoring databases from a particular source.
But this was just the very basics as far as just getting everything installed and ready to go.
We actually learn how to do all of this in a much better fashion in a couple lectures in the future
.
Okay thanks.
And feel free to ask any discussion questions in the forums in case you're lost or get stuck in any
steps.
Okay thanks and I'll see you at the next lecture.