Hello everyone and welcome to the views lecture.
So in the views section of the course we're going to be doing is introducing you to database views concepts
and then showing you how to manage views such as creating modifying and removing views from the database
.
So what is a view.
Well formally we can think of you as a database object that's that of a stored query.
So if you can be accessible as a virtual table in postgresql sequel.
So in other words this post-career sequel views just the logical table that represents data of one or
more underlying tables through some sort of select statements.
So this is probably better explained through the use of an illustration.
Imagine you have a database.
So here we have this kind of like stack of disks representing or a database.
And we have three tables in it.
One two two and three.
And each of those tables has some columns in it.
If you want to get a particular query to show certain columns and join these tables in a particular
way what you would have to do is do what it says here on the bottom some sort of select statement of
columns from then a bunch of joint statements.
But you can do is take advantage of the view statements and eventually convert this entire complex query
into a simple statement that just says select everything from view.
So notice that what The View is doing is just showing you a view of a particular select query.
But it's not actually doing is doubling up and storing that data physically.
It's almost just like that particular query is being pointed to this view of it.
So what have you does it help simplify the complexity of a query because you can just query the view
which is based off of some other complex query and sort of having to rewrite it.
You could just use a simple select statement with your new view object.
So like a table you can grant permissions to users through a view that contains specific data that users
are authorized to see.
And if you provide a consistent layer even the columns of underlying table changes.
So to create a view we use to create these statements.
And the simplest syntax of the creative statement just looks like this.
You just basically say create view the name of whatever you want to call that view.
Then you say as.
And then you just have your whole select query of a semi-colon.
So this is better shown through just a quick example in postgresql sequel.
So let's go ahead and hop to P.G. Adwan and open up a sequel Ed..
OK so here I am at PG admin what I'm going to do is go ahead and click our DVD rental database.
We worked with a lot and I'm going to go ahead and execute an arbitrary sequel query on it.
We're going to be doing is messing around with two tables.
The first one is going to be the customer tables slushes review what's in it.
As far as the columns.
So I have these customer IDs story.
DS first name last name email and then some time information and then the other table we're going to
be looking at is the address table so the address table has an address some district information and
phone information if it's available and postal code information if it's available.
So some of these are null values.
But what we can do is go ahead and join these two tables that customer table and the address table say
what kind of a more complete table view of customer information.
So let's say I want maybe their first name or last name their e-mail Altes go ahead and then say their
address and phone and I want that from the customer table.
But notice like address and phone information that wasn't in the Customer table and the address table
so I have joined this.
So I was going to go ahead and do a simple inner join.
I say join our address or join address and then we're going to stay on and the column that links them
both.
Is this address underscore ID column.
So I'm going to say on customer that address ID equals
address Dot's address underscore ID.
Some might call in.
So it's going to make sure that works.
I just ran that.
So the first name the last name email address and the phone so looks like my simple join works.
Now I wouldn't want to have to keep writing this complex sequel career or save this complex SQL query
somewhere.
If I had to keep doing this sort of query on a day to day basis if for some reason this is a really
common query it would be nice to be able to save this table that gets returned as a view and that's
exactly what we can do to view and create new statements.
Second can say create new and let's call this customer info and then we're going to say as.
And then you have your giant selects queries statement.
So I'm going to go ahead and run them and you'll notice the query returns successfully if no result
.
That means that views been created.
So now what I can do is say selects all the columns from customer in underscore in-fill am now basically
that complex series query complex sequel query has been saved as the view.
Customer info and that's really just the main idea of the view.
So the view.
Keep in mind it's just this virtual table meaning it's not actually making a copy of all that data it's
just viewing it off of the other tables.
Based off your sequel query that complex query did earlier.
And that's really the main purpose of the view itself.
And now what I want to show you are two quick case statements are key clauses that go along with the
view or create view statements.
So one of them is alter view and rename to.
So the alter view allows you to just rename the view so I could say something like Alter view.
And then I'm going to put in customer underscore info and then I can say rename to and now I can rename
it to a different name for that.
So instead of saying customer info I can say something like customer master list or something like that
.
Run it.
You should get no results.
And now what I can do is say selects Asterix so all columns from that customer
master list.
And here we have our customer master list again.
So basically that just allows you to rename views again.
All you have to do is say alter view.
Then you just put in the name of view doesn't matter and then you say rename to and here you put your
new name of the view so that's it for renaming the view.
Just say alter view put in the name of your view and then rename it to some new name.
If you want to go ahead and remove an existing VM postgresql that's also really simple command.
You just say drop view.
Then we can go ahead and say customer.
It was customer master underscore list.
So if we go ahead and run that return successfully and that we'll go ahead and drop the view.
So again just a quick note removing a view that does not exist in the database will result in error
.
So you can do it just like dropping a table.
If I try running this again for instance it'll say customer masterlist doesn't exist.
So just like drop table.
I can use the if exists clause here to check first if it exists and then they'll give you a notice instead
of an error.
So just say Oh.
Do this on his list does not exist skipping.
All right.
So that's really it for the view basic concept that you just had to get from this was just the Create
view statements as.
And that's really all there is to as far as creating the view is just the nicer cleaner way to save
really complex queries as views.
Instead of having to retype or save that specific complex query.
OK thanks everyone and I will see you at the next lecture