Hello everyone and welcome to the sequel statement fundamentals section of the Course section is going
to focus on sequel syntax and what's really important about what you're going to learn here is that
the syntax in this section can be applied to any major type of sequel database.
So if you move on to work on like a sequel database or an Oracle database the sequel syntax you learn
throughout the section of the course and any time are going to be learning specific sequel's syntax
statements and queries you're going to be able to apply that knowledge to basically any major type of
sequel database.
So we're going to start with the basics and have challenges along the way to test your understanding
with all that being said.
Let's go ahead and get started