Hello everyone and welcome to the select statement lecture in this lecture we're going to start a more
formal presentation of the select syntax and then we're going to show some examples through a sequel
Ed. afterwards.
So a quick no.
A lot of times people prefer saying select clause instead of select statement in this section of the
course we're going to use the terms statement and clause interchangeably.
So just keep that in mind.
Either ones really correct to use throughout this course.
So going along one of the most common tests you're going to have to do when you're working on a sequel
database is to query data from tables by using the select statement and that select statement has many
clauses that you can combine it with to form really powerful queries so you can get really specific
information from your tables in your database.
So right now we're going to start off with the very basics and the basic form of a select statement
query data from a table looks something like this.
So if we look at this bottom line here that's the basic syntax of a select statement.
And these two lines are basically which are these two keywords selected from are pretty much going to
be in almost all your sequel queries.
And the syntax goes like this you say select and then you pass in a list of column names separated by
a comma for each column and then you're going to say from and the table name.
So you select the list of columns from the name of your table.
So again first specify that list of columns in the table from which you want to query data in the select
clause and you use a comma between each column.
In case you want to query data from multiple columns and if you want to query data from all of the columns
you can actually just use an asterisk as a shorthand for all columns and then second.
In that case the table named after the from keyword.
So we'll be using both those column notations and the Asterix notation throughout this course.
So something that you'll notice as you go along with this course the school language is actually case
insensitive.
It means that you can use the select on all uppercase or select in all lowercase and the effect is the
same.
By convention However we're going to use sequel keywords in uppercase to make the code easier to read
and stand that clearly.
So whenever you're using a sequel keyword I would always recommend writing in a per case because when
you come back to the code later it's going to be a lot easier to read.
And by convention pretty much all the sequel code you're going to come across is going to follow that
convention of putting sequel keywords in uppercase.
And one quick No it's usually not good practice to use an asterix in the select statement because you
can imagine that if you have a really large table with many columns the select statement of an asterix
is going to query all the data from the columns in your table which may not be necessary.
So usually in a real case where you trying to get a specific set of data you're not going to put an
asterix in to retrieve all the data.
However since we're working with small tables as example tables that we downloaded in the previous section
using an asterix is OK because the tables are small enough where it takes basically just a few milliseconds
to query all the data on a normal running computer.
However in a normal database server if you say select Asterix it's going to make your database work
server work a lot harder and it's also going to increase the traffic between that database server and
its applications.
And as a result it's going to slow down whatever application is dependent on that database.
Therefore we should usually specify the column names in the select clause whenever possible to get only
necessary data from a table.
So while we are going to be using the Asterix notation a lot throughout the course because there are
specific tables and example tables are small.
Keep in mind that you should only be really saying specific column names that you want to get back in
order to save time.
OK.
With that being said let's go ahead and see a couple of examples of the select statement in sequel.
I'm going to go ahead and jump to P.G. admin now.
OK so here I am at PGE admin.
If you're using a Mac all you have to do is just type it to your terminal.
Or excuse me or Spotlight search PGE admin.
It should auto complete and then you just click enter and this should open.
If you're using a Windows then just do a search for PGE admin and basically the same thing it should
pop up and it should open.
Looks like this.
So once you have this running you can go ahead and essentially double click here.
Has the red X on your post Chris sequel version and then it should connect to all your databases that
you created and we're going to do is go ahead and go to the DVD rental database that we created in the
previous section and the database that we restored.
So if you come to databases you'll get a list of all your databases.
I have a couple here but the one we're looking for is the one you made in the previous section with
all the DVD rental information.
And in this case mine is called DVD rental.
So go ahead and click on it and you should be able to click on schemas below it click public and you
should see that you have the tables here that we did in the previous section.
If you need any review on how to actually download and restore all the data in this table go ahead and
check out the lectures in the previous section where we go over that.
But for now what I want you to do is that in order to do a sequel query go ahead and click a DVD rental
and then she'd come here we see like a little magnifying glass with the word sequel in it and I'll say
execute arbitrary sequel queries.
Go ahead and click that and you'll get a window pop up that looks something like this.
And this is your sequel Ed. And this is what we're going to use in order to actually type in our sequel
syntax.
So it going to be really useful because basically no matter what operating system use as long as you're
using PGE atom in with the sequel editor it should look the same on any operating system so that's really
convenient socially for teaching purposes.
So now we're going to do is go ahead and type select statement.
So let's go and say select and I'll show you first how it Asterix works then go ahead and put an asterix
that's usually shift eight's usually above the eight number so I want to say select Asterix from is
the second keyword and then we're going to say the table name.
So let's go out and select a table.
What I'm going to do is go back to PGE Ottman.
Check out the table here.
And I see a list of tables.
Let's go ahead and play one of a few of these we'll say actor so selects Asterix from actor and the
way you end a sequel queery here is by putting a semicolon.
So I'm saying select Asterix from actor and that's meaning return all the columns from actor and let's
go ahead and execute the query here.
You can also press F5 if you're using a Windows machine in order to execute that query as a hockey.
All right.
Great.
So if you look down below we have our data output going to go ahead and expand that a bit.
So we see your data output and we since we set Asterix that means return all the columns from the actor
table.
So you can see we have an actor Id a first name last name and last update column.
So these are the column names in this first line and the line below it is the data type that exists
in that column.
So for example the actor ID is an integer data type so these are all integers.
The first name column is character vary and that basically stands for a string data type where you actually
have characters in it.
And this number in parentheses stands for the limit of how many characters can be in there.
And then if we see here on this last column this is a data type time stamp.
Don't worry too much about data types right now data types become a lot more important when you're dealing
of certain where statements or more importantly when you're actually creating the tables.
So we actually have a whole lecture on data types.
If you want you can explore it really at any time in the course.
It's over down in the creating and tables and databases section go to explore that if you want to learn
a little more about the data types.
Or you can just go throughout the course and reach it naturally.
So from now on I won't worry too much about the data types answer really just queering from the table
.
OK.
With that being said let's go ahead and explore a couple of more methods of using that select statement
basics so here.
Select Asterix which means going to select all the columns.
What I'm going to do now is select particular columns and in order to do this I take the column names
I'm going to say select.
Let's go ahead and get the first name and the last name of those actors and I say select first underscore
name and then say comma last underscore name.
So you just pasan basically a list here separated by a comma for every column.
Let's go ahead and run that.
And you notice now I just get the columns that I requested back.
OK.
So right now we're just getting every single row in that column that information later on we're going
to learn how to use where statements and other clauses and sequel in order to limit the amount of rows
we get back based on certain conditions that we won.
So if we want every actor whose name starts with P or something where we learn how to do that later
on but right now for this lecture all you need to know is the basics of using an asterix or column names
with the select and from statement.
So let's go ahead and do one final review of how to use this.
You again say select and go ahead and make those keywords capitalized.
Again you don't have to.
It'll still work if they're not capitalized but just by convention it's better to have it be capitalized
because easier to come back to read.
So we start with the keywords select.
Then you put in the column names.
So I remember a column name was actor Id.
So then you say from Again all caps because it's a key word and you actually notice what's nice about
the sequel editor is it.
It will highlight the keywords so they're a little bit of a shade of blue.
And then you say the table name.
And in this case the table name is actor.
And then you put a semi-colon it in the.
That's the end of your query.
So if we run that we'll have actor ideas a column and we'll overturn all the rules here.
OK.
That's really all there is.
The very basics of using a select statement and I will see you at the next lecture.
We're going to discuss even more ways to build off this basic select statement.
So again just select Asterix for all the columns or just a list of the column names separated by a comma
space from space the table name semi-colon.
OK thanks everyone.
I'll see you at the next lecture.