Hello everyone and welcome to another challenge.
And in this case we're going to be challenging you on learning how to use the select syntax for sequel
.
So in this challenge you're going to get a situation the actual challenge I want you to implement some
hints the challenge and then the solution all warn you when the hints and solution are coming up next
so that if you want to solve the problem on your own you can go ahead and pause the lecture and see
if you can solve it on your own.
So don't worry.
I'll warn you in hints and solutions are coming as far as the situation.
We have a database in the tables and now we want to send a promotional e-mail to our existing customers
.
So we're going to want is some information such as their e-mails and their names.
So the challenge is to use a select statement to grab the first and last names of every customer and
their email address.
Remember to click on the database and then select the arbitrary sequel query button in order to get
to the sequel editor.
Other than that.
Good luck.
Now you can go ahead and spazzes lecture if you want to try it out on your own.
Up next we'll go over some hints so I'll go ahead and wait for a second case you want to posit.
All right now I'm going to go over some hints so some hints are.
You'll want to use the customer table.
You'll also may want to use Select Asterix from customer semi colon in order to get an idea of what
columns use So remember you have to use that semi-colon in order to end your sequel's state.
So those are just a couple of hints.
Hopefully this general task shouldn't be too hard given what you just learned.
But up next is the full solution.
Saw it first second before going to the solution slide.
OK let's go ahead and go over the solution.
So the solution is just this.
You're going to say select first underscore name comma last underscore name comma email.
So from the customer table these three columns are the main columns I want you to get in order to send
out that promotional email.
Now you'll notice something here is I've written this on two separate lines.
I said select my column names and then from that table in the database and then I ended it off a semi-colon
so you can go ahead and write sequel queries in multiple lines and sequels and keep reading everything
as if it was written on one line until it runs into a semi colon.
So this is really nice for making your queries very readable in a lot of times you'll see people basically
for every keyword that shows up they'll start another line.
OK so that's it for the solution.
I hope you were able to solve it on your own first or at least gave it a really good shot.
Up next we're going to learn some more fundamentals for sequel's statements.
Thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next lecture.