Hello everyone and welcome to the lecture on select this thing.
So this lecture we're going to get an overview of how to use Select Distinct keyword.
It's going to be really useful for some common queries where you just want to remove duplicate.
So let's go and discuss what select distinct looks like in its syntax and then we'll go through an example
.
So in a table a column may contain duplicate values so you can imagine if you had a table full of dates
you may have duplicate dates and you just really want to grab the stinks dates or maybe have a list
of films and you just want to grab the stinko films etc. so that the stink keyboard can be used to return
only the stings or different values.
So let's go ahead and look at what the syntax for that would look like it's going to look like this
.
You'll say select space distinct and those are keywords so I put them in all caps.
Then the column names you want to select separated by comma and then the save from the table name.
So let's go ahead and try this on an actual example.
So I get to hop over to PGE Atman and then open up.
Sequel editor there.
OK everyone.
Now I'm at PGE admen three and I'm going to go out and select my DVD rental database and run a sequel
query on it.
So just as a reminder if I expand this and show the public the schemas etc. and then show the tables
here we can see the variety of tables I have.
And right now we're going to focus on the film table.
So let's go ahead and click the database execute arbitrary sequel queery And now we can run sequel queries
on this.
So let's start off by just saying select is Asterix which means select every column from film semi-colon
and in case you want a little shortcut and not have to click execute queer every time you can use EF
5 on your keyboard in order to execute that query.
Again that's just to type it out here for you.
That's EF 5 that's the hot cat clicking.
So I don't have to click execute queery every time.
Continuing on here we see that we have a film ID column a title column a description column some release
years language ID Rensil duration etc. and then some rental rates replacement costs and some more information
.
Now let's go ahead and learn how we can use distinct to grab some information that might be handy.
Let's say you wanted to know all the distinct years that films were released in your database.
So right now if we look at the number of rows our database has we scroll all the way down you'll notice
it has 1000 rows but you'll notice here at the very bottom we have a 2006 release year.
And as you scroll all the way up you also 2006 release here and now you're wondering is 2006 the only
release year is that if we looked at all the distinct release years as 2006 the only one.
So here's what you can do will say select
this.
And in this case we'll just select release underscore year as the column we want.
And now you'll see that it's returned all the distinct values that release your hat.
In this case it was just one year.
For whatever reason this database all the release years are from 2006.
So that's interesting something to keep in mind.
Let's go ahead and check out all the data one more time and again I know I mentioned that usually using
asterisks like this isn't good especially for a large database if you're calling everything.
Let's us this is a toy database for examples.
You want to worry about that right now.
Later on we'll show you how to just grab the first two columns for she rose I should say in case you
just want to call them names continue it on another interesting topic we might be interested in is the
rental rate so you can see we have a variety of rental rates such as for 99 99 cents to 99 etc..
And now I want to know what are a distinct rental rates we have for this rental DVDs store.
Well I'll say select listings pass in the column my wants rates and then go ahead and run this.
And so now I know that this DVDs store basically only has three rental rates.
It's either a 99 cent movie a 299 dollar movie rental rate or ifour $99 movie rental rate.
So you can see the power of select distinct statement just by itself.
Later on we'll see how we can combine the state with other sequel Syntec statements and then perform
really powerful queries to grab really specific information right and hopefully you can see just the
power of using Select Distinct on a column to grab really valuable information because if you didn't
have select distinct answering the question of well how many rental rates do you have.
Would it be a lot harder to do you'd only be able to select everything and then you have to manually
go through it.
Right.
So you'd have to basically sift through this thousand columns and try to find which ones are the uniques
and keep track of them.
But select the stings allows you to easily answer that question.
OK.
Go ahead and practice Select Distinct on a couple of other columns or some other tables if you want
.
But coming up next is a quick challenge to make sure you fully understand select listings.
Thanks everyone and I will see you at the next lecture