Hello everyone.
Welcome to the next challenge for you.
The Select Distinct challenge.
We're going to have an overview of the challenge.
So what situation is the actual challenge itself in context of the sequel syntax and then some hints
and solution.
And as always I will warn you in the hints and the solutions are coming.
So is the situation we want to know the types of ratings movies can get in the United States.
So for example P.G. 13 rated r etc..
And we want to know which ones we have in our database.
So your challenge is to use a Select Distinct statement to get the distinct rating types our films can
have in our database.
So for example you're going to use the select distinct statement in order to figure out do we have an
R rated movie in our database.
How could you use a select statement to answer that question.
So remember to click on the database.
So in this case that DVD rental database then select arbitrary secret query button to get to the sequel
editor.
That being said Best of luck you can continue watching for hints in the solution.
All right.
So go ahead and puzzle video.
Now if you want to do a funny Hintz but I'm going to go to the Hintz lecture or slide now.
So a couple of hints you'll want to use the film table to do this and you can use select Asterix from
films semi-colon to get an idea of what columns to use to actually find the name of that column.
All right so those are your hints and a solution is coming up next.
So go ahead and positivity now if you want to try it on your own before seeing the solution.
Ok so now let's go to the solution.
So the solutions actually quite simply want to say select the stinks rating.
So rating is the name of the column and it's from the film table so select distinct rating from film
.
So Michael.
And your sequel query.
OK hopefully you're able to figure that out on your own.
If not go ahead and review the Select Distinct lecture for a better background on how exactly to solve
the problem.
Thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next lecture