Hello everyone and welcome to the select where lecture in this lecture we're going to learn how to use
the select clause of the where statements.
So what are the most important topics for Sequel fundamentals is using Select with where the selection
is going to be a little longer than the previous ones.
We're going to cover a couple of things along of that where statement or WHERE clause.
So again in previous lectures you've already learned how to use the select statement to query data from
a table in a database.
Another question is What do you want to query just particular rows from a table matching some sort of
condition.
In this case you're going to need to use the where clause in the select statement.
So the basic syntax that the sort of statement looks like this you have a select keyword list of columns
you want to select and you say from then the table name then you have the keyword where you're going
to have some sort of condition or some conditions statement there and then you have a semi-colon to
end the entire query.
So we're going to discuss and this lecture is what are those conditions and how can we actually build
them.
So again that where clause appears right after the FROM clause of the select statement and the conditions
are used to filter the rows returned from the select statement and postgresql in particular provides
have various standard operators to construct those conditions and the conditions and operators we're
going to learn right now are pretty much applicable to any sequel engine.
So some of these basic operators you can probably already guess what they do based on what they look
like.
But there's also a description here on the right hand side.
And these are basic operators you can use along with select where statement.
Now we're basically going to cover all of these throughout this lecture through examples in the postgresql
sequel tables and databases.
Basically what we're going to do is use the operators on the left hand side in along with a select and
a where statement to only query particular rows from a table.
So let's go ahead and show some slides of a couple of examples and then we'll actually Diven open up
a sequel editor and explore all of these just a little more.
So imagine you want to get all the customers whose first names are Jamy so you can use the where clause
with the equal operator that equals sign as follows.
Here below you would say select last name comma first name.
So that's the last name column and the first name column from the customer table where then you have
some sort of conditional statement and this is our conditional statement we want that first name column
value to be equal to the string Jaymie when we define that string with single quotes and then we have
a semi-colon to end the entire query.
So that's one simple example of using the equals operator in order to only get back rows where the customer's
first name is Jamie.
So imagine you want to select the customer whose first name is Jamie and whose last name is rice.
Then you can use those logical operators that were at the bottom of that chart a n d and in order to
combine two conditions.
So if we go back real quick here we have the operators notice at the bottom two and that are or those
allow us to combine conditions using the other operators.
So let's go ahead and go forward again to we want this customer whose first name is Jamie and last name
is rice.
So we can say select last name comma first name.
And again it doesn't really matter what order we're actually selecting these columns and that's just
going to specify what order you want your data output to be in.
So we'll explore that when we see the examples.
So again we say select the columns you want from the customer table where the first name column value
is equal to Jamie.
And that's the keyword.
The last name column is equal to rice than a semi colons end.
And if those column values are strings or character varying strings you have to put those single quotes
in there as well around Jaymie and rice.
So imagine you want to know who paid the rental with amount is either let's say less than you or on
US dollar greater than eight U.S. dollars.
So you want to know who paid a rental value with an amount that was either less than one U.S. dollar
or greater than eight U.S. dollars.
Outside of that range you could use the following sort of statement here you could say selects let's
say Customer ID amounts payment they columns from the payment table where amount is less than or equal
to.
So that has a color operator one or the amount is greater than or equal to eight.
So here if we look we have these conditional operators that Lessner equal sign or that greater than
or equal to sign.
And then we have the numbers and then we have the logical operator or in between those two conditions
.
So here is less than equal to and then greater than 2 so let's go out and play around our database to
see couple of more examples and get some more practice.
So go ahead and open up P.G. admen and open up a sequel editor and let's so we can actually play some
more select where statements are going to go ahead and jump to P.G. admin and open up a sequel.
Ed. now.
OK so here we are P.G. admin.
When I'm going to go ahead and do is go to my databases expand it then select DVD rental and go up here
to execute an arbitrary sequel query and that should bring up this query editor.
So let's go ahead and start off with just learning how to use the select where statement and in order
to do that let's go in and explore a particular table from our database we'll call it the customer table
.
It's going to run that.
And so you notice here we get our data output after selecting every single column.
So now we're going to add a where statement to this in order to continue to use those comparison operators
to mess around with this and only query certain rows so let's say I want to get where else go ahead
and say where the first name is equal to.
Let's go ahead and say Jared semi colon.
Run that.
And so you notice now with the data output I only get all the columns where this is true.
And what's nice about these sort of select from where statements is I can't call for any calls back
.
So I can just get for instance the email column and get Gerrard's e-mail back.
So this column here that you're selecting doesn't actually have to be included in the WHERE statement
.
So you can select all the columns none of the columns some of the columns etc..
They don't actually have to match up with your WHERE statement here and your select statement here.
So hopefully that makes sense as far as the column you're selecting.
Let's go ahead and explore a couple more tables.
So Nel's go ahead and check out the payments table.
Run that.
So that's selecting all columns from the payment table.
Since I don't have any other conditions to return all the rows so it's going to filter this out by rows
using some of those comparison operators that we saw earlier.
So we're going to do now is go ahead and say we have where the amounts column value.
Let's go ahead and say where it's equal to seven dollars and ninety nine cents.
And since the amount column is just some numeric value we don't have to put this around quotes or anything
.
So it's going to run that.
And now we get the data output for where the amount was equal to seven ninety nine.
And if we scroll down here we'll notice that we have 621 rows returns if we didn't have that where statements
and we ran that and returned all the rows.
If you scroll down you'll notice we get over 14000 rows.
So that's the difference between using a selects and using a select where.
So let's just walk through all the operators so we just saw the equal operator.
Let's go ahead and explore a couple more.
We can say where the amount is greater than $5.
So that's how you would use that operator that returns everything that was greater than $5 the Kundera
thing that was less than $5 now would be everything that was less than $5.
You can see here the amounts are less than five.
And then you can start doing things like less than or equal to.
So for example if I say give me the amounts that are less than four ninety nine you'll notice here I
get a 499 amount over at the fourth row that if I actually run this now I don't have the 499 amount
because I'm only saying less than not less than or equal to.
So if I do want to retain those 499 values I can say less than or equal to.
So these operators basically behave as you would expect them to.
And now I can say I have a four ninety nine value here in the amount in the fourth row.
So again that's because I said the equal sign there instead of just a less than sign.
So I can say less than or equal to or I can say greater than or equal to and then I can also do not
equal in the way I can do NOT equal as an exclamation points equal sign and that will basically give
me all the values.
I just run that that are not equal to 499.
So that returns all the columns where the amount column was not equal to 499.
Then again I can actually ask for specific columns here so I can say Give me the amounts and maybe the
payment the column values run that will only return those two columns where this condition here is true
.
OK.
So those are the operators themselves.
Let's go ahead and add some logical operators.
So the logical operator and allows us to basically combine multiple conditions.
So let's say I want to get where rows were the amounts was 499 and rows were the amounts is equal to
let's say ninety nine semi-colons and that if you notice here I don't get any returns.
Now that makes sense because I'm using an AND statement here.
So the the amount column value can't be both for ninety nine and one ninety nine it can be one or the
other.
So that's where we have to use an OR statement here and now if I have an OR statement then I do get
the values that are either 499 or 1 99.
In order to use an NS amounts will have to go ahead and see some more different types of queries so
let's go out and make an example where we can use an AND operator in order to do this let's go ahead
and go back to the customer table.
So I must say selects all the columns from the customer table.
And so here we have the customer table.
So let's go ahead and explore how we can do this.
So let's go ahead and say give me these all the columns from the customer table where where the store
underscore ID is equal to 1.
And let's go ahead and say and first name.
Well we can also say an address id here so instead of using the first name that's going to use at or
the so say we're story is equal to 1 and the address underscore ID is greater than.
Let's go ahead and say five.
So if you go ahead and run that now we get results.
You'll notice all the story ideas here and the results in the data output are one to make sense.
Given our first condition and all the actors say these are greater than five.
So if you scroll to the right here under the address id column we should see everything being greater
than 5 and that's true there.
So that's how you can use the and operator.
So hopefully that makes sense as far as like when you can use and when you can use or so.
And you want both conditions to be true.
And it doesn't really make sense to use and in most cases on the same column because that column can't
have two specific values on that row.
If it's just a normal integer or string data type.
Now we can use or on the same column in order to selectively condition by the same column.
So I could say story the equal one or store or underscore the equal to two.
And if you notice now all the stories are really equal to one or two were to say and here this doesn't
make sense right because the store ID can't be one and two at the same time.
So in that case you don't get anything back.
So hopefully that clears up the use cases for or.
And so or makes sense for these same columns.
And it makes sense to use and when you have two different columns something like again an address id
to be let's say greater than 200 and you can also then add more things like greater than or equal to
two hundred etc. and that will keep filtering out the rows that you want.
So that's how you can use a Select where statement in order to build out further understanding of this
in the next century going to do is have a select where challenge and I want to challenge you to create
queries and I'll give you hints along the way if you need them in order to really build out your understanding
of how to use Select and where.
So let's go ahead and jump quickly to the slides just so you can get a quick overview of everything
we learned.
So as a quick review we learn how to combine a simple select from statement with a where clause in order
to filter out rows based on some sort of condition and comparison operators and those logical statements
and that or allow us to create some conditions in order to further select our queries.
So up next we're going to test your understanding of these and select and where with some challenges
.
OK.
Thanks everyone.
And best of luck on the challenges which I will see you in the next lecture for