Hello everyone and welcome to the challenge lecture for the select where statements.
So in this lecture we're going to get a quick update on what the challenge structure is going to look
like for the rest of the course and then we'll get the challenges and the solutions that challenge.
There's going to be three challenges for the section.
So quick notice.
We now know enough to begin answering challenge questions posed as business tests.
So for example the challenge questions are going to be posed in the form of something like how many
customers have the first named Jared versus previously we were being really explicit something like
use the select where statement to find Jared in the first name column of the customer table.
From now on we're actually going to focus more on business tasks or just general business questions
for example that how many customers have the first name Jared versus explicitly telling you what to
do in sequel.
The reasons for that is in a real world you're not going to be told what sequel commands to use or it's
going to be told a business question.
So that's what we're going to move towards that.
And also as we go later on throughout the course there's going to be multiple ways to solve the question
or the challenge.
So we're not going explicitly say how to use your sequel query skills you're going to able to choose
the way you like the best.
OK.
So let's go in and see our first challenge and an example of this.
So the first select where challenge is this a customer forgot their wallet at our store and we need
to track down their e-mail to inform them.
So what I want you to know or give me is what's the email for the customer with the name Nancy Thomas
.
OK.
So again the challenge is what's the email for the customer with the name Nancy Thomas All right.
Coming up next is the solution to this query.
So go ahead and pause the video now.
You don't want to see his solution yet.
OK here's a solution.
So a solution is to select the e-mail columns to select e-mail from customer table where first name
is equal to Nancy and the last name is equal to Thomas.
A quick note here.
There's only one person of the first name Nancy.
You could have also said where a first name equals Nancy.
OK.
So that should have given you the e-mail for Nancy Thomas.
Here's the next challenge.
Next challenge is a customer wants to know the movie outlaw Hinkey is about.
So could you give them a description for the movie outlaw Hinkey.
Again your challenge is to give them the description for the movie outlaw Hank.
OK.
So up next is the solution for this.
So go get impassivity now.
All right.
Now I'm going to go to the solution.
So the solution is to select that description column from the film table or the title is equal to outlaw
hanky.
Remember to put that semi-colon in see.
And the query.
OK our last challenge is this.
So the situation is a customer's late on their movie return.
And I know their address is 2 5 9 iPods right.
That's I.
P O H drive.
I want to call them to let them know that they're late on their movie return.
So can you give me the phone number for the person who lives that 4:58 9 I drive.
OK.
So up next is the solution to this.
So here's a solution you had a select the phone call from the address table.
So I didn't explicitly tell you what table you may have looked at the customer table first but the easiest
way to it is select phone from address where address is equal to 2 5 9 iPod drive.
OK.
So that's it for the challenges.
Great job.
And now we're going to learn some more tools and some more queries statements we can use with select
and where.
Thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next lecture