Hello everyone and welcome to the Count function lecture this lecture we're going to learn about the
Count function how to use it.
We'll see some general syntax examples and then we'll actually do some real examples in action for example
database.
So the count function returns the number of input rows that match a specific condition of query.
So basically just counts where the condition was true.
So an example syntax may look something like this select count Asterix and notice the parentheses there
from table.
So let's go ahead and break down this statement a little further that count Asterix function returns
a number of rows returned by a select clause.
So that would just be the number of row count that we've seen earlier.
When you apply that count to the entire table postscripts sequel actually scans the table sequentially
.
You can also specify a specific column count for readability.
So for example you could say select count and then a specific column from the table.
So similar to that count Asterix function that count column function returns number of rows returned
by that select clause.
So it just returns a single number of rows.
However keep in mind that that count column method does not consider null values in the column and we'll
see that later on.
OK.
Quick final note.
We can actually use the count of dustings.
For example you can say select count this stinks column from table and that will count the number of
distinct rows for that particular column.
Let's go ahead and see some examples so we can flesh out this idea a little further.
I'm going to go ahead and chop to PGA admen now.
OK.
So here I am at PG admin.
Let's go ahead and select our DVD rental database and click on the X Q. arbitrary sequel queries and
just couldn't execute some stuff.
So let's say I want to just to get the number of transactions in the payment table.
So let's say I wanted to do this the old fashioned way I could say select everything from payment tables
to my colon and I press 5 there.
And what I would have to do without using the count function is grab every thing and then scroll all
the way down and then note the actual count which is one.
Fourteen thousand five hundred ninety six.
But now if I just say counts the number of rows from payments which is basically just counting the number
of transactions from the payment table.
So I run this guy or this query.
Notice I now I just get a much faster response time.
So if we scroll down here we can see 11 milliseconds and now I get the same count.
Fourteen thousand five hundred ninety six.
So you can see this is a lot nicer and it's also a lot more readable.
OK.
So let's see an example of using it with distinct.
So let's get the number of amounts that a customer pays.
So for example I can say selects which is go ahead and see everything.
One more time.
Run that query.
So notice I have various amount types.
I have seven ninety nine one ninety nine 299.
Let's say I just wanted to know the count of the distinct amount types.
So how many distinct types in the amount column are there.
So then I would say counts and then I specify distinct amounts parentheses and so I'm going to count
the distinct amount types in that amount row.
So if I run that I get 19 distinct types in the amount row and that's the total count there.
And something I also want you to know is that you can go ahead and use parentheses which did the Stintz
function as well.
So if I had another set of parentheses here PGE admin will go ahead and highlight that syntax for me
to show me which princes match up with which parentheses.
But just putting a cursor next to them.
But just for readability you may prefer to write it out with two sets parentheses here.
Now if I go ahead and run that again we get the same results.
All right.
So that's just the basics of using count along with dustings count in general.
We're going to revisit count a lot.
It's going to be especially useful when we learn about group by clauses.
But right now we can go ahead.
We won't have a challenge specifically on count but we rule we will be revisiting counts in all the
challenges from now on.
So there's not going to be a specific challenge for count but you'll definitely see it pop up again
and again.
So keep it in mind as you go on through future challenges.
OK thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next lecture.