Hello everyone and welcome to the limit statement lecture.
So it's going to be a very quick lecture just to introduce the limits sequel query concept.
So limit allows you to limit the number of rows you get back after a query.
It's really useful when you want to get all the columns but not all the rows.
So usually pretty much always goes at the end of a query.
Best way to show this is just through a couple of quick examples.
So let's go ahead and jump over to the Peachi admin so we can see some examples of this.
OK so here I am at PGE admin what I'm going to do is just go ahead and select the DVD rental database
and then execute some arbitrary sequent queries.
So to show you a good use case for limit imagine you wanted to figure out what all the columns in for
example the customer table was.
You can say select Asterix from customer.
So my colon run this.
Now if you're doing a really large database which are table or data set which is what you're usually
going to be doing in this case is reasoning and sample data set.
It's only about 600 rows.
Five hundred ninety nine.
So it's not a big deal currently to return all of these rows but usually it is going to be a big deal
.
So in that case what you can do is go ahead and add limits at the very end of your query and then you
enter a number signifying how many rows you want back.
So in this case I'll say limit 5.
And if I go ahead and run that query number.
EF 5 is the key or the hot key for running a query instead of having to click here execute query.
And so now I've limited that to just five rows and it returns the first five rows for that query.
So there's two really good use cases for this one which will learn about later is when you order or
use ORDER BY.
So you can just grab like the top five or the first one when you order stuff and we'll learn about ORDER
BY in the next lecture.
And the other great use case for this is when you just want to figure out what all the columns were
for that particular table.
You can just say limit 5.
That way you return everything as far as the columns you're not returning the entire database so it
doesn't take a whole long time to execute a query.
So for example just limit one goes ahead and returns you this.
So again it's a pretty basic use case.
Just limit your keyword goes at the end.
So if you have other stuff go.
You would just go ahead and fill it in here.
So select a certain column from customer maybe have Sunwear statements etc..
And then at the very end of all these statements you just say limit and it limits your response to just
how many rows you specify.
OK.
There's that challenge for this because it's a pretty simple concept.
Again at the end of your query you can just say limit and then the number of rows you want back semi-colon
.
OK thanks everyone.
And then the next lecture we're going to learn about.
ORDER BY.
Thanks and I'll see you at the next lecture