Hello everyone and welcome to the ORDER BY statements lecture.
When you queried data from a table post Chris sequel returns the rows in the order that they were inserted
into the table.
If you want to sort the resulting set you can use the ORDER BY clause in conjunction with the select
statement.
So the ORDER BY clause allows you to sort the rows returned from the select statement in either ascending
or descending order based on the criteria specified so that would be a particular column you want to
order the data by.
So the following is going to illustrate the syntax of that select statement.
You'll say selects either columns that you want.
So again select the columns that you want from the table that you want and then you're going to see
Order By then the column name you want to order by and you're going to know it's either an ascending
order or descending order.
So this slash here is just to note the various options here so you'll either say order by the column
name and then ASC for ascending order or DSC for descending order.
I will see examples of this later on.
So again you specify the column that you want to sorts in the order by clause and if you want to sort
the resulting set by multiple columns you use a comma to separate between two columns.
I will show examples of that as well.
So you don't just have to order by one particular column.
You can order by multiple columns and then again you use A.S.C. to sort the resulting set in ascending
order and dsc to sort the resulting set in descending order.
If you leave it blank the order by clause will use A.S.C. by default.
So just keep that in mind.
OK with that being said lets go ahead and jump to OPG admin and code out some examples with sequel.
Hello everyone.
Now we're at PGE admin so I'm going to go ahead and do this select the DVD rental database and then
execute arbitrary sequel queries on that database.
OK so here are sequel Ed..
So let's go ahead and practice some basic order by examples.
So let's go to take a quick look at the customer table.
I'm gonna say selects Strix.
Everything from the customer table member I got to say from customer there.
So select everything from customer and let's go ahead and run that.
OK so here is a customer table.
Now imagine I wanted to sort a query and just get the first names and the last names sorted by the first
name in ascending order.
How would I do that.
So I just want the first names and last names so I'm going to go in and change this Asterix to those
columns.
I'll say first underscore name comma last underscore name some selecting the first name of the last
name from customer and then what I'm going to say is order by and then the column I want to order by
in this case I want to order by first name and I'm going to clarify that I want to order an ascending
order a se.
So if I run that 5 here I have in alphabetical order the results for the first names sorted out that
order.
So you can see we start off with the A's.
Aaron Adam Adrian if we screw all the way down we'll get to the last one which is Zackery Z.
So a through Z it's ordered in ascending order.
Go ahead and delete a C here and just run it like this and execute that.
You'll notice I get the same results and that's because remember the default for ordered by is A.S.C.
.
So you don't get any difference whether you put A.S.C. or you don't use A.S.C..
However I wanted that same result in descending order.
I would use DSC So if I run that query noticed now I start with Zachery I go all the way down to the
A's and outs Z through a.
OK.
So let's do one more basic example here.
Let's say I want to sort the customers my last name in descending order I would use the descending orders
but I would also change the column.
I want to order by two last name so I'm going to say select first name comma last name from customer
order by the last name in descending order around that.
Now I have the last names here young and etc..
In the standing order all the way.
I all the way down I should get some A's for last names so add Avni Adam Adams etc..
Great.
So let's say I wanted to sort the customers by first name in the ascending order first and then sort
the sorted results by the last name in this in order to produce the final result set.
So let me show you what I mean by that.
Imagine here that I say select first name last name from customer and an a.a group or.
Scuse me.
Order by first underscore name ascending order and I'm going to put a comma because I'm going to order
by multiple columns so I get a first order by the first name in ascending order.
And then ongoing to sort by the last name call them in descending order and you can think of this as
basically calling an order on the results of this query.
So use a comma to separate the columns you're ordering by and then you're going to say order by first
name first in ascending order and then whatever the results of that is I want you to order it by last
name in descending order that will produce the final result set.
So me going to show you what this looks like.
OK.
So we have our ordering now.
And basically what's going to happen is if the first name was the same anywhere than the last name ordering
is going to take into effect.
So it's going to scroll down a bit and look for some names some first names that were the same.
And since I'm familiar with this dataset I know that there's going to be two people called Kelly.
So if you scroll down to the k's maybe see the F G H I J K so scroll down a little more until we get
to the name Kelly for the first name.
So here we have now.
If you go to row 327 and 328 we have Kelleys So there's two Kelleys here.
So we sorted the first name column in ascending order and then we sorted the last name column in descending
orders.
That means if you had two people the first first name with the same first name the last name column
is gonna be sorted in descending order.
So if we look at this here Torres's first instead of not.
So if we go ahead and run this with ascending order then we'll see that not because first and Tor's
become second.
So is kind of a really basic example but it's important to show that you can sort order by multiple
columns.
So go into that one more time execute the query.
And if we go to that Roche was about 327 and 328 ish for Kelly.
So now we notice as we said both first name ascending and last name ascending for the Kelly then K becomes
first this is a through Z and Torah's becomes second.
So that's just an example of ordering by multiple columns.
OK.
One more thing I wanted to let you know is that postscripts sequel actually allows you to sort an order
by columns even if they're not selected.
So give an example of this.
Go ahead and show what the entire
table looks like.
Just say select all from customer leave that and run it.
So let's say I wanted to sort by the for example email address.
So in postscripts sequel I could say actually let's say I want to sort by the last name to be a more
obvious example a sort by the last name but only show the first name so I'll say first name.
So select the first name from customer order space by last name semi-colon in front that here you have
the list of first names but are ordered by the last name.
So this is nice.
I can order certain requests or columns even if I don't want that column in my final results.
Now this is allowed in postscripts sequel other and say sequel such as my sequel or Oracle sequel database's
may not allow you to do this.
So keep that in mind.
So most standard sequel queries will only allow you to sort rows based on the columns that appear in
the select clause.
So post gres sequel has the ability to sort resultset spaced on columns that do not appear in the selection
list.
So here I select that first name but I ordered by last name which didn't appear in the selection list
here.
Other sequel engines will not allow you to do that.
You'll have to be forced to select the column if you want to order by it.
So just keep that in mind.
Usually it's good practice to follow the most basic sequel queries that will transition from one database
to another.
So I would recommend that you always select the column if you're going to order by it.
So this should really look like this.
Since this is going to be the most easily translated from database to database.
OK with that being said.
Up next are going to be a few challenges that will test your knowledge of order by and will also test
your knowledge of how you can use limits with the order by statement.
OK so thanks everyone and I will see you at that next lecture.