Hello everyone and welcome to the challenge lecture for the ORDER BY statement.
So in this lecture you'll receive the challenge task and then in the next slide you'll get some hints
on how to solve it in the next slide you get the solution and I'll give you fair warning before we get
to the hints or solution slides for the challenge task.
OK.
Your first challenge is to get the customer ID numbers for the top 10 highest payment amounts.
Again just get the customer ID numbers for the top 10 highest payment amounts.
You may have to do some exploring to figure out what table is right for that sequel query.
All right.
So go ahead impassivity now.
Coming up next is the hints for this challenge.
Moving on to the hints so hints you'll need to use the payments table and you also need to use order
buy in limit together to solve this.
And remember you can use A.S.C. or DGSE to get the desired results of YOUR ORDER BY statement so either
ascending or descending.
Just keep that in mind.
And coming up next is the solution to the challenge to go to impassivity enough you don't want to see
the solution yet.
OK moving on to the solution.
So the solution looks something like this.
I said select customer id column and the Amount column from the payment table order by the amount in
descending order and limit 10.
If you just said ORDER BY amounts you would have gone in the wrong order in order to get the highest
payments you had to say descending order and limit 10 to only get the top 10 results.
And notice here I said customer id an amount column requested even though post-career sequel doesn't
actually require you to say the amount column.
If you're going to say ORDER BY amount you could have just said customer ID.
It's good practice to include the column name that you're ordering by.
So just keep that in mind.
That way the sequel syntax can be moved from any sort of sequel engine like Oracle sequel or my sequel
etc..
OK moving on to the next challenge the next challenge.
I want you to get the titles of the movies with film IDs 1 through 5 so just get the titles of the movies
with the film IDs 1 through 5.
So one two three four five.
OK.
Coming up next are the hits for this challenge to go in a positive if you don't want see the hints you're
living on.
OK the hints are you going to want to use the film table.
And again you'll need to use the order by and limit statements.
And again remember you can use a C or D A C to get desired results.
OK moving on to the solutions for this challenge.
The solution is select film Id title release year from film order by film.
Limit 5.
So again you actually didn't have to specify which columns you wanted since I just wanted the film Id
You didn't have to.
Well since I just wanted the title really you didn't have to actually call for release year but I just
did that to show a couple more columns.
Really all you had to say was select title from fill order by film Id.
I just put a few more columns in there so the query looks a little more fleshed out.
Again it's good practice to always include the column filt mighty that you're ordering by.
In this case it's film Id really was not an actual necessary column.
I just put that in there you should just see 2006 for all of them.
OK with that being said.
Great job everybody.
Let's go ahead and learn some more and I will see you in the next lecture.
Thanks everyone