Hello everyone and welcome to the between statement lecture.
So just a quick note in the next few lectures we're going to be discussing the between in and like statements
and you're not going to get challenges until we discuss all three of those so just keep that in mind
.
So after this lecture I will discuss it.
And after that lecture will discuss like.
And then you'll get some challenges.
OK.
So stuck with the between statement first so we can use the between operator to match a value against
a range of values.
So for example a general syntax for this is going to be some value between low and high semi colon.
So if the value is greater than or equal to the low value and less than or equal to the high value the
expression returns true or vice versa.
And we can rewrite the between operator by using the greater than or equal to or less than or equal
to operators as the following statement value greater than or equal to low in value less than or equal
to high.
So if we go back with the between low and high is basically doing the between statement it's just a
nice way of writing this statement out.
If you have some value which is basically a column right so some value column greater than or equal
to low and some value call of greater or less than or equal to high.
So for example you could say the payments column.
So you could say if we go back here.
Give me a payment that is between two ninety nine and 399 and that would return where that's true.
And that's just another way of writing this like a where statement where payment was greater than or
equal to 299 and payment was less nickel to 399.
So this basically a nice way to not have to write this over and over again you can just choose a between
statement and it makes it a little more readable.
So if you want to check if a value is out of a range we can ease the not between operator as follows
.
You can say some value column is not between low and high.
So that's basically another way of rewriting this you can save value less than low or value greater
than a high.
This is the same thing as the not between operator told doing.
So let's go ahead and take a look at some real examples on our sample database to get a better idea
of how to use between and not between.
OK.
So I going to go ahead and jump to the sequel database and P.G. adamant.
OK here you are at PGE admen.
Let's go ahead and click on the DVD rental database and execute some sequel queries.
And here we are at the sequel editor.
So imagine you wanted to selects payments ID's and payment amounts that were between $8 and $9.
So let's go ahead and show you an example say selects.
In this case we'll start off by just selecting everything from the payment table and we'll limit it
to five rows just so he can get a reminder of what the payment table looks like.
So if you run that click in a five run that I have the payment I.D. the customer I.D. the staff I.D.
the rental I.D. and then the amounts metric here.
So that amount column and then the time stamp.
So what I want to know.
Let's say I just want to get the customer ID column and the amount column back for payments that were
in between eight and nine dollars.
How would I do that.
So I'm going to say select the customer id call them and the amounts call them from the payment table
and then I'm going to say well where the amount is between eight and nine dollars.
OK.
So let's go ahead and see if that works.
And it looks like it did.
So if we look at this now we have all the columns are all the rows I should say where the amount was
between $89 and this case is either $8 to 99 cents or eight dollars in 97 cents.
All right.
So that's basically a nicer way of writing out this where amount statement without having to write an
all those comparison operators that greater then are less than equal to cetera and let's say I wanted
to get any payment whose amount is not in the range of 89 what I could do is say something like this
just not between 89.
So this is going to return all the rows that we didn't get back.
So if I run this now I have all the rows where the payment is not between eight and nine dollars.
So anything 799 and below or $9 and above.
OK.
So you can notice that this is a lot more readable than using a bunch of comparison operators.
And it's also a lot easier to write.
All right.
One last example.
Let's say I want to check a value against some ranges of dates.
What I can do is something like this.
Let's go ahead and just check out what the date column looks like some going to look ahead and say selects
payments under underscore dates.
Column from payments and I'm just going to say
limit 5 so we don't call everything back.
So this is what her payment date looks like as far as the column and we'll discuss how to deal with
date types in a lot more detail later on.
But right now I just want to show you is that you can actually use a basic literal date string format
to query based off the dates and that format is just going to be the year the month and the date in
dashes So it's going to be what we see here.
You have a four digit year dash a two digit month dash a two digit dates and you don't have to worry
right now about this entire time stamp without the time zone.
And again we'll discuss how to deal with dates and time stamps in much more detail later on.
Right now we'll just keep it simple.
So let's say I want to get
payments in amounts so I'll say amounts.
Comma payment dates from payments that occurred between let's say 2007 February 7th and 2007 February
15th.
So how would I do that.
It would look something like this I would say select the amount and payment date column from payments
and then I'm going to say where the payments underscore date is between.
And here I can actually just Taipan strings going to say a single quote They're going to put in the
year and we said February 7th.
So notice how I say my four digit year number dash two digits for the month.
Just for the dates.
And I'm also going to say Ann's
2007.
And I think we said the 15th so February 15th here and then semi colons.
And that's.
So it's going to run that check worked.
And there you have it.
Now we have all the payments that occurred between those two dates.
So apparently it looks like they all occurred on the 14th.
So that's it's a..
All right.
So just a quick overview what we learned in this quick lecture was how do you choose between and not
between.
So again if I want to say not between those two dates and run that will give me all the occurrences
that didn't occur between those two dates which would have just been blocking out everything that occurred
on the 14th.
OK.
Again we'll learn how to deal with time stamps in much more detail later on.
But here's one way you could do it.
You can just pass in a string that looks like this.
All right in the next lecture We'll discuss the in statements and then the lecture after that we'll
discuss the like statement and then we'll be able to build off some more complicated challenges for
you to solve.
All right.
Thanks everyone.
Go ahead and review the lecture in case you want to learn a little more about between and not between
.
And Casey Nira Radia he didn't get a good understanding the first time around.
But really what I would encourage you to do is just go ahead and play around the tables right now.
So just to make sure you understand how to use between and not between.
So go ahead and mess around with some of the other tables like customer et cetera and mess around with
between and not between just to make sure you have a full understanding.
OK.
Thanks everyone and I'll see at the next lecture