Hello everyone and welcome to the in statement lecture in this lecture we're going to learn about the
in statement and how to use it and we also get a very brief introduction to something known as a sub
query well-discussed so queries in much more detail later on.
But right now we'll just learn about them as a brief introduction where we're learning about the end
statements.
So what is the in statements you can use the in operator with the WHERE clause to check if a value matches
any value in a list of values.
So the syntax of an operator looks like this.
You say value that would be the column you're looking for.
So that column value in and then you have parentheses and a list of values.
So the expression returns true to value matches and the value of the list value one value 2 etc. and
the list of values is not limit to a list of numbers or strings but also the result of a set of select
statements.
And so this would actually be a sub query.
You could say value in and and you print the CS.
You actually have a sub query.
So select value from table name will go over some queries in much more detail later on.
But I want you to be aware of it in case you're looking at statements on your own somewhere else you
may see this show up just like between.
You can use the not operator to adjust and in statement so you can say something like.
Not in the list of values but let's go ahead and see some use case examples so you can get a better
idea of how to actually use that in his statements.
OK.
Go ahead and jump to Peachi Adam now.
OK so here we are at Peachi admin I'm going to go ahead and click DVD rental and then select execute
arbitrary series query or sequel queries sorry and get to the sequel editor.
OK.
So let's go ahead and review are in.
OPERATOR And how do you use that in statements.
So I'm going to go ahead and mess around with the rental table.
So let's just go ahead and check out what the rental table looks like and to say select everything from
rental and then I'm going to say limits just once we can just we can see what columns you have available
to us.
So we have the rental I.D. the rental dates inventory ID customer id return date step ID and then the
last update.
So suppose I want to know the rental information of a customer ID 1 and 2 so I could use the in operator
as follows.
I could do something like this.
I would say let's just do a couple of columns Hirose selects customer id call them so select the rental
Id call them.
And finally the return they call them.
So I'm selecting those three columns from rental and then this is where we're going to use the inside
operator or in statements.
I don't want to only get rental information for customer IDs 1 and 2.
Can I do that.
I can say where customer ID.
Basically the value column in and in print CS I'll start passing in the list of values I want and notice
the sequel.
Ed. actually highlights your list.
Here are sin tax purposes so you can see a highlighted.
Once I have finished my list so our customer I.D. is in one and two.
And let's go ahead and do an order by just to add on to this or say order by return dates descending
so we can start to flush out what a real SQL query would actually look like when we add a lot of moving
parts to it and let's go ahead and run this.
So what we get out.
OK.
So here we have Frenzel information for customer IDs where their customer is either in one or two of
that rental ID.
So that idea that specific renting transaction and then the return date in descending order.
All right.
So let's say I wanted to get everything that was not customer 1 or 2.
I couldn't say not in one 2 then run that and I'll get everything else that wasn't there.
You know this is actually quite a few rows so just keep that in mind and let's go ahead and just show
one more example of in here.
So I could say let's say maybe I'm looking for a couple of IDS like 7 13 and 10.
So if I run that now I get 7 or 13 and 10.
So this really nice because it allows you to search for specific row values or column values I should
say where the column he calls a particular value but you can now do it in a way that you don't have
to be in sequential order.
So the between statements and those comparison operators which is greater than or equal or less than
or equal to etc. Those usually had a deal some sort of range like between 1 and 5 for less than 10 etc.
.
Now I can actually just put a list of specific values using the in statement.
So that's going to be really convenient.
And so what I can actually think of this as is basically a series of or statements.
So I'm basically saying this and it's just a cleaner way of writing this so let's say I'm saying we're
customary in seven 13 10 that list this exact same thing as if I was just writing several equal statements
.
If I was saying or customary the equal seven or customer id equal 13 or customer id equal 10.
So that's actually the same thing as that in statement.
So remember the between statement when we're showing various ways of rewriting them with comparison
operators here if I run this this is actually the exact same thing of just using an in state and off
the list.
So you'll notice that use in statement is a lot nicer.
So the operator is shorter and more readable than a query that uses a bunch of or statements like this
.
And what's actually really nice is that postscripts sequel will execute the query with the in operator
Much faster than the same kuri.
That is a list of or operations like this.
So if you ever find yourself doing something like that you should really be thinking about using an
in statement for both readability readability and speed.
So this should just be in and then the list of values so let's just say one two three.
Run that.
And here we have customer IDs that are equal to one two or three.
OK let's just go ahead and do one more example.
Let's go ahead and check up the payment table see finger.
Any good data from there saw sullenness select everything from payments.
What say limit one.
Go ahead and run that.
So here you have customer id staff ID rental ID an amount.
So let's go out and say select all the columns from payments where the amounts is in.
And let's go ahead and say seven ninety nine and also eight ninety nine.
Let's go ahead and run that.
So now I have all the rental values where the amount was either 7 9 9 or 8 9 9.
And you notice again this is a lot more readable than having a bunch of or statements with the equal
clauses there.
And it also runs a lot faster.
So great use cases here for N and we'll see them a lot more throughout our challenges and the rest of
the SQL queries as we combine all these little tools we're learning to build out really nice strong
powerful queries.
Okay thanks everyone and I will see you at the next lecture or we're going to be discussing the like
operator.
Thanks and I'll see you there.