Hello everyone and welcome to the like statements lecture this lecture we're going to learn about the
like statements.
We'll get an overview of how to use it and then we'll also see some examples in the PGE admin of the
SQL query.
OK so suppose the store manager asks you to find the customer and he doesn't actually remember the exact
name.
He just remembers that the customer's first name begins of something like J E N so it could be Jenny
.
Jennifer doesn't really remember.
So how can you find that exact customer.
That store manager is asking for one way to do it would be to find the customer in the Customer table
by looking at that first name column.
Maybe you sort it alphabetically and then see if there's any value that begins with J E N.
So that would actually be really tedious because there are so many rows in that customer table you know
scroll down get to the J section the net the J E etc..
So there's a better way to do this and it's using the like statement and something known as pattern
matching.
So fortunately you can use this like operator and postgresql sequel and most other sequel engines also
support this like statements operator to use the following query.
So you would say select the columns you want from the table you want.
So first thing last then columns from customer table where the columns first name is like.
And then you kind of have some special characters here.
You have a string and you put in J E and in a percentage sign.
And that basically is going to start some pattern matching where it's going to be anything that starts
with J E N and any characters after that.
So to go into this and a little more detail notice that that where clause contains that special expression
.
So the first name that column the like operator in the string that contains a percent sign or a percent
character and that's referred to as a pattern.
So the query returns rows whose values in the first name column begin with Jan and may be followed by
any sequence of characters.
So that technique is called pattern matching.
So again with that percent sign does we go ahead and go back to the actual query here.
It says OK find me any values where the first name column the value in the first name column is like
J E and percentage sign meaning it starts of J E N and any characters after that.
So anything like Jennifer a Jenny I don't know Jeremiah whatever could be returned here.
So that technique again is known as pattern matching.
So you can construct the pattern by combining a string with wildcard characters and that's another term
in a more common sequel term for these sort of percent signs and underscores.
So those are known as wildcard characters because wildcard basically means you can put in anything you
want after that and you can use the like or not like operator to find the matches.
So use that percent sign for matching any sequence of characters and you can use an underscore for matching
any single character.
So let's go out and see some examples to improve our understanding of how to use these wildcard characters
or pattern matching along the like statements.
So I'm going to go ahead now and hop over to PGE adamant to do some queries.
OK so here we are at PGE admen.
Go ahead and click on DVD rental and select execute arbitrary sequel.
So I can begin to type in some sequel.
Wanting to do just go ahead and do that.
First example we're talking about.
So the store manager just remembers that the name starts with J E N I say selects first name column
comma last name column from the customer table where we'll say first underscore a name like that special
key word.
And this is where we're going to put in those wild cards or special operators for pattern matching.
So he put in the string new wants J E J E N and then we have the percent sign which is the wildcard
and then a semi-colon.
So that basically means return anything that starts with J E N and any number of characters after that
.
So if you go ahead and run that we get back.
Jennifer Jenny of IEEE and Jenny ending of a Y.
OK.
So that's what we can use that in the most basic example.
Well let's go ahead and see some more examples.
So that wildcard character can actually also go at the beginning.
So we can ask though in the beginning.
So let me show you an example that let's say we just remembered that the name ended in a Y we could
say.
Percent sign Y.
And what that means is any number of characters so that percent cite wild card means any number of characters
and the ending with a Y.
So in this case we should get all names for Y.
And here they are.
So we have Mary Dorothy Nancy beti etc. and actually quite a few up to 87 were returned their so you
can now use percent signs as wildcard operators to get Rose that either begin or end with certain characters
and you can actually use them in the middle.
So in conjunction.
So for example let's say you wanted to figure out any names that had e are in them somewhere in the
name.
You could actually do something like this.
You could say we're first name is like percent sign.
Our percent sign.
And that's going to return any names that have e are somewhere in the name.
So any carrot any number of wild card characters before any number of wild card characters after it
.
So if you go ahead and run that now we get any name that had e are somewhere in the name.
So we have Jennifer.
That's at the end of the name Kimberly that's in the middle the name Catherine in the middle name etc.
.
So what what's actually happening here let's break it down.
Sequel is saying grab me the first name and the last name column from the customer table or the value
in the first name column is like.
Percent sign.
E.R percent sign with a string.
So they're single quotes there.
So it's that saying is any number of characters 0 through whatever e are and then percent sign any number
of characters or through whatever.
So it doesn't matter if it shows up in the beginning at the end or somewhere in the middle.
It's going to return where the first name column is equal to those values.
So that's going to be really useful for us later on.
Now we also discussed another wildcard operate operator and that was the underscore and with the underscore
allows us to do is match for a single character.
So again the percent sign is going to match any sequence of characters 0 through infinity characters
and underscore is going to match for any single character.
So let's go ahead and check that out.
So let's say if select first name underscore last name from customer first name is like I'm going to
edit this.
I'll say underscore h e r.
Percent sign single quote semi-colon.
And if I run that we can take a look at what's happening here.
So you're telling sequel now it's instead of any sequence of characters every underscore just counts
for a single character.
So basically now here we're only giving sequel the option of saying OK replace the underscore with any
single character as a wildcard and then H.
R. and then percent science so any number of characters after that.
So if we look at the results here we get first name C as a single character H.
Percent sign.
T g is a single character.
Ichy are present sign as single character etc. and any number of characters can come after that.
H e r string of characters.
Let's go ahead and take some look at.
Not like examples.
So just to quickly show you how to use not like let's say we wanted anything that was not like jeon
.
So I could say where not like a single quote here.
J E N percentage sign single quotes semi-colons.
If I run that no I get basically the exact opposite.
If I were to say just like J and percent sign.
OK.
And there are the results there.
So that's all there is to it.
As far as the like operator something I also want you to be aware of is in this case this like operator
is case sensitive.
Postscripts sequel provides the I like operator the X. exactly like the like operator except it values
matches without case sensitivity.
So to show you an example of that let's say I knew the name started with a bar like Barry or Barbara
I could say I like so case insensitivity and then I could say all capitals BAR Are percent sign single
quote semi-colon here and run that.
And so you'll notice here if I edit this capitalization in any way.
So here is all caps.
So if I say B lowercase a uppercase R and run that I'm going to get the same results.
However if I did that just using like in Iran that I wouldn't get anything back because like by itself
is case sensitive.
But I can use.
I like for case insensitivity.
So just keep that in mind.
All right.
So later on we're going to get some practice of some challenges to really focus your understanding of
the underscore in the percent sign.
So like really goes hand in hand with percent sign and underscore those wild card or card operators
.
She should always be keeping them in mind when you see something like the like statements.
OK.
Thanks everyone.
And I'm excited for you to tackle the challenges coming up next.
I'll see you at the next lecture