Hello everyone and welcome to your first general challenge lecture.
So I'm really excited for you to take on this first general challenge because the general challenge
tests are going to utilize all the skills that you've learned so far you'll receive the general challenge
task and you'll get hence the challenge and then the solution to the challenge.
These challenges are going to be a little more difficult than what you've seen earlier.
So try breaking down the problem into individual tasks in order to solve the task completely.
So let's go ahead and get started.
Your first challenge and business task that I want to answer is this.
How many payment transactions were greater than $5.
Again just what's the number that count of how many payment transactions were greater than $5.
OK.
Coming up next are the hints.
So go ahead and puzzle video.
Now if you want to see the hints here.
Moving on to the hints so you'll have to use the payments table.
And you'll also need to use count and aware along with some sort of comparison operator in order to
distinguish what's greater than $5 so just keep that in mind.
OK.
Coming up next is the solution.
So the solution is actually pretty straightforward.
You want to select counts amounts from the payment table where the amount is greater than five.
So let's take it a couple of concepts.
Just a general concept of selecting from that very first thing we learn then the concept of counting
the amount column and then using where along of some sort of comparison operator to filter out which
amounts we were looking for.
So again that was select the counts amount column from payment table were amounts greater than 5 member
to put that semi-colon in to end your query.
Okay.
Next Business Teske how many actors have a first name that starts with the letter p.
Again how many actors have a first name that starts with the letter P.
OK.
Coming up next is a hint.
So go ahead impassivity enough you know incident hints yet.
OK here comes the hints so you'll need to use the actor table order to answer his question.
And you'll also need to use the like statements and some sort of wild card operator such as the percent
sign or the underscore.
So go ahead and review the like lecture.
If you need any refreshment or a refresher on how to use that percent or underscore wild card operators
OK.
Coming up next is the solution to this challenge.
So here it comes.
So the solution is select count.
In this case I'm just selecting all the rows you can see and asterisks here and this because I just
want to count basically all the rows from actor where the first name column is like.
And this is where it gets a little tricky to say like a single quote.
Capital P.
Percent sign Cup quote.
And that's because what's going to happen here is you're going to say select the count asterisks meaning
just count all the rows from actor where your first underscore name column is like the percent sign
.
Meaning where the value of first thing columns starts for P..
OK so go ahead and review that solution makes you type it out yourself in case you're able to get it
.
But coming up next is one other challenge task.
So here it comes.
OK your next challenge is how many unique districts are our customers from.
That's how many unique districts are our customers from.
OK coming up next are some hints on how to solve the challenge.
So here comes the hint slide so you'll need to use the address table and you'll also need to use counts
and distinct So go ahead review the distinct lecture in case you don't remember how to use distinct
but you'll need that in order to solve the challenge which was how many unique districts are our customers
from.
OK so coming up next is the solution.
So go ahead and posit it enough you want to see the solution yet.
OK here comes a solution for it.
So the solution was to select count distinct district from address.
So this is going to basically do this is going to say select and if we start from the inside here it's
going to grab all the distinct districts.
So that means if you have for instance a district called Alberta if you have it several times throughout
that column so several rows have the value of Alberta in that the district column what the stink is
going to do is just select all the unique ones.
So it means Ill just filter it down to Alberta only shows up once or that particular district only shows
up once and then what count is going to do just counts all those distinct districts and that's basically
going to give you the answer of how many districts or unique districts other customers from and you
have to get that from the address table.
OK so one more challenge.
I want you to retrieve the list of names for those distinct districts from the previous question.
So this is going to be a really similar question.
I just want to make sure you really flesh out your understanding fully and just retrieve the list of
names for those distinct districts from the previous question.
OK here comes the hints.
So again you need to use the address table and really strong hint this is going to be very similar to
the previous challenge solution.
So it's really only editing.
Basically one word.
OK so hopefully you can get it.
But if you don't go ahead and posit video now try to get it.
And now we're going to this solution.
So here comes a solution for it.
The solution is to basically just remove that count.
So if you just say Select Distinct district from address you won't get the actual number count.
You'll just get that list of the distinct districts that the customers are from.
OK hopefully you're able to get that.
Another challenge here is how many films have a rating of R and a replacement costs between $5 and $15
.
That's how many films have a rating of R and the replacement costs between $5 and $15.
OK go ahead impassivity.
Now try to solve this challenge on your own using your siecle querying skills.
And up next are some hints on how to solve this challenge.
Ok here comes the hints.
So the hint is you'll need to use the film table and you may also need to use between and a where statement
with some sort of comparison operator in order to solve that issue of between the $515.
Hopefully the word between earlier was a clue for you too.
In order for you to figure that out on your own.
OK so those are hints.
Go ahead impassivity enough you want to attempt the problem on your own.
But coming up next is the solution.
Ok here comes a solution.
So the solution was to select count Asterix so just select the count of all the rows from film where
the rating is equal to that string are a single Co.
Our single quote and replacement underscore cost column is between 5 and 15.
Notice I don't have to put strings between 5 and 15 because they're both just numeric data types.
OK so let's go to break this down a little further.
Sometimes it confuses people why you have to just select count as tricks here.
It's sort of like title or something.
And that's because splicing count Asterix you're basically just saying count the number of rows returned
which makes sense because it doesn't matter what column you select.
You're still going to be counting the same number of rows there.
So you're saying just select the count of the number of rows from film that get returns when you select
.
The rating is equal to r and the replacement cost has b between 5 and 15 dollars.
OK so another challenge.
This one's going to be maybe a little trickier.
Testing your pattern matching skills.
How many films have the word Treumann somewhere in the title.
That's how many films have the word Treumann somewhere in the title.
OK so coming up next are some hints.
Go ahead and posit that you enough and want to see those hints yet here comes the hints so you'll need
to use the film table to solve this and you'll also need to use like we have some sort of wild card
operator.
So again you can review the like lecture in order to get an understanding of how to use those wild card
operators in case you've forgotten.
All right.
I mean up next is the solution.
Here it comes.
So the solution is to select count Asterix.
Again we just want to select the count of the number of rows returned from film where the title column
is like.
And this is where maybe it is a little tricky for you.
But remember the question asked if we just go back to sleights here.
It asked how many films of the word Treumann somewhere in the title.
So not at the beginning not the end just anywhere in the title and that means we had to use the wildcard
operators on both ends of Treumann meaning any number of characters or any sequence of characters can
come before Truman.
And that includes spaces and any sequence characters can come after Truman.
OK so that was the solution.
So select count Asterix from film where the title is like and then single quote.
Percent sign Treumann percent sign.
Single quote semi-colons.
And that query.
All right great job.
Hopefully you found those challenges.
Straightforward a little tricky but not too hard.
This should have been pretty basic.
Well we're going to learn from now on is going to really up your skill level in school learn how to
do joints in group bhai's which are some really powerful sequel statements and that will really take
you to much more professional level understanding of sequel and the ability to use postgresql database
in order to do some real professional queries.
OK thanks everyone.
Hope you enjoy those challenges and I will see you at the next lecture.
Thanks