Hello everyone.
Welcome to your first assessment test.
You've actually had a lot of challenges along the way so this isn't going to be a very long assessment
test section is going to be three quick questions and it's also going to be an article lecture format
so you won't see any videos.
You'll just get the actual text of the question you're going to be provided with the answers to test
against.
So for instance if the question is something like tell me how many customers do X Y and Z you'll also
be provided with the answer and I'll say something like the answer should be 20.
You won't actually be provided with the full sequel solution until the lecture after the test lecture
again.
So the next lecture you're going to questions and then some answers.
Check your work against.
And then once you've actually matched up or you still haven't been able to match up to the exact answer
you can go to that lecture after that to get the full sequel query solution.
Keep in mind you may have done SQL queries that are slightly different.
There's a couple of different ways to solve each of the questions.
So as long as you actually get the right answer you should be good to go.
OK.
Thanks everyone.
And best of luck on the assessment test.