Hello everyone and welcome to databases and tables in this section we're going to focus on creating
and restoring databases and make heavy use of PGE admin that graphical user interface or GeoEye that
we previously installed Peachi admin is a great tool and it's going to save you a lot of time for these
specific types of tasks.
Restoring a database or creating a new database etc. later on we're going to learn more about direct
sequel's syntax like selector.
Order by where that kind of thing.
So don't worry too much about focusing on the sequel syntax right now.
In this particular section we're just going to use PGE admen so that you feel comfortable in creating
and restoring databases.
In case you ever want to create a restore database to practice your sequel syntax queries later on.
So it's important that we get this down really well first before we actually move into the learning
style Rexx sequel syntax and programming queries out.
So don't worry that's all coming but we're going to focus right now on PGE admen see feel comfortable
creating restoring databases with all that being said let's go ahead and get started.
I'll see you at the next lecture