Hello everyone and welcome to the creating and restoring a database lecture in this lecture we're going
to do is create a base with the P.G. admin graphical user interface for UI console and then we're going
to restore a database and learn how to delete a database.
Something to note here is basically when we were installing the original DVD rental database we were
kind of doing it especially for the Windows installation through a very manual command line process
.
We're going to do now show you how you would actually probably do this if you were implementing post
sequel at work.
You would just use the PGE admin Council and save yourself a lot of time.
So let's go ahead and jump to the PGI item and console.
OK.
So I'm here at the PGE adamant console and what I have is DVD rental and postscripts remember a DVD
rental was our first installation of the sample database.
We're going to do now show you how you can do it basically much quicker and much simpler using the PGE
oddment 3 console which again is on databases right click and select menu database and then go ahead
and name your database.
We'll call this DVD to then click OK.
Now you'll notice that we have the DVD to database created for us member last time we had a use a sequel
query and we said create space database and then the name of the database of a semi-colon.
Here we just did it by the right click with the GeoEye console.
So just to show you a reminder of how we did it last time member I selected postscripts and then I selected
sequel to execute a sequel query brought up my sequel editor and the way you would do this in pure sequel
you would say creates database and the name of your database which you could say let's say test DVD
and then call semi colon and to let it know that stay on the line that's all you want to write.
And then we'll click Run quick return successfully.
This is exactly the last time.
And then on databases if we just hit refresh.
Now we have a new test DVD data database so it's up to you what you prefer.
I would imagine most people just like the right click of creating a database so let's go over how to
delete a database we'll do the test DVD right now.
The most convenient way to do it using PGE admin is right click select Delete drop and then we'll go
ahead and just drop that database.
All right.
So we have DVD rental and DVD to DVD rentals already filled.
We go to schemers and public Inori has the tables for the actual database which we did in a very manual
way.
Now let's see if we can do that in a little bit of a nicer way to DVD too.
So if we look at the schemas the public schemas for really DVD to notice we don't have any tables or
anything right now so because we haven't actually populated this database with any information.
So let's go ahead and use PGE admen in order to do that.
What you're going to do is go ahead and Right-Click DVD 2 and go ahead and click restore.
So restore is going to allow us to actually search for that tar file.
So if you click these three dots you'll get a pop up if you remember from the Windows installation video
for the DVD rental database.
I had my tar file in this folder under computer OAC Program Files postscripts sequel.
You may still have it under the downloads folder but notice I don't actually see it.
I just see that nine point five folders.
So if you remember having that tar file over here the reason it's not showing up is because right now
we're exclusively looking for backup files.
So I don't want to say look for all files and now I can see that the tar file right there and I can
click open and then just click restore and it will take a little bit of time but it will restore everything
and basically fill out all those tables.
Select done.
Let's go ahead and then refresh DVD to database and I'll notice it has all the same tables as the original
DVD rental where we did this manually with the command line.
All right so now you know basically two ways of creating and restoring databases.
The first is the more manual way when we basically walk through the installation of DVD rental.
The second one is kind of the nicer way with the GeoEye.
So right clicking on database's say new databases once you've created the new database you can right
click and save restore.
OK.
So that's fully restoring a database of all the information well we're going to do.
Next is learn how to restore a database with just the table schema meaning we just want the tables and
everything set up all the relationships.
But you don't actually want the data information there.
That's a little bit trickier.
So we'll cover in the next lecture.
All right let's go ahead and do a quick review of what we just did.
OK.
So just a quick overview we learn how to create a database with PGE admin using the graphical user interface
specifically learn how to use it also restore a database and delete a database member just using a right
clicking and those dropdown menu.
So that makes it very easy.
So now you kind of have two ideas of how to create and restore databases.
I think you'll agree with me that the second one using the GeoEye is quite a bit easier.
I'll save you a lot of time.
Up next we're going to learn how to restore just the table schema so you can imagine that maybe you
are opening up a new DVD rental store so you want to restore a new database with all the same table
schema both no data because you're opening up a new DVD rental store and now you want to set up a database
have it empty so you can later on add stuff to it.
OK.
So that will be up in the next lecture.
Thanks and I'll see you there.