Hello everyone and welcome to the overview of challenges lecture.
So throughout this course you're going to be receiving challenges and these challenges are going to
allow you to test your understanding of postscripts and basic and more advanced sequel commands as you
go throughout the course.
The basis of these challenge scenarios will be that you've just been hired as a sequel consultant for
a DVD rental store.
So that's going to be the basic background as we give you challenges throughout the course.
So as far as solutions to the challenges challenges are going to start off very simple and basically
be asking you to repeat what you just saw in the previous lecture.
So don't worry if you're finding challenges to be very very basic at the beginning because that's how
they are.
Later on you're going to be provided with solutions or walk through video solutions for the tougher
challenges.
So at first the challenges are going to start off simple and ask you to repeat what you just saw in
the previous lecture and there's not going to be a specific solution to that challenge because you can
just reference the previous lecture later on the as it challenges get harder you'll need to be provided
with the solutions at the next lecture after the challenge lecture or we'll have a whole walk through
video in case it's a very difficult challenge.
Keep in mind that challenges may show up unannounced.
So always be ready for them with all that being said I hope you enjoy these challenges.
And I really hope you do them.
They're going to be a great way for you to get a chance to test your understanding and test out your
sequel knowledge on the example database as we go along through the course.
OK.
With that all being said I will see you at the next lecture.
Thanks everyone.