Hello everyone and welcome to your first surprise challenge and in this challenge your scenario is this
.
There was an accident in the server room and someone spilled some soft drink on the server causing it
to go down and that server contained the database.
Luckily you're around to restore that database that you saved as a zip file.
So your challenge is to restore the DVD rental database given the DVD rental but zip file.
As for the solution you can reference to previous video lecture for the solution.
Again you're basically just going to be repeating the exact same process we just did in the previous
lecture on your own.
All right thanks everyone and I'll see you at the next lecture.
And best of luck on the challenge.