Hello everyone and welcome to this lecture on restoring a database table schema only.
So in this structure we're going to learn how to restore a database but with only the table schema and
the table schema is the table names and the data types step along in that table but doesn't actually
contain any data.
So there's actually a really common tasks that you should know well and the reason for that being is
if you ever find yourself needing in a real world situation to put the database schema somewhere else
you don't want to actually copy over the data either because you're going to be filling it out with
new data or because you have privacy concerns where the information in that data in your original database
is private.
And if you're gonna copy that database schema over to a development server you don't actually want to
copy private user information into your new database.
So that's why this is actually such a common task and PGE Atman is actually going to make it really
easy.
So let's go ahead and jump to P.G. Addleman now.
So I'm going to go ahead and get started by opening up PGE admen.
OK so hearing him at PGE admin terminal or window if you will.
And you'll notice I right now have three databases.
Given the previous stuff that we set up I want to see two things in two different ways that you could
do the sort of restore.
One is to restore it into a database that already has the data.
So go ahead and expand DVD rental schemas public.
You'll notice that I have the 15 tables and if I were to click on one of these individual tables and
look over rows the estimates that there's about 200 rows there.
So there is actual data in this.
And if you double click this you can then begin to explore the columns etc..
So this table excuse me this database of DVD rental has all the tables and that has all the data.
So keep that in mind.
Something to do first is create a new database so I can do that either through the command line or simply
by right clicking on databases and saying new database.
And I will name this data base.
Let's just say only schema now will say okay let it go ahead and create that database.
All right so now I have my only schema database.
And you notice if I check the public schemas I don't have any tables here.
So what I'm going to do is to take full advantage of PGE admin here and right click and say restore
.
So this whole process should look familiar to you but since this is the first way when we restored and
created a full database I have my format equal to custom or tar and I have my file name which is that
DVD rental that tar file.
So here's the link to where my file is.
Go ahead and make sure the file path towards yours is is correct.
Or you can click on these three dots to continue exploring.
So the caveat here being I don't actually want to copy the entire data.
I just want to copy the table schema.
So how do I do that.
I can go to restore options number one.
And you'll see here and there type of objects.
Ill say only schema and that's exactly what I want to do.
So I want to make sure I click that.
So I don't actually take in any of that data and if I click restore and wait a little bit while it works
you'll notice it says Process return X code zero meaning everything worked out.
If I click done we should hopefully we make sure we refresh this order and looks good.
You'll see I have tables here.
So under my only schema database I was able to restore those tables and let's make sure it actually
worked by selecting the actress table.
And now you'll notice I have zero rows so I've copied and restored all the table schema including the
columns of the type set it's expecting.
But the actual data is no longer there.
So it has no rows of data.
It just has the table schema that it expects.
Okay.
So that's how you would do that if you were creating a new database for that table schema only restore
.
Now let's say I wanted to restore onto an existing database that already had the data.
So for example my DVD rental database here I go to tables.
Remember if I check actor it already has 200 rows of that data.
So how could I restore this database that it only has the schema essentially just get rid of all that
data but keep the table schema.
Well I can do that in a really similar manner.
I right click DVD rental click restore.
Wait for it to load.
I'm going to restore it again from that tar file under restore options.
Number one I'm going to say only schema and this is where you have to remember the additional step.
If your database still contains data you're going to go to restore options.
Number two you know what you're going to do is say clean before restore.
And that's essentially just going to clean away any data that is currently in that database before you
restore it.
That way you don't accidentally retain the data and you only pass in the data schema or the table schema
excuse me.
So let's go ahead and restore this and make sure all worked.
Go ahead and give it some time.
Looks like it finished a slick done.
And now if I go ahead and refresh this DVD rental I go to all my tables.
I have all of them and if I check actor now you notice that the DVD rental database that previously
had all the data is now just containing that table schema.
So that relationship all the tables and the columns it's expecting with none of the actual rows of data
.
All right.
Perfect.
So that's how you can restore a database with just the table schema and no data along with it.
All right everyone thanks and I will see you with the next lecture