Hello everyone and welcome to another challenge in this challenge.
A new DVD rental stores opening and you've been assigned to create its database.
So what you have to do is create and restore a new database from DVD rental dot tar that tar file and
only restore the table schema as we just did in the previous lecture.
We don't want all of that data since this is a new DVD rental store so you can just basically imagine
that we just want to copy only the table schema from the DVD rental the tar into a new database.
OK.
With that being said if you want a solution you can reference the previous lecture.
Thanks everyone.
Best of luck on the challenge and I'll see at the next lecture.